[music] At night, around one in the morning, in a small provincial town with no particular name, a young man of about 27 or so
walks into a solitary wooden annex in the courtyard, to visit a civil engineer sitting on a sofa with a latticed back
and hard leather cushions, and almost immediately notices an untouched boiled chicken on a plate by the window. My name is Armen
Zakharyan, this is Armen and Fyodor’s literary channel, and today we’re launching a new segment: “Episode.” In it, each time, we’ll carefully
examine a single fragment from world literature and figure out why this episode is special and how what we call art
works within it. For our first attempt, we’ve chosen one of the most chilling, yet fascinating,
scenes from Dostoevsky’s novel The Devils. It’s an episode nearly at the very end of the book, from its concluding part. There, a certain Verkhovensky
comes at night to the home of a certain Kirillov and sees a boiled chicken with rice on the windowsill. And though there’s a loaded
pistol lying right next to the chicken, it’s not the pistol but the chicken that serves, in this scene, as the Chekhovian gun, which is about to go off. However,
to understand what this "shot" is, and at whom it’s aimed, we first need to figure out who these two are and how they ended up here, in the same room
at night, in the annex. Interestingly, even at the very beginning of the novel, as we’re just being introduced to the characters, Dostoevsky already lays
the groundwork for their eerie night encounter. Kirillov—he is a young man, around 27; Verkhovensky, almost symmetrically, a young
man, about 27 or so. This pointed similarity, of course, only accentuates how deep their differences lie. Kirillov is
a vivid representative of Dostoevsky’s famous string of fanatic heroes—heroes who become obsessed with an idea
and begin to serve that idea, to live for it alone. Only, Kirillov’s plan is different: in the name of his idea, he intends to die. Kirillov
is obsessed with the thought of “the man-god.” He comes to this through a problem that the literature of the second half of the 19th century
often tried to solve: how is one to live after rejecting God? Suppose God is no longer there. Suppose we no longer believe in Him,
We’ve, as Verkhovensky might put it, “decommissioned” him. And yet, the need to fill the void left in his place—it remains.
And while another Dostoevsky character, also in The Devils, says, “If there is no God, then what kind of captain am I after that?” Kirillov says,
“If there is no God, then I can take His place.” Remember Grebenshchikov sang, “You feel the draft because that place is vacant.”
Kirillov feels that very draft, and he formulates a terrifying, mad idea, with which he then falls in love: if
a person, he says, dares to affirm his will—to leave life not out of anger, nor fear, nor rage, but solely and precisely because
he has the right, then, Kirillov reasons, with this act he will transform all of humanity and himself become the man-god.
“But there have already been millions of suicides,” they tell him. “Not for that,” Kirillov replies; “all from fear, not for that!” And this
mad approach of his uncannily resembles an episode from Don Quixote. Remember, when the audacious hidalgo tells Sancho
he plans to imitate the great knights of the past and go mad? The pragmatic Sancho then asks, “But, sir, do you have a reason to go mad? What’s the reason?”
“That’s the whole point,” Don Quixote replies. “That’s exactly what’s unusual about my venture: who ever heard of a knight going mad for a reason?
Let there be no gratefulness nor reward involved; the trick is to go mad for no reason at all.”
And as we’ll soon see, these echoes in the words of Kirillov and Quixote are not accidental in the least.
So, to carry out his mad idea, Kirillov has a loaded revolver lying by the window, next to the chicken. You may ask, why is he waiting, then? Why isn’t he
carrying out his intention if, in fact, he needs no external reason? This is where his nighttime visitor comes into play:
the revolutionary and nihilist Pyotr Stepanovich Verkhovensky—a completely different sort of character, a fascinating hero, both ridiculous and terrifying,
comic and parodic, terrifyingly talkative and theatrical, but at the same time horrifying because he’s ready for any evil. Verkhovensky
in a way, is reminiscent of Mephistopheles, though Mephistopheles had a better sense of humor, and being older and more experienced in life, he was more modest. However, what matters is that they both
are ultimately divided: Verkhovensky is a thoroughly practical man.
He believes the ends justify any means. Upon hearing about Kirillov’s project of ideological suicide, Verkhovensky
immediately devises how this can be put to good use—not to transform humanity; he doesn’t care a bit about that,
but for his own devilish plan. He decides to commit a political murder, and since Kirillov absolutely doesn’t care how or when to die,
he asks Kirillov, before his suicide, to write a confession to this murder; in other words, to use Kirillov’s death as
an alibi for his own crime. So, that’s the situation at the time of their night meeting: a conflict between the spiritual—albeit sick—
but spiritual Don Quixote was also insane—and the material, between the elevated and the base, between the tragic and the pragmatic.
But how to show all this through a single image? Through the chicken. As often with Dostoevsky, the episode unfolds
rapidly: Verkhovensky has barely walked in, has just clarified, “Well, our intention is firm, I hope we’re not backing out of the suicide?”
“We’ll sign the paper.” And then, almost without a pause, he says, “Ah, I notice something there on the window. On the plate.” He walks over: “Oh! Boiled chicken
with rice. But why is it still untouched? So we’re in that frame of mind where even chicken—” Kirillov interrupts,
“It’s none of your business, be quiet.” “Oh, of course, and it makes no difference, but for me it does now. Imagine, I’ve hardly dined today, so if this chicken,
as I suppose, is not needed any more—” Note how Kirillov phrases his reply:
“Eat it, if you can.” Verkhovensky can. More than can—for himself and for someone else. “Thank you,” he says, “and tea afterwards too,”
and what follows is even more chilling, the cherry on top of the scene: Verkhovensky instantly makes himself comfortable at the table at the far end
of the sofa, and with extreme greed throws himself at the dish, but at the same time, every moment watches his victim. Kirillov, with furious
disgust, stares at him motionless, as if unable to tear himself away. Verkhovensky here is the triumph of the flesh—he eats greedily,
with appetite, with relish—for the man sitting a meter away is about to shoot himself, which means the chicken, too, is vacated. Notice: in this
one paragraph, Verkhovensky takes away from Kirillov everything: his freedom, his last will, his last meal, and at last,
his life. The chicken is, of course, only a metaphor, because in truth, Verkhovensky is a cannibal: people are only expendable
material to feed his pitiful ambitions and dreadful plans. Does mankind’s happiness justify a single tear of a child? Ivan Karamazov asks.
“And is the child with a garnish, or just by itself?” Pyotr clarifies. And Kirillov, this strange Kirillov—with his mad idea, but still
not an evil heart—cannot tear his gaze away. He watches in terror as Verkhovensky devours the chicken, because it is not only
the chicken he devours, but Kirillov himself—he is about to eat him. “Barabek gobbled forty men, a cow, an ox, a crooked butcher,
a cart, a hoop, a broom, a poker—he ate the chicken with garnish, finished with this world,” and all this tangle of contradictions, fears,
and fates, Dostoevsky shows in a single supper scene, through one plate of cold chicken with rice. The eloquent horror of this
gastronomic scene was brilliantly captured in the legendary production of The Devils at St. Petersburg’s Maly Drama Theatre, in
Lev Dodin’s six-hour play, staged for nearly thirty years. Those lucky enough to see it
surely remember Verkhovensky’s chicken scene. See it once live—it’s unforgettable. Here’s a fragment of how
this scene was played. This illustration, really, could have ended our discussion of today’s fragment, if not for
one detail: this opposition—refusal of food, gluttony as a metaphor for values conflict—can also be found
in a book Dostoevsky loved deeply, a book which influenced all his major works, a book which he said was the deepest and strongest in all the world,
and which we’ve mentioned today, of course—Cervantes's Don Quixote.
Remember how the relationship between Don Quixote and Sancho Panza is built in the first part—we spoke of it in one of the early episodes
of Armen and Fyodor devoted to this novel. Sancho is obsessed with food: he constantly reminds Quixote about eating; at every opportunity,
he strives to get his fill, regardless of what his master is experiencing at the moment—whether he preaches, fasts, or
suffers. And the great American director Orson Welles, in his Don Quixote— which, by a strange coincidence, would be released almost
alongside Dodin’s production—depicts a scene uncannily similar to that episode from The Devils: there, Sancho Panza, before the fasting Quixote’s very eyes,
will greedily devour—what do you think?—of course, a chicken. [music] [music]
I want this... that Marina will go… One can only clarify that in the spirit of Cervantes’s Don Quixote, this episode is true;
in the letter, not entirely—in the text of the novel, there was no such scene with a chicken exactly like this one.
However, this is easily explained: Cervantes didn’t read Dostoevsky, unlike Orson Welles. This is Armen and Fyodor’s literary channel,
and the “Episode” segment. I hope our experiment with this new laconic format was a success, and if so, please write
in the comments which other episodes you’d like to see in this segment in the future. For now, that’s it. My name is Armen Zakharyan,
until next time. [music]