[music] At night, sometime around one o’clock, in a small provincial town without a defined name
a young man, about 27 years old or so, enters a solitary wooden wing out in the yard—to visit
a construction engineer, who is sitting on a sofa with a latticed back and hard leather
cushions. Almost immediately, he notices a plate on the windowsill with an untouched boiled chicken
My name is Armen Zakharian, and this is Armen and Fyodor’s literary channel. Today we are launching a new section
called “Episode.” Each time, we’ll closely examine just one
fragment from the pages of world literature and analyze why this episode is special—
special, and how what we call “art” functions within it. For our first attempt at this,
we have chosen one of the most disturbing yet fascinating scenes from Dostoevsky’s novel “Demons.” It’s an episode almost
at the very end of the book, in its concluding part. There, a certain Verkhovensky comes by night to the house of
one Kirillov, and sees a chicken boiled with rice on the windowsill. And though right next to the chicken lies
a loaded pistol, in this scene it is not the gun, but the chicken that plays the role of Chekhov’s gun, which is about
to go off. But to understand what this shot is, and at whom it’s aimed, we need to
first figure out who these two are, and how the two of them ended up here, together in the wing, at night,
in the same room. It’s remarkable how, even at the very beginning of the book, just as he introduces the characters,
Dostoevsky is already paving the way for this horrific nighttime encounter between them. Kirillov—a young man, about 27,
Verkhovensky—almost a mirror image, a young man of about 27 or so. This deliberate similarity, of course,
only underscores how deep the differences between them run. Kirillov is a vivid representative of that famous line of Dostoevsky’s fanatics,
heroes who become passionately obsessed with some idea, start serving this idea, living for
this idea. Only Kirillov’s plan is different—he intends, in the name of his idea, to die. Kirillov is obsessed with the notion of the God-man.
He arrives at it by pondering the dilemma that the literature of this period, the second half
of the nineteenth century, often struggled to resolve: how can one live after rejecting God? Suppose God no longer exists. Suppose we
no longer believe in him. We, to use Verkhovensky’s term, have “written him off.” But the need to fill
the emptiness left in his place—that need remains. And while another Dostoevsky character, in the same
“Demons,” says: “If there is no God, then what kind of captain am I?”, Kirillov says,
If there is no God, then I can take his place. Remember how Grebenshchikov sang: “You feel
the draft from the vacancy in that place.” Kirillov feels just that very draft
and formulates a terrible, insane thought—a thought he then falls in love with. “If
a person,” he says, “resolves of his own will, for no reason—not out of anger,
not out of fear, not out of malice, but solely and simply because he has the right—to depart from life,
then, Kirillov reasons, in taking this step he will regenerate all of humanity and himself become a God-man.
But there have already been millions of suicides, he’s told. “But none—none did it for this reason, not out of fear or for that purpose!” Kirillov retorts.
And this crazy logic of his strikingly recalls an episode from
“Don Quixote.” Remember, when the audacious, delusional Quixote tells Sancho Panza that
one should imitate the famous knights of the past and go mad. The pragmatic Sancho then asks: “But,
Señor, do you actually have a reason for going mad? What’s the reason?” — “Therein
lies the point,” Don Quixote answers. “That’s precisely the peculiarity of my
undertaking: whoever among the wandering knights went mad for some reason
—such a one does not merit reward nor thanks. The trick is to lose one’s mind without any reason at all.”
And as we’ll soon see, these parallels in the words of Kirillov and Quixote are far from accidental.
So, to fulfill his mad idea, Kirillov has a loaded revolver on the windowsill, next to the chicken.
You might ask: “So what is he waiting for? Why
doesn’t he carry out his intention, if, after all, he needs no reason for it?” Here is where his nighttime
visitor comes in—a revolutionary and nihilist, Pyotr Stepanovich Verkhovensky. This character
is completely different, an extraordinary figure—funny and terrifying at the same time,
comically and parodically, frighteningly loquacious and theatrical, but also terrifying, because he’s ready for any evil.
Verkhovensky, yes, to some extent resembles Mephistopheles, but Mephistopheles had a better sense of humor, and
by virtue of life experience and age, he was more restrained. But the most crucial thing is that they are fundamentally different. Verkhovensky
is a supremely practical person. He believes the end justifies any means, and
having encountered Kirillov with his ideological suicide project, Verkhovensky immediately
figures out how to put this to good use—not for the regeneration
of humanity—he couldn’t care less about that—but for his own demonic business. He decides
to carry out a political assassination—and since Kirillov is utterly indifferent to
when or how he dies, to have him write a confession to the murder before his death, thus using Kirillov’s death
as an alibi for his own crime. So, this is the setup
at the moment of their nocturnal meeting: a conflict of the spiritual (however sick; Don Quixote was mad, too)
and the material—a clash of the sublime and the base, the tragic and the pragmatic. But how do you convey all this
through a single image? With a chicken. This episode, as so often with Dostoevsky, unfolds
rapidly: Verkhovensky has just come in, has just clarified, “So—the intention
still stands? I hope the suicide is still on? The paper—you’ll sign?” And almost without
pausing, he immediately says: “Well! But I notice something over there, on the windowsill, on a plate.” He approaches
“Oh, a chicken boiled with rice! But why is it still untouched? So we’re
in such a state of mind we can’t even touch the chicken…” “I ate,” interrupts
Kirillov, “and it’s none of your business, be silent, of course, it doesn’t matter to me. But
for me, it’s not the same. Imagine, I’ve barely eaten dinner, and so now,
the chicken, I assume, is no longer needed…” Pay attention to how
Kirillov formulates his answer: “Eat, if you can.” Verkhovensky can—oh, he can,
both for himself and for the other guy. “Well, thank you,” he says, and then, “and tea!”
And then it gets even more chilling—the “cherry on the cake” of this scene. Verkhovensky immediately
settled at the table, at the other end of the sofa, and with extraordinary greed attacked the food, but at the same time
kept an eye every moment on his victim. Kirillov stared at him with angry disgust,
motionless, as if unable to break away. Verkhovensky here—he is the triumph of the flesh,
he eats greedily, with appetite, with excitement, as the man a meter away from him is about
to shoot himself—but that means the chicken is up for grabs, too. Note, in this one paragraph, Verkhovensky strips from Kirillov
absolutely everything: his freedom, his last will, his last meal, and, in the end, his life.
The chicken is, of course, just a metaphor, because in essence, Verkhovensky sees people as expendable resources,
matter that feeds his pitiful ambitions and schemes. “Is the happiness of mankind
worth the tear of a child?” asks Ivan Karamazov. “And is the child served with a side, or alone?” clarifies Pyotr
And Kirillov—this strange Kirillov, yes, with his insane idea, but still not an evil
heart—cannot look away. He watches in horror as Verkhovensky devours
the chicken, because he’s not eating only that—he’s also about to “eat” Kirillov
Verkhovensky—the Barabek: ate forty men and a cow, and a bull, and a crooked butcher,
and a cart, and a shaft, and a broom, and a poker, ate the chicken with a side and finished it off. And this whole tangle of contradictions, fears,
and destinies Dostoevsky reveals in a single scene of eating, through the image of a plate of cold chicken with rice.
The eloquent horror of this gastronomic scene was perfectly captured in the legendary
production of “Demons” by the Saint Petersburg Small Drama Theatre, in a six-hour
performance by Lev Dodin, which ran for almost thirty years. Anyone who was lucky enough to see this performance
can no doubt recall Verkhovensky’s scene with the chicken. Once you’ve seen it live,
it’s hard to forget. Here's a fragment of how this scene was played
This is an illustration. In fact, we could end the discussion of today’s
fragment here, if not for one detail. The point is, this contrast—refusal to eat versus gluttony as a metaphor
for value conflict—is found in a book Dostoevsky greatly
admired. A book that influenced all his major works, about which he
once said that nowhere in the world is there a work deeper or stronger. And finally, a book
we’ve already mentioned today—of course, Cervantes’s “Don Quixote.” Remember how
the relationship between Don Quixote and Sancho Panza is built in the first volume? We talked
about this in one of the early episodes of “Armen and Fyodor” dedicated to that novel. Sancho
is obsessed with food, constantly reminding Quixote about meals. At every opportunity, he tries to eat,
regardless of his master’s state—whether he's preaching, fasting, or suffering.
And the great American director Orson Welles, in his “Don Quixote,” which, by a
remarkable coincidence, will be released almost simultaneously with Dodin’s production, depicts a scene uncannily reminiscent of
this episode from “Demons”: there, Sancho Panza, before the fasting eyes of Quixote, will greedily devour
—what do you think? Of course—a chicken. [music] I want this, for Marina to
It only remains to clarify that in spirit, this episode completely matches Cervantes’s “Don Quixote,” but as for the letter—
not entirely: in the text of the novel, there’s no scene with chicken quite like this. Still,
in the end, it's easy to explain: Cervantes never read Dostoevsky, whereas Orson Welles did.
This is Armen and Fyodor’s literary channel and the “Episode” section. I hope our experiment with this new concise
format was a success. If so, please let us know in the comments which other
episodes you’d like to see in this section in the future. For now—that’s all. My name is Armen. Until next time! [music
.