[Music Playing]
One night, around 1 AM, in a small provincial city with no specified name, a young man about 27 years old or so enters a solitary wooden annex, visiting a construction engineer.
Sitting on a sofa with a latticed back and hard leather cushions, he almost immediately notices a plate with an untouched boiled chicken on the window.
My name is Armen Zakharian, and this is the literary channel Armen and Fyodor.
Today, we are launching a new segment called "Episode." In it, we will closely examine a single fragment from the pages of world literature each time and analyze why this episode is special and how art works within it.
For our first experiment, we have chosen one of the most eerie yet intriguing scenes from Fyodor Dostoevsky's novel "Demons."
This episode is near the very end of the book, from its concluding part. Here, someone named Verkhovensky arrives at night at Kirillov's house and sees a boiled chicken with rice on the window.
Although there is a loaded gun lying right next to the chicken, it is not the gun, but the chicken that plays the role of Chekhov's gun, ready to "go off."
However, to understand the shot and its target, one must first figure out who these two are and how they ended up here, together in one room at night in the annex.
Interestingly, Dostoevsky prepares the ground for this eerie nocturnal encounter already at the very beginning of the book, just as he introduces us to the characters.
Kirillov is a young man of about 27. Verkhovensky mirrors him—also a young man of approximately 27 years.
This deliberate similarity only underscores the deep differences between them.
Kirillov is a vivid representative of Dostoevsky's famous lineup of fanatic heroes—characters too passionately absorbed by an idea, living and serving it.
However, Kirillov has a different plan: he intends to die for an idea.
Kirillov is obsessed with the notion of the "man-god." He approaches this idea through a question typical of 19th-century literature: how to live after renouncing God?
Suppose God no longer exists.
Suppose we no longer believe in Him, as Verkhovensky might put it, we've "decommissioned" Him.
But the need to fill the void in His place remains.
And while another Dostoevsky character in the same "Demons" remarks, "If there is no God, then what kind of captain am I?"
Kirillov says, "If there is no God, then I can take His place."
Remember, Grebenshchikov sang, "You feel a draft because this place is vacant." Kirillov senses that very draft and formulates a dreadful, insane thought, in which he himself then falls in love.
If a man, he argues, decides to end his life not out of anger, fear, or malice, but merely because he has the right, he will transform all of humanity with this step and become a man-god.
But there have already been millions of suicides, they tell him.
"But not for this reason, all with fear and not for this," Kirillov replies.
This insane approach of his bears an amazing resemblance to an episode from "Don Quixote."
Remember when the bold hidalgo tells Sancho Panza that he plans to mimic the glorious knights of the past and go mad?
The pragmatic Sancho then asks, "But do you have a reason to go mad, Señor? What is the reason?"
"That's the point," Don Quixote replies, "the uniqueness of my endeavor is precisely in going mad without any reason."
As we will soon observe, the echoes in the words of Kirillov and Quixote are not accidental.
To implement his mad idea, Kirillov has a loaded revolver on the window next to the chicken.
You might ask: then what is he waiting for, why doesn't he carry out his intention if he doesn't need a reason for it?
This is where his nighttime visitor, the revolutionary and nihilist Pyotr Stepanovich Verkhovensky, comes into play.
This character is entirely different—an extraordinary hero, both funny and terrifying, comical to the point of parody, talkative and theatrical.
Yet terrifying because he is prepared for any evil.
Verkhovensky resembles Mephistopheles in some ways, though Mephistopheles had a better sense of humor.
And due to life experience and age, he was more modest.
The main thing they share: Verkhovensky is an extremely practical person.
He believes that the end justifies any means. Intervening with the intriguing project of ideological suicide, Verkhovensky immediately thinks of how it can serve his cause.
Not for a rebirth of humanity, he doesn't believe in that at all, but for his diabolical business.
He decides to commit a political murder, and since Kirillov doesn't care when or how to die, he asks him to write a confession for this murder before his death.
In other words, to use Kirillov's death as an alibi for his crime.
Thus, at the moment of their nocturnal meeting, we have a conflict of the spiritual—and though sick, Don Quixote was also mad—and the material;
the conflict of the elevated and the grounding, the tragic and the pragmatic.
But how to show this through a single image?
With the help of a chicken. The episode, as is often the case with Dostoevsky, unfolds rapidly.
Verkhovensky has just entered, has just clarified: "Our intentions remain valid? I hope we are not backing down from suicide, we will sign the paper?" and almost without
pause, suddenly, he notices something on the window, on the plate.
He approaches the window. Wow, a boiled chicken with rice, but why is it still untouched?
"We're in such a state of mind that even the chicken..." -- "I ate!" Kirillov interrupts him.
"It's none of your business, be silent!" -- "Of course, and besides, it's all the same to you now".
"But to me, it's not the same, you see. Imagine, I've hardly had lunch, so if the chicken is now, I assume, not needed anymore..."
Pay attention to how Kirillov formulates his response: "Eat, if you can."
Verkhovensky can, oh he can, for himself and for that guy.
"Thank you," he says, and then: "and some tea." And something even creepier follows, the worm in the cherry on the top of this scene.
Verkhovensky readily settled at the table on the other end of the sofa and with extreme greed attacked the meal, yet watched his victim every moment.
Kirillov looked at him with angry disgust, motionless, as if unable to tear himself away.
Verkhovensky represents the triumph of the flesh here; he eats greedily, with appetite, with fervor.
After all, the person sitting a meter from him is about to shoot himself, but the chicken is therefore up for grabs.
Notice, in just this paragraph, Verkhovensky takes away everything from Kirillov: his freedom, his last will, his last meal, and finally, his life.
The chicken is, of course, only a metaphor, because in essence, Verkhovensky is a cannibal; people to him are expendable material, feeding his petty ambitions and plans.
Is the happiness of mankind worth a child's tear? — asks Ivan Karamazov.
“A child with garnish or just plain?” Verkhovensky clarifies.
And Kirillov, this strange Kirillov, yes with his insane idea, but still with an unmalicious heart, can't tear himself away, he watches in horror as Verkhovensky
eats the chicken. Because he's eating not just it but also him, Kirillov, right now.
"Verkhovensky-Barabek munched a man and didn’t look back. Forty more, then cow and bull, butcher bent and belly full; cart and hoop and broom and vice, poker, mop, and boiled rice. Chicken too — with rice precise — and then, he chewed up paradise."
And all this tangle of contradictions, fears, and fates Dostoevsky shows through one dining scene, through one plate of cold chicken with rice.
The eloquent horror of this gastronomic scene was very accurately captured in the legendary production of "Demons" by the St. Petersburg Maly Drama Theater in a six-hour
performance by Lev Dodin, which played on stage for almost 30 years.
Those who were lucky enough to attend this performance surely remember the scene with Verkhovensky’s chicken.
Having seen this once live, it’s hard to forget. So take a look at a fragment of how this scene was played.
We could end the discussion of today's fragment here if it weren't for one detail.
that this juxtaposition of refusal from food—gluttony, as a metaphor for a value conflict, appeared in one book which
Dostoevsky greatly cherished, a book that influenced all of his main texts, a book he said had no equal in the world in depth or strengh.
Finally, the book that we mentioned today—of course, "Don Quixote" by Cervantes.
Remember how the relationship between Don Quixote and Sancho Panza is structured in the first volume. We spoke about this in one of the early episodes of "Armen and Fedor" dedicated to this novel.
Sancho is fixated on food, he constantly reminds Quixote about it, and at every opportunity, he strives to eat, regardless of whether his master is sermonizing, fasting, or suffering.
And the great American director Orson Welles, in his "Don Quixote," which coincidentally will be released nearly simultaneously with Dodin's play,
will depict a scene painfully reminiscent of this episode from "Demons." There, Sancho Panza will be greedily devouring, in the presence of a fasting Quixote, what do you think? Of course, a chicken.
It remains only to note that while this episode corresponds quite well to the spirit of Cervantes' Don Quixote, it does not fully match the text.
In the novel's text, there was no such chicken scene.
However, after all, it is easily explained: Cervantes did not read Dostoevsky, unlike Orson Welles.
This is the literary channel of Armen and Fyodor, the "Episode" segment.
I hope the experiment with this new concise format was successful, and if so, write to us in the comments what other episodes you would like to see in this segment in the future.
Meanwhile, that's all. My name is Armen Zakharian. Until next time.
[Music Playing]