[Music] Before we begin, it seems right to make a certain digression.
Today's discussion was born from an unrealized debate with many Russian philologists, translators, and literary critics who are accustomed to placing Don Quixote and Odysseus side by side, discussing them in the same breath
as cunning wanderers. It seems to me that such a comparison is not only superficial, but it belongs to a type of comparison that can offend and outrage both participants simultaneously.
As if to say, how can I possibly be compared with that? It's like comparing Brodsky with Yevtushenko or Nabokov with Dostoevsky. Of course,
Odysseus and Quixote are fated to be placed side by side because they embody the two main journeys of European literature. However, in their case, beneath the unity of form hides the opposition of content.
Don Quixote is not merely an heir or incarnation of Odysseus: Don Quixote is, in almost every way, the anti-Odysseus. This is precisely what we'll talk about today. My name is Armen Zaharyan, and you are with "Armen and Fedor", a literature-centric channel. Here
in our close circle of Quixotists and Odysseopaths today, we will encounter
real magic as we try to transport ourselves to the only place where they could possibly meet and imagine what that meeting would be like.
Previously, I have discussed each of them separately: the channel has episodes on what it means to be Odysseus and what it means to be Don Quixote. So if you want to get the maximum aesthetic pleasure from our conversation today, I recommend listening to those first.
So, Don Quixote and Odysseus. It would be a mistake to deny that there are obvious signs that unite them. They are both warriors. Odysseus is a king,
a leader of an army under Troy, Don Quixote is a knight. Both constantly find themselves in difficult situations and seek a way out. Both are active heroes, they
refuse to accept the status quo, they influence the surrounding world. Finally, both have been dubbed ingenious, but this coincidence only occurs in their Russian incarnations. In Quixote's native language
he is "Ingenioso Hidalgo", ingenious, while Odysseus, even in the text of Quixote, is prudente — prudent. In other words, all these coincidences
are no more than similarities of costume. The main thing that unites Odysseus and Don Quixote is wandering, being in constant motion. But it is from this similarity that their essential differences begin. Do you know why
the famous hobbit Bilbo Baggins from Tolkien's tale cannot be placed alongside Odysseus and Quixote? Because his story is a there-and-back-again.
Don Quixote is only "there," Odysseus is "back". The entire meaning of Odysseus's journey is the return home, what the Greeks called "νόστος". The essence
The essence of Quixote's movement is the opposite: he seeks to break away from home, to emerge into the world, to go as far as possible. In this sense, Don Quixote chooses what those same Greeks called "κοῖλος", and opposed it to nostos (return). Thus, Odysseus and Quixote both move
in opposite directions. Hence, from the very start, they are turned toward each other with equal force of movement but different vectors of its application. They draw near. However,
if Don Quixote gallops from point A to point B, while Odysseus at the same time sets sail from point B to point A, what will happen? Sooner or later they will meet. And we even know where, but that will come later.
For now, at the very start, at the maximum distance from each other, Quixote and Odysseus most closely resemble each other: they both sit in detention. One on the island of the nymph Calypso, the other in his home reading endless knightly novels. However, even
the type of their imprisonment is already distinct: Odysseus is weary in body, Don Quixote in mind. Thus,
as opposites, they are drawn towards each other; the closer they get, the fewer things they share. Don Quixote is extremely earnest
in everything he does, and therefore eternally amusing to others, and everyone laughs at him who finds the time. One of the characters will say, "The benefit of Quixote, his sagacity, cannot compare at all to the pleasure his follies provide."
Odysseus often makes jokes about others, but woe betide anyone who dares joke about him. Don Quixote is constantly beaten, pelted with stones, caged, and repeatedly thrashed, his face scratched, and in one scene nearly crucified.
Odysseus is invulnerable: he enters the cyclops' cave, navigates between Scylla and Charybdis, survives shipwreck, loses companion after companion, yet emerges from Poseidon's upheaval relatively unscathed. At crucial moments, no one manages to even strike him, let alone hit him. Don Quixote
is credulous, constantly deceived, eternally manipulated for public amusement. Odysseus is cautious and calculating, trusts no one; moreover, he deceives everyone, lies, feigns, evades, and mimics.
The naive Don Quixote will once say, "One cannot and should not call deception that which has a good purpose." For Odysseus, the end always justifies the means. Quixote
is self-assured and arrogant to a certain point,
completely devoid of doubt. Odysseus can be haughty, but overall he evaluates himself and his powers much more soberly, being prone to doubt.
From this sobriety of Odysseus and the arrogance of Quixote derives another difference: Odysseus is extremely grounded, Quixote is extremely lofty. He is, after all, a knight,
talking about honor, valor, and courage. Of course, his bravery often seems ludicrous, but he truly enters a cage with lions. Odysseus, however,
more often speaks of the stomach. In all of Homer's "Iliad," all the heroes collectively mention the tyranny of the stomach over people less frequently than does the sole Odysseus in his personal epic.
Every tirade about the stomach begins with the suffering, which, of course, is awful, and ends with the fact that there's nothing baser than our horrid stomach, and it wouldn't be bad to have a snack.
The main irony of this comparison, of course, is that Odysseus here is not just the anti-Quixote, who fasts and eats wild acorns. Odysseus here is the spitting image of Sancho Panza.
Don Quixote is a very poor strategist; as a commander, he is a real disaster: under his command, Sancho, who dreamed of becoming a governor, becomes a laughing stock. Odysseus
is charismatic, calculating, and cruel. Under such leadership, even death is glorious. Odysseus is wise, Don Quixote is mad,
Odysseus is king, Quixote is a holy fool, Odysseus an Old Testament avenging god, Quixote a New Testament Christ. [Music]
Thus, being complete opposites, they converge at one point. We were not warned about this in school textbooks, but the route from A to B and back passes through the underworld. Both Odysseus and Don Quixote
descend into the afterlife, and this, of course, is the only possible meeting point along their routes.
For Odysseus, it is a descent into the realm of the dead; for Don Quixote, it is a descent into the cave of Montesinos. But even in this, the heroes remain true to themselves: Odysseus goes to Hades out of necessity,
because no other means for achieving his goal is offered to him. When he learns of the need to go to the underworld, Homer's description of his reaction is this: "He rolled in bed for a long time and wept," and his first question post-sobbing was, "And who will guide me there?" Don Quixote
descends into Montesinos' cave voluntarily, without accompaniment or preliminary conditions, because Quixote fancies himself a hero, and a hero is destined for trials.
Just before the descent, he notices that he and Sancho forgot to take a bell, with which they could signal upwards, an excellent excuse to postpone the adventure, but knights don't retreat; the meeting has to happen, and Quixote descends into the cave. And then the most terrifying thing happens —
Odysseus isn't there. They have arrived. By all accounts, the logic of events, the inheritance of heroic experience - he should have been there. But Odysseus is a practical man: he
goes to the realm of the dead for a prophecy from the seer Tiresias. The madman Quixote — he is of no interest.
At the bottom of the damp cave in utter darkness, the knight remains alone. It is then that he encounters his own disbelief, his own madness. Standing in
the cave, he ponders: if Odysseus isn't here, then perhaps all the rest — castles and giants, princesses and islands — never existed either.
At this point of intersection in their paths in the afterlife, Odysseus boldly sets sail towards new challenges, having left the most terrifying behind.
For him, nothing has changed since Hades for Odysseus is material, and the most rational thing now is simply to continue adhering to his plan, so as not to have to, Heaven forbid, climb into Hades a second time. But what is good for Odysseus, for Quixote means death. And
after passing this point of non-meeting, he begins to doubt, and among the tapestry of his imagination, patches of rationality begin to appear, lethal to a madman. Quixote now starts to tread in place, with mounting fear peering into himself.
His journey becomes a wandering through those corners of consciousness where he should never have gazed. Now their paths will never again intersect: each leaves their underworld renewed and goes their separate way. Ahead of Odysseus lie new
challenges, but afterwards — a triumphant return, a faithful wife, a loving son, and revenge on his enemies. Whereas
Don Quixote ends his journey as a knight who called himself reckless and daring, who spoke of himself: "I defended the downtrodden and straightened wrongs, punished audacity, convinced giants, and trampled monsters, and there is no feat beyond human capabilities that I have not accomplished."
This daring madman will end his journey with perhaps the saddest assessment he could come to: "I do not know for sure if I am good, I can only say that I am not bad either."
Armen Zaharyan was with you. Until next time.
[Music]