[Music] Before starting, it seems appropriate to make a brief digression.
Today's discussion arose from a missed debate with many Russian philologists, translators, and literary scholars who are accustomed to equating Don Quixote with Odysseus, discussing them through
the lens of cunning wanderers. I perceive such a comparison as not only superficial but also as one that may offend and upset both participants at once.
As if to say, how can anyone compare me with that? It's like comparing Brodsky with Yevtushenko or Nabokov with Dostoevsky. Of course,
Odysseus and Quixote are doomed to be placed side by side because they embody two primary journeys of European literature. However, in their case, the unity of form hides a content contrast.
Don Quixote is not merely a successor or reincarnation of Odysseus: Don Quixote is, in almost every way, an anti-Odysseus. This is precisely what we will discuss today. My name is Armen Zakharian, and you are on "Armen and Fyodor," a literature-centric channel. Here
in our close circle, the leaves quiet down, and
with real magic, we will try to transport ourselves to the one place where they could meet and imagine what this encounter would be like.
Previously, I have spoken separately about each of them: the channel features episodes on what it means to be Odysseus and what it means to be Don Quixote. So, if you want to get the most aesthetic pleasure from our discussion today, I recommend listening to those first.
Body, Don Quixote — mind. Thus, it would be a mistake to deny that there are a number of obvious features that unite them. Both are warriors. Odysseus — a king,
a leader of the army under Troy, Don Quixote — a knight. Both constantly find themselves in difficult situations and seek a way out. Both are heroic, their
dissatisfied with the status quo, they impact the surrounding world. Finally, both have been nicknamed clever, but this coincidence is observed only in their Russian incarnations. In his native language
Quixote is the “Ingenioso Hidalgo,” ingenious, whereas even in Quixote’s own text, prudent is sensible. In short, all these coincidences are
no more than similarities in costume. The main thing that unites Odysseus and Don Quixote is wandering, being in constant motion. But it is from this similarity that essential differences begin. You know why
the famous hobbit Bilbo Baggins from Tolkien's tale cannot be placed alongside Odysseus and Quixote? Because his story is there and back again.
Don Quixote is only “there,” Odysseus “back.” The entire meaning of Odysseus’s journey is returning home, which is what the Greeks called "νόστος." The essence
The essence of Quixote's movement is the exact opposite: he seeks to escape from home, to venture into the world, and go as far as possible. In this sense, Don Quixote chooses what those same Greeks called "κοῖλος," contrasting nostos (returning). That is, Odysseus and Quixote both move
in opposite directions. Thus, from the very start, they are turned towards each other with the same force of movement but different vectors of application. They converge. However,
if Don Quixote prances from point A to point B, while Odysseus at the same time sets sail from point B to point A, what would happen? Sooner or later, they will meet. And we even know where, but that will come later.
For now, at the very start, at their maximum distance from each other, Quixote and Odysseus are most alike: they are both in confinement. One on the island of the nymph Calypso, the other in his home over endless reading of chivalric romances. However, even
the types of captivity already differ: Odysseus — by body, Don Quixote — by mind. So,
as opposites attract, they begin to be pushed towards each other, the closer they get, the less they have in common. Don Quixote is extremely serious
in everything he does, and therefore infinitely ridiculous to others, and everyone amuses at his expense. One of the characters says: “The benefit from Quixote, his prudence cannot compare to the enjoyment his follies bring.”
Odysseus often jokes about others, but woe to anyone who jokes about him. Don Quixote is constantly beaten, pelted with stones, caged and repeatedly beaten, his face is scratched, and in one episode, he is almost crucified.
Odysseus is invulnerable: he finds himself in the cyclops’ cave, navigates between Scylla and Charybdis, survives shipwreck, loses companion after companion, but emerges from Poseidon's water relatively intact. In critical moments, no one manages to not only strike him but even hit him. Don
is gullible, constantly deceived, endlessly lied to, manipulated for public amusement. Odysseus is cautious and shrewd, he trusts no one; moreover, he deceives everyone, lies, pretends, twists and mimics.
Naive Don Quixote once says, “It cannot and should not be called deception if it has a good purpose.” For Odysseus the ends always justify the means. Quixote
is self-assured and overconfident to a certain point,
he is entirely foreign to doubts. Odysseus can be arrogant, but generally, he evaluates himself and his strengths much more soberly, he is prone to doubts.
From this sobriety of Odysseus and the arrogance of Quixote emerges another difference: Odysseus is extremely grounded, Quixote extremely elevated. He is — after all a knight,
talks about honor, valor, and bravery. Of course, his bravery is often laughable, but he enters the cage with lions for real. Odysseus more often
talks about the stomach. In the entire "Iliad," all the heroes combined mention the power of the stomach over man less frequently than Odysseus alone.
Every time the tirade about the stomach begins with the fact that suffering, of course, is terrible, and ends with how nothing is baser than our terrible stomach, and it wouldn't be bad to have a bite to eat.
The main irony of this comparison, of course, is that Odysseus here is not simply the anti-Quixote, who fasts and subsists on wild acorns. Odysseus here is the spitting image of Sancho Panza.
Don Quixote is a very poor strategist, as a leader he is a true disaster: under his leadership, Sancho, who dreamed of becoming a governor, becomes a complete laughingstock. Odysseus
is charismatic, shrewd, and harsh. Under such leadership, even death is appealing. Odysseus is wise, Don Quixote is a madman,
Odysseus — king, Don Quixote — holy fool, Odysseus is an Old Testament deity-punisher, Don Quixote a New Testament Christ. [Music]
Thus, despite being complete opposites, they come to the same point. We weren't warned about this in school textbooks, but the route from A to B and back passes through hell. And both Odysseus and Don
descend into the underworld, and this, of course, is the only possible meeting point on their route.
For Odysseus it's a descent into the realm of the dead, for Don Quixote — a descent into the Cave of Montesinos. But even here, the heroes remain themselves: Odysseus goes to Hades out of necessity,
because he is presented no other means to achieve his goal. When he learns of the need to go to the underworld, Homer describes his reaction as: "He turned over endlessly in bed and wept, and the first question after the sorrow was: 'And who will lead me there?' Don Quixote
descends into the Cave of Montesinos voluntarily, without accompaniment or preconditions, because Quixote fancies himself a hero, and for a hero, trials are fitting.
Just before the descent, he notes that he and Sancho forgot to take a bell, by which a signal could be given to the surface, and it's a perfect excuse to postpone the adventure, but knights do not retreat; the meeting must take place, and Quixote descends into the cave. What follows is most eerie —
Odysseus is not there. They arrived by every calculation, the logic of events, by hereditary heroic experience: he should have been there. But Odysseus is practical: he
goes to the land of the dead for prophecy from the old seer Tiresias. The madman Quixote — he is of no interest.
At the bottom of the damp cave, in impenetrable darkness, the knight remains alone. It is then, for the first time, that he encounters his own disbelief, his own insanity. Standing in
the cave, he wonders: if Odysseus is not here, maybe none of the rest — the castles, the giants, the princesses, and the islands — existed either. In
the underworld meeting point of their routes, Odysseus confidently turns his ship towards new challenges, leaving the most terrifying behind.
For him, nothing changes, as Odysseus's Hades is material, and the most rational thing now is to simply continue sticking to his plan so as not to have to venture into Hades once more. But what is good for Odysseus is death for Quixote. And
after passing this point of non-meeting, he begins to doubt, and in his fantasy's canvas, spots of common sense appear, fatal to a madman. Quixote now begins to tread water, looking into himself with growing fear.
His journey becomes a wandering through those nooks of consciousness where he shouldn't have gazed at all. Now their paths will never cross again: each emerges renewed from their underworld and journeys on their individual way. Odysseus has new
trials ahead, but after them — a triumphant return, a loyal wife, a loving son, and vengeance over his enemies. But
Don Quixote will end his journey a knight, referring to himself as mad and daring, saying of himself: "I stood up for the humiliated and straightened injustice, punished arrogance, convinced giants and trod on monsters, and there is no feat exceeding human abilities that I haven’t accomplished."
Yet this daring madman will conclude his journey with perhaps the saddest assessment he could reach: "I do not know, whether I am truly good, to say — that I am not bad either."
This was Armen Zakharian with you. Until next time.
[Music]