The audience loves detective films.
It’s nice to watch a movie
already knowing how it ends.
And besides, it’s flattering
to feel smarter than the authors.
Residents of the capital claim that
this incredible story
happened in Moscow.
Odessa locals insist it took place
in their city.
Leningrad and Rostov-on-Don
disagree.
Seven cities dispute it
in exactly the same way
as seven cities call themselves
Homer’s birthplace.
It must be said that it’s unknown
where this story took place—
or whether it happened
at all.
So, as you may have noticed,
it was a dark night.
The unknown man tried very hard
to go unnoticed,
and he succeeded.
It was so dark, quiet,
and deserted here
that you almost felt like
committing a crime.
- Call Post No. 2-06...!
- Yes, sir!
- Block off all highways!
Get me the photos immediately—
- ...of the tire tread impressions!
- Yes, sir!
Tanya! And you—find out about the fingerprints.
So, from one district,
a third car has been stolen.
It’s the same hand at work—
experienced and skillful!
That hand works in cotton gloves
from Factory No. 8.
Then it’s not Fedka “Gold Tooth.”
And what did the oil analysis show—
the oil the criminal loves
to pour on garage hinges?
The oil turned out to be refined.
And did you notice that in the yard
where the theft occurred,
and on the street nearby,
lots of cars without garages spend the night.
Yes.
And stealing a car off the street
is easier than from a garage, isn’t it?
That’s a very accurate observation.
If we apply Stanislavsky’s teaching
about the super-objective,
an interesting thought arises:
the criminal is taking the path
of greatest resistance. But why?
Once we uncover his super-objective,
we’ll catch the criminal.
That’s brilliant!
Comrade investigator, I forgot
to mention one detail—
- ...maybe it’ll help.
- I’m listening, comrade victim.
On my rear fender, someone scratched
an obscene word with a nail...
Wait... so... which one?
Hello, Lyuba. I’m back.
Comrades! Fill the vehicle faster.
Don’t bunch up at the back.
Yuri Ivanovich, the trolleybus entrance
is on the other side.
Coming.
- Hello, Yakov Mikhailovich!
- Hello, Detochkin!
- So, how’s your uncle from Dushanbe?
- My uncle? Bad.
Last time it was
an aunt from Moldavia...
A cousin!
- No, you said...
- She passed away.
Yeah... we’re all mortal, Detochkin...
we’re all mortal.
And if people didn’t die,
we wouldn’t be able to insure them
against death.
You won’t deny, Detochkin,
that I’m being considerate toward you.
Every time your relatives fall ill
or die,
I grant you
unpaid leave.
You’re an exceptionally considerate boss.
That’s right, Detochkin, but
you have a great many relatives...
and I have very few staff positions.
You see, your trips
disrupt our plan.
I’ll catch up!
Understand, I can’t place
family interests
above public ones.
- I... I’ll catch up!
- Well, go on—catch up.
A policeman stopped me yesterday.
The power of attorney isn’t valid.
You need to stop by and certify it
at the notary’s office.
- Sign here, please.
- Dima, sign!
Honestly, I don’t even know myself
why I insure my property.
What about fires?
It’d be a shame if such property
burned down for nothing.
Maybe we should insure
our car?
Did you buy a car?
Car insurance is issued
in case of total loss
or accident due to collisions
or natural disasters.
- And in case of theft?
- In case of theft—no.
I’m not so wealthy
as to pay for natural disasters, too.
- And where do you keep it?
- Come here!
Beige... the color isn’t flashy...
And you don’t have a garage?
Not yet.
I’m working on it, but it’s
a tough business.
They promise to allocate a spot...
so for now—no garage.
But I already got a lock... Japanese—
you can’t pick a key for it.
Yes, hard to pick... and you can’t
get it with a picklock either.
You’d need an oxy-acetylene cutter,
and cutting with one... what a hassle...
You’re a smart one.
- Need a ride?
- We’re not going the same way.
As you wish!
Everyone who doesn’t have a car
dreams of buying one.
And everyone who has a car
dreams of selling it,
and doesn’t only because
once you sell it, you’re left without a car.
A person, more than any other living creature,
loves creating
additional difficulties for himself.
That’s exactly what explains the desire
to have one’s own car.
The thought that five and a half thousand
have simply been thrown onto the pavement
can poison any happy life.
- Mom!
- You’re here!
I can’t understand what kind of business trips
an insurance agent could have.
Why are you standing there? Lunch is ready—
go wash your hands.
What heavy things are you carrying
in your briefcase?
Things I need for work.
It’s scary to look at you—
you’ve gotten so thin and drawn...
Korchnoi won the chess tournament...
I was rooting for Tal.
He fell behind by half a point...
Don’t laugh at your mother.
These trips seem suspicious
not only to me...
To whom else?
You’re eating onion soup
made to the recipe of the great writer Dumas père.
Lyuba finds these trips suspicious.
And she’s right.
She doesn’t want to marry
a good-for-nothing. - Did she tell you that?
No, not now. He’s only just arrived.
That evening, Maksim Podberezovikov
was moving in an unknown direction.
From the other end of the city, in an even more
unknown direction,
Yuri Detochkin was walking.
They were walking toward their fate.
They were drawing closer.
Every investigator inevitably has a hobby
to which he devotes time
free from the hunt for criminals.
Sherlock Holmes, for example, played the violin.
Maksim Podberezovikov—
acted in amateur theatre.
...The development of people’s amateur art
is moving forward in giant strides.
The spirit of the times has finally reached
us as well—amateur groups.
They’ve begun consolidating us, creating
people’s theatres—so to speak, forming all-star teams
out of club troupes.
Today is a festive day for us.
Today we are creating a new
people’s theatre.
I hope it will be a strong organism...
a united one.
Comrade Detochkin, don’t fidget—
sit down.
Within the hospitable walls of our
House of Culture, all conditions have been created
for people of different professions
to join Melpomene,
who, as we know, was the muse...
Our people’s theatre, in particular,
is being formed, so to speak, from two
friendly groups... uh... from the police troupe and, uh...
the drivers.
- I recognize you.
- That wasn’t me.
But you said, “And who are the judges?”
I didn’t say anything like that about judges.
You did, you did...
You played Chatsky, didn’t you?
I... I completely forgot...
And now we’ll be acting with you
in the same production.
- I’m very glad!
- Me too!
There’s an opinion that people’s theatres will soon...
supplant...! At last...
professional theatres!
And that’s correct!
An actor who isn’t paid a salary
will act with greater inspiration.
Besides, an actor has to work somewhere...
It’s wrong if he spends the whole day,
you see, hanging around the theatre.
Just imagine how much better Yermolova would have acted in the evening
if during the day she had...
you see... worked...
at a grinding machine.
The title of people’s theatre
is a serious responsibility.
Whom haven’t we played
in our groups!
Isn’t it time, my friends, for us
to take a swing at William, you see,
our Shakespeare?
And we will!
Transistor radio “Alpinist,” please.
Careful, I beg you.
Excuse me, which of you is Dima?
I’m from Oleg Nikolayevich.
- Which Oleg Nikolayevich?
- A friend of Leonid Osipovich.
I need a foreign tape recorder—
American or German.
We have a very good domestic one.
No, a domestic one won’t do.
- A foreign one has to be sourced.
- I understand. How much?
- What’s going on, citizen?
- Just looking.
What is this, a zoo or something?
Go watch the TV over there.
- Fifty.
- Fifty?
- Get a grip.
- We need to find one, bring it. Italy?
We’ll have to hold off...
- ...leave your phone number...
- All right.
- A pack of Belomor, please.
- No Belomor.
Well... what do you have? Then give me
“Drug” cigarettes.
Taxi! Taxi! Taxi!
Please! I beg you!
I’m late. Is this your car?
- No.
- But you’re a driver?
No, no.
- Then what are you doing here?
- I want to steal a car, and you’re in the way.
Then please steal it with me—
I’m late for my train.
Ah! Get in. Only you’ll be
an accomplice.
There! I warned you!
Get him! There he is! Got him!
Hold him! Hold the thief!
Hold him! Don’t let him go!
You little thief!
I’m not a thief! I’m late for my train.
Please—here’s my ticket!
He came prepared! Look how
thoughtful! Huh?
Finally! Quick! They caught the crook.
He tried to steal my car!
- Who’s the owner?
- I am—well, we are.
I’m not a thief. I was late for my train,
and he took my ticket.
- Your documents?
- Here. My ticket.
- And yours.
- What?
- We won’t sort this out here.
Who’s a witness? - Me. What happened?
I’m not a thief. The thief ran away.
Unfortunately, I didn’t remember his face...
I’m late for my train!
Though... I’ve already missed it.
- Is it yours?
- Of course not! God forbid!
Yes, I’m a witness. A witness. Me.
I look better in profile...
So then, I’ll start from the very beginning.
They didn’t deliver any Belomor to me today.
Well... they didn’t—so they didn’t.
Could you make it shorter?
Young man... in your profession,
you mustn’t rush.
Belomor is a detail for the investigation!
And that very man
who climbed into your car
also asked for Belomor at first,
and then bought “Drug” cigarettes—
30 kopeks a pack,
with a little dog on the label.
And that’s when I thought:
“Why is he nervous? Why?”
Stop! Stop, stop! What are you thinking about all the time?
Every actor must know his part by heart,
and don’t run idiotically around the stage.
You have to act with your head!
And don’t be rude, or I’ll send you off the field... uh...
off the rehearsal!
- I’m not being rude, I...
- B-r-e-a-k!
Yevgeny Aleksandrovich, in this spot:
“Leave it, for God’s sake!”
Ah... leave it! Break!
- What am I, a kid to him or something?
- Don’t get upset! Come on...
- What are you smoking?
- “Drug” cigarettes.
Yes, yes... “Drug” cigarettes... the dog on the label...
thirty kopeks...
Normally I smoke Belomor, but there was no Belomor.
No Belomor—exactly right.
That’s why he bought “Drug” cigarettes.
- Who is “he”?
- The criminal.
What criminal?
A modern one—I’d even say
a new type of criminal.
What did crooks used to forget
at the scene of the crime? - What?
Caps, cigarette butts—and now...
Shakespeare!
Don’t be scared—
there are no blood stains here!
- So you’re an investigator?
- Yes. I handle car-theft cases.
No fingerprints. The criminal
works in gloves.
- But you’re not interested?
- No... I’m very interested!
You see, there’s no library stamp, no...
I’m saying: there’s no library stamp
and no owner’s name.
You know how some people
write their names in books?
I know, but I don’t.
There’s a gang operating in the city.
They steal private cars.
In a year, four cars were stolen
from one district.
Three!
Well, you’ve already heard. Yes—three.
They failed to steal the fourth.
But soon it will be over.
- How?
- We detained one member of the gang.
A respectable man—an engineer.
Wife’s a doctor. Two kids.
- What does he look like?
- Kind of short.
- Round-faced?
- Yes...
- And... and you arrested him?
- Well, why such a harsh measure?
He was going to run off to a resort,
but I took a written undertaking not to leave town.
What if he’s not an accomplice?
A respected man—and you deprived him of his vacation?
My instincts tell me he’s not guilty.
But the final determination is a matter
of a few days.
I already know the distinguishing signs
of the gang leader...
Tall... wears a raincoat,
a hat, carries a briefcase...
and the main feature—stooped...
And how are you going to catch the leader?
Comrades! Everyone back for the second half!
We’d like a trap
for a large animal.
- Fox? Wolf?
- Bear. - He’s joking.
Tell me... how does it work?
You put the bait here.
- Do you have bait?
- Yes, yes.
The predator smells the bait... creeps up,
creeps up... and the beast is caught!
- Lovely!
- Write it up!
- I think everything is fine.
- Splendid! Bring ice cream...
Sima! You’re not in the woods!
Guys, don’t split up! Stay together!
Semitsvetov! Dima!
- She’s blonde!
- Beige-ish!
Guys, when I’ve been drinking,
I don’t get behind the wheel.
Give us a ride, Dima! Give us a ride, Dima...
Give us a ride, Di-ma!
Quiet! Quiet! Quiet!
They’ve invented this test tube at the police—
where you... ugh!
You breathe into it and it shows right away
whether you’ve been drinking.
And if you have, they take your license.
- I’m going anyway!
- Sima, this isn’t the beach!
- Why are you lying down? It’s a polish!
- So what!
- Listen, I’m r-really plastered!
- Yeah!
I must place myself
in a horizontal position.
- Who is it?
- Lyuba, it’s me!
What is it?
What happened?
Lyuba, you see, they’ve set traps everywhere!
- Oh my God!
I’m so unlucky, so unlucky—
I’ve had such bad luck!
The criminal made two attempts
on the same car.
Not a random coincidence. I think
he wanted to steal your car in particular.
Reasonable... I figured that out too.
But you shouldn’t set a trap
for a living person.
You couldn’t protect us from the bandit,
so we had to take up self-defense.
Why did he fixate on your car in particular?
Do you suspect anyone
among your acquaintances?
Our acquaintances are perfectly decent people.
Well, maybe someone
envies you?
Envies what? What strange questions.
Check the clinics—
whether anyone has come in
with a characteristic leg injury.
Let’s set up surveillance
on your car!
No, thank you...
Tomorrow we’re putting up a garage.
What do you mean you won’t come?
Look, the director will award you a penalty kick!
Ah, your leg hurts! Then lie down...
Of course, I’ll pass it on... get well!
- Whose leg?
- A leg! The right person’s leg!
- All right then, call.
- When?
When your car gets stolen.
Dima, they’re taking away Toptunov’s dacha!
- Who’s taking it?
- Are you stupid or what?
Daddy, they’re taking away Toptunov’s dacha.
And rightly so—long overdue!
We have to fight crooks, for sure.
Why is he a crook? The man knows how to live.
Tell me—on what salary
did the deputy director of a knitwear
factory build himself
a two-story mansion?
- That’s his business!
- No, it’s ours!
We will fight mercilessly
those who live on unearned income!
- Quiet, Daddy!
- Oh, you got scared!
I’ll give you a knee to the backside
and you’ll fly off my property!
Dad, I’m sick of your barracks humor!
What do you mean, “with a knee”? Why?
And why are you putting on airs, son-in-law?
Who do you think you are?
This is my dacha!
Let everyone hear—this is my dacha!
It’s registered in your name!
But it’s being built with my money.
Prove it!
Will you stop it already?
You live in this world
on a power of attorney!
The car’s in your wife’s name, the dacha’s in mine—
you own nothing. You’re a nobody!
Why! Why do I have to live like this?
God, why? Why?
I—a man with higher education—
have to hide, adapt,
wriggle out of things! Why can’t I
live freely, openly?
Oh, when will this end! Never!
And what exactly do you mean?
Do you know what I can—
quite simply—
do to you for this?
- I know... I know...
- He’s scared!
Have pity on him, Daddy!
This type must always remember who I am!
And he’s a common crook!
Still, I ought to give you a knee!
- Who is it?
- Lyuba, it’s me!
- What happened? Another trap?
- No, this time it all worked out.
You’re leaving? On a business trip?
Now? At night?
It’s not my fault... I have to...
because, you see,
a business trip is a rather
complicated undertaking.
Lyuba! Why get
so upset.
I’ll be back in a few days.
I’ll write to you from there. You hear?
Lyuba! I’m very upset too.
See?
Hello. You know, our right turn signal sticks.
And when shifting gears,
there’s this sound...
Let’s listen.
Yes, and the day before yesterday,
the car smelled of gasoline all day.
Let’s smell.
Where’s the car?
- Comrade chief...
- Hello!
I see you’re driving alone. Help me,
please, start this old wreck.
- Start the motorcycle?
- Yes. I can’t manage it alone.
No, the battery’s run down.
I asked the bosses a thousand times
to give me a new motorcycle.
Yeah... with an old battery,
this isn’t life.
- Ready? Three-four, go?
- Let’s try.
Come on, get a run-up!
Run-up, run-up.
- Okay... stop! I see you’re tired?
- A little.
- Now let me take you for a ride.
- What’s the point?
Listen, friend. Let’s hook it to
your Volga. You got a tow rope?
Who knows what’s in there...
I don’t remember. I’ll check.
I’ve got a tow line!
Great!
All set! Thanks, friend—you saved me.
- Man is a friend to man.
- Exactly.
Misfortune happened to me—
you helped.
If it happens to you—I’ll help.
And together we’re doing a common cause:
you in your way, and I in mine.
Tell me, friend, is there a telegraph
somewhere around here?
Not far—get in, I’ll show you.
Please grant me 5 days’ unpaid leave
due to the sudden serious
condition... serious condition...
of my beloved nephew.
Right, right... right! I understand! Writing it down...
that’s all!
- Resting?
- Uh-huh...
- Did something happen?
- No, nothing, nothing.
- Who’s the owner?
- I am.
Vehicle documents.
Sorry.
A chase! What detective plot
can do without one?
One runs, another gives chase...
that is the immutable law of the genre.
A detective story without a chase is like
life without love.
Detochkin loved children. He couldn’t
have acted otherwise.
Detochkin realized it was the end.
He wanted to close his eyes,
but he was afraid of running over a Young Pioneer.
But the inspector also loved children
and was no less noble than Detochkin.
- Got you, brother!
- Yeah, got me!
You won’t get away from the police... what the devil!
Hold on a second!
- You... wait, don’t drive off!
- What is it, brother?
What, what... well, again, you see,
the battery...
I warned you. With an old battery—
this isn’t life.
I always feared it. There’ll be important work,
and it’ll let me down.
There! They didn’t transfer me
to a new motorcycle.
My sympathies.
- Bad luck for you.
- But good luck for you!
Of the two of us, one of us
had to get lucky.
So what do we do now, brother?
Why were you running from me?
Habit. You chase, I run.
And I’ve got a habit too. You run,
and I chase... you could’ve gotten out and helped.
We could’ve hooked it to your Volga,
like last time.
No way! I’ve already seen how you repay kindness.
Forgive me!
Don’t interfere!
Look—the police!
Lock the garage! Proceed!
Lift it!
Lower it!
I always said he was
a talented criminal.
Maybe even... more talented than me.
Holy smoke—all the money in one-ruble bills!
Don’t distract me, or I’ll have
to start over.
Five thousand five hundred! That’s it!
Why is all your money in one-ruble bills?
That’s suspicious. Not good!
And who are you—some prosecutor?
I’m not asking where this car is from
or why there are no documents.
And I can tell you frankly:
I stole this car.
And I can tell you frankly too:
I’m a pastor.
These rubles are donations for him! Well!
Just a little left!
And you believe in God?
Everyone believes—some believe
that God exists, others believe that He doesn’t.
Neither can be proven!
Will you count it?
I will!
Here—just as promised...
a Grundig tape recorder.
But is it new?
- Absolutely new. I checked it personally.
- Then write it up. I remember everything.
- Eighty!
- What? You said fifty!
- Personal circumstances changed.
- You know, that’s plain robbery!
I’m not insisting. It’ll be gone in a second.
An elegant item...
- ...four tracks... stereo.
- Write it up!
Citizen, it’s sold—don’t touch it with your hands.
It’s sold.
Why did he still want to steal
your car in particular?
- What’s wrong with you?
- I got caught...
I’m finished... an investigator
came to see me.
You’ll go to jail—don’t steal!
Semyon Vasilyevich!
You’re in my house!
Your home is prison!
Inka, Inka! What do we do? What do we do?
Inka, what do we do?
Start drying crackers!
Dima, don’t worry! You need to bribe
the investigator!
Have you lost your mind? Bribe him!
You’re crazy!
- Give him a lot—then he’ll take it!
- Silence! Attention!
I won’t allow it! Shame!
Dad, with your lectures you should speak at your market.
I sell strawberries grown
with my own hands.
And for bribes, not only my son-in-law—
I’ll grind my own daughter into dust!
No worries! Prison will reform you.
In ten years you’ll come back
a different man!
Put the little bird down!
You should marry an orphan!
Don’t doubt it—I have that money.
Here... a full briefcase.
Do you really want to transfer
- ...this amount to an orphanage?
- Yes.
Were you raised in that home?
Are these your personal savings?
Well, how can I put it... in general...
I had a hand in it too.
Hello! I need Yuri Ivanovich Detochkin.
- I’m Yura’s mother.
- Pleased to meet you.
I’m from the people’s theatre.
I’m very happy Yura
is acting in the theatre.
- I think he has ability.
- He’s simply talented.
- He didn’t come to rehearsal...
- Dear, he’s on a business trip.
I hate his business trips.
He bolts in the middle of the night, disappears.
Lyuba’s right—something’s not right.
Lyuba is Yura’s fiancée.
He’s somehow old-fashioned.
He’s been courting her for ages.
They met when he
came to insure her...
Tell me—what kind of business trips
can an insurance agent have?
- What’s your profession?
- Investigator.
Then you figure it out!
When I was young,
an investigator courted me.
But I married a Red Army soldier.
We sang: “Our locomotive rushes вперед,
and the stop is at the commune!”
- When did he leave, and for how long?
- Three days ago, at night.
And the strangest thing—he went to say goodbye to Lyuba
in some Volga.
- Ah! So he took a taxi!
- No, he himself was behind the wheel.
- Does Yuri Ivanovich drive?
- Yura? He worked as a driver for 10 years.
Then he had an accident—he got a concussion.
The doctors advised Yura not to drive for a while,
so he took a job as an insurance agent.
What’s wrong with you?
To which city did you send
your employee Detochkin
on a business trip?
I didn’t send him anywhere.
Detochkin has a great many
chronically ill relatives
in various cities of the Soviet Union.
I recently received a telegram... here it is. Here.
His next beloved nephew fell ill.
He took unpaid leave.
Maksim was beside himself.
Memories burned his heart.
How cleverly Detochkin hid his interest in tracking the leader! Hypocrite!
How he stole a car
with the help of a crane!
A vile schemer—a thief!
He betrayed what was dearest—friendship!
And such a person deserves no mercy.
Mom? It’s me. I just arrived...
I’m fine... is everything calm at home?
No one came by?
You played yourself with that people’s theatre.
An investigator came to see you.
- Defend yourself, sir!
- I am at your service...
I have the honor to attack you...
- Where have you been?
- What the hell—I was on a business trip!
And how’s the nephew?
- What nephew?
- The beloved one!
And the wolf trap? And the sore leg?
And the “Drug” cigarettes?
Stop improvising! In Shakespeare’s time
there were no “Drug” cigarettes!
And besides—why did you switch
to prose?
- Podberezovikov!
- Yes?
What are you thinking about all the time?
Stop it! Stop waving
your saber!
What a blow!
Easy!
- Where is he?
- He came to!
- Alive!
- Break!
- How many cars did you sell?
- Four.
Let’s say four. A decent sum—an entire fortune.
How did you turn out like this—your mom’s so good,
sings about the locomotive.
- Excuse me, are you crazy?
- No, I’ve got a certificate.
What an actor!
I always said: a real crook
is usually a good actor!
You stole only from those you considered crooks.
I guessed right away!
Think they’ll shave off a year or two at trial?
Where do you hide your capital?
- Here.
- Aha! I see!
Hello! Why didn’t you tell me right away?
Please come with your friend
to a separate office.
Raya! Lyuda!
They’ll bring fresh beer—just delivered—
and serve dried fish...
- The fish was just caught!
- Your friend’s a joker!
Tell me, is there any news
about the car?
Soon there will be.
- Let’s go.
- Let’s stay a bit longer, if possible.
It’s unlikely they’ll feed me in prison
the way they do here.
- What is this?
- A change of underwear, just in case.
- And this?
- Certificates, receipts, documents...
- What documents? Where’s the money?
- This is the money.
What? You transferred
the money to children’s homes?
Uh-huh.
- And how much did you keep for yourself?
- I kept nothing.
Only for travel and per diem.
Yes, dear viewer, Detochkin
didn’t take any money for himself.
He may be a thief, but a selfless,
honest man.
They spread accounting documents on the table.
It’s an audit... bring them our “house beer.”
Okay.
I didn’t sell the first car.
I left it with the police in Kursk.
I stuck a detailed written explanation
to the windshield,
then went to the station and returned
to Moscow.
And... with the second car, an injustice happened.
I drove it to the police too,
and left a note again
that its owner was a crook!
But they returned it to the owner...
that’s when I decided to sell them!
I love you!
Here! The warrant for your arrest!
Now give it to me!
Take it!
- And now I’ll tear it up!
- Maksim! Maksim, don’t you dare!
- Yura!
- Don’t! You’ll get in trouble!
Maksim! Guys! We’re friends! Guys!
Dad! Everything’s fine! Dad!
Everything’s fine! Dad!
Then take it for yourself!
I’m giving it to you!
Come in! Goodbye!
Goodbye!
Friend! Friend!
If I fall ill, I won’t go
to the doctors.
I’ll turn to friends,
don’t think it’s delirium...
Listen, friend! Don’t jail me until after
the premiere, I beg you!
I’m not going to jail you at all.
Live free!
Such a role! It happens once in a lifetime, you see?
Play the premiere and all
the performances after.
- ...no need for the later ones.
- No, you must, you must!
- Oh, you sweetheart.
- I’m going to Lyuba!
Don’t get hit by a car!
Why did you do it? Who asked you?
Who forced you?
Look at yourself.
You’re... an idiot.
You reason like
a three-year-old.
Why are you sitting there? Get up!
What am I supposed to do? Oh my God!
Did you think about me? No? No.
You always thought only about yourself.
They’ll lock you up, Yura.
- And they’ll be right.
- They’ll be wrong.
Button up. I’ll wait for you, Yura.
Five years, eight years, ten years.
Thanks... ten... ten, so then
I’ll be 46.
Yes, that’s... of course...
- Oh my God!
- What have I gotten myself into!
- Into what? Into what?
No, just look—
what you look like...
What do I look like?
Oh my God, you ruined my whole life,
Yurochka!
Yura!
- Good morning! It’s me!
- Hi!
Have you heard that today
another car was stolen again?
And today, you haven’t looked out the window?
Hello? Hello! Why are you silent?
You’re looking out the window, aren’t you?
Well? How is it?
Why did you do it?
Since when have you been stealing
cars from honest people?
Where are your principles?
No. It’s Stelkin’s car,
and he’s a bribe-taker.
What Stelkin? This is the car
of a famous scientist! A Doctor of Sciences!
One moment, I’ll check the card index.
He’s got a card index! A card index!
Wretched bureaucrat!
It’s Stelkin’s car,
and he’s a bribe-taker.
Impossible... did I really make a mistake!
You will immediately return the Volga
to its owner. And as for you, I advise you...
Come to me, as they say,
with your belongings!
And the play?
There will be no play!
Come in!
Here is the report on the work completed.
The warrant... for my arrest.
Good evening!
- Congratulations on the premiere!
- Same to you.
They brought me such a funny wig!
And why do you need a wig? Your whole life
has been lived in makeup anyway.
And why are you speaking about my life
as if it’s already in the past?
Because tomorrow is the trial.
You’re facing five years.
I have mitigating circumstances.
I’m an honest man.
What kind? That you stole cars
from one crook and sold them to another?
Well, there were some shortcomings
in my work. Who doesn’t have them?
You, for instance, couldn’t catch me
for a long time.
It’s hard to catch someone
who leads a double life!
I-it always oppressed and tormented me.
Uh... tie my bow.
No good deed can be accompanied
by lies and deceit.
Imagine that—took justice into his own hands,
carried out retribution.
Honestly, it’s all stupidity
and a crime.
Defendant, where are you going?
So you also think
- ...that I’m guilty?
- Yes!
Comrades, the audience is a full stadium.
Everyone to the stage.
Yes, don’t forget: “To be or not to be?”
And you’re not ready again?
Here, Hamlet, my handkerchief! Wipe your forehead!
The Queen drinks to your success, Hamlet.
But the third time, Laertes, you must not jest.
Fight with full strength.
- Do you fear I think you a milksop?
- Do you think so? Let’s begin!
Let us forgive each other, noble Hamlet.
Be pure before heaven! I follow you!
Horatio!
- I die... mother... farewell!
- Yura, I’m here!
All rise! Court is in session!
We continue the hearing.
Detochkin broke the law, and the law,
as we know, doesn’t like jokes.
In all the judge’s practice,
there had never been such a strange, paradoxical case.
Under the law, Detochkin faced
imprisonment for up to five years.
Detochkin is not simply a thief. He’s worse!
He’s a bandit!
He must be tried
for banditry with breaking and entering!
This type took aim at the most sacred thing we have—
the Constitution!
It says: “Every person
has the right to personal property.”
“It is protected by law.” Every person has the right to have a car,
a dacha, books... money! Comrades,
money hasn’t been abolished yet.
From each according to his ability, to each according to his labor—
in cash.
Criminal proceedings have been initiated
against witness Semitsvetov.
Dad! - It’s fine, it’s fine—you’ll find yourself another one, an honest one!
If Dima Semitsvetov’s future
was now fairly clear,
then Yuri Ivanovich Detochkin’s fate
remained still uncertain.
At last the court called
the most important witness: Maksim Podberezovikov.
Honorable judges.
At first I handled this case
as the investigator.
But when it became clear that
the accused is my friend,
I withdrew from the case
and now appear
only as a witness.
I understand, honorable judges, that you face
a difficult task:
Detochkin broke the law,
but he did so for noble reasons.
He sold cars,
but gave the money to children.
He is, of course, guilty,
but he... is not guilty.
Have mercy on him, honorable judges:
he is a good man.
And an excellent worker!
If you don’t know, keep quiet.
Freedom for Yuri Detochkin! Yura!
Quiet! I demand silence, or I will
immediately have the courtroom cleared!
Defendant, you are given
the last word.
Citizens judges, perhaps
I acted incorrectly,
but from the bottom of my heart.
I... couldn’t stand it.
They steal—steal a lot... I wanted
to help you, citizens judges.
Please let me go!
I won’t do it anymore...
I swear I won’t!
As is already known, the audience loves detective films.
It’s nice to watch a movie
already knowing how it ends.
This incredible story,
which no one knows where it took place,
or whether it happened at all,
is coming to an end.
Hello, Lyuba. I’m back.
Russian subtitles at
http://subtitles.ee
29.09.2003