The audience loves detective
movies.
It’s nice to watch a film,
already knowing how it ends.
And in general, it’s flattering
to feel smarter than the authors.
People in the capital claim that
this unbelievable story
happened in Moscow.
Odessans insist it took place
in their city.
Leningrad and Rostov-on-Don
disagree.
Seven cities dispute it
in exactly the same way
as seven cities call themselves
Homer’s birthplace.
It must be said, no one knows
where this story happened—
or whether it happened
at all.
So, as you may have noticed,
it was a dark night.
The unknown man did his best
to remain unnoticed,
and he succeeded.
It was so dark, quiet,
and deserted here
that one couldn’t help
wanting to commit a crime.
- Call Post 2-06\V...
- Yes, sir!
- Block all highways!
Get me the photos urgently—
- ...of the tire tread prints!
- Yes, sir!
Tanya! And you check on the fingerprints.
So, the third car has been stolen
from the same district.
It’s the same hand at work—
skilled and experienced!
That hand works in cotton gloves
from Factory No. 8.
Then it’s not Fedka “Gold Tooth.”
What did the oil analysis show—
the oil the criminal so loves
to pour on garage hinges?
It turned out to be refined oil.
And did you notice that in the yard
where the theft happened,
and on the street nearby, a lot of
cars without garages spend the night?
Yes.
And stealing a car from the street
is easier than from a garage, right?
That is a very accurate observation.
If we apply Stanislavsky’s theory
of the “super-objective,”
a curious thought arises:
the criminal is taking the path
of greatest resistance. But why?
Once we uncover his super-objective,
we’ll catch him.
That’s grand!
Comrade investigator, I forgot
to mention one detail—
- ...maybe it will help.
- I’m listening, comrade victim.
There’s an obscene word scratched
with a nail on my rear fender...
Wait... right... which one?
Hello, Lyuba. I’m back.
Comrades! Fill the trolleybus quicker.
Don’t bunch up at the back.
Yury Ivanovich, the entrance is
on the other side.
Coming.
- Hello, Yakov Mikhailovich!
- Hello, Detochkin!
- So, how’s your uncle from Dushanbe?
- Uncle? Bad.
Last time it was an aunt
from Moldova...
A cousin!
- No, but you said...
- She passed away.
Yeah... we’re all mortal, Detochkin...
we’re all mortal.
And if people didn’t die,
we wouldn’t be able to insure
against death.
You won’t deny, Detochkin,
that I show you consideration.
Every time your relatives fall ill
or die,
I grant you
unpaid leave.
You’re an exceptionally considerate manager.
True, Detochkin, but you have
an awful lot of relatives...
And I have very few staff positions.
You see, your trips
throw off our plan.
I’ll catch up!
Understand, I can’t place
family interests
above public ones.
- I... I’ll catch up!
- Then go catch up.
A policeman stopped me yesterday.
The power of attorney is invalid.
You need to stop by and have it
certified at the notary office.
- Sign here, please.
- Dima, sign it!
To be honest, I don’t even know
why I insure my property.
What about fires?
It would be a shame if such property
burned down for nothing.
Maybe we should insure
our car?
Did you buy a car?
Car insurance is provided
in case of total loss
or damage due to collisions
or natural disasters.
- And in case of theft?
- In case of theft—no.
I’m not so rich
as to pay for natural disasters
as well.
- And where do you keep it?
- Come here!
Beige... not a flashy color...
And you don’t have a garage?
Not yet.
I’m working on it, but it’s
a hard business.
They promise to allocate a spot...
so no garage yet.
But I already got a lock—Japanese.
You can’t pick a key for it.
Yes, hard to pick... even a lockpick
won’t do it.
You’d need an acetylene torch—
and cutting with a torch... that’s such a fuss...
My clever girl.
- Need a lift?
- We’re not going your way.
Suit yourself!
Everyone who doesn’t have a car
dreams of buying one.
And everyone who has a car
dreams of selling it,
and doesn’t only because once you sell it,
you’re left without a car.
Man, more than any other living creature,
loves creating additional difficulties
for himself.
That is exactly what explains
the desire to own a car.
The thought that five and a half thousand
have simply been thrown into the gutter
can poison any happy life.
- Mom!
- You’re here!
I can’t understand what kind of business trips
an insurance agent could have.
Why are you standing there? Lunch is ready,
go wash your hands.
What heavy things are you carrying
in your briefcase?
Necessary work items.
It’s scary to look at you—
you’ve gotten so thin and worn out...
Korchnoi won the chess tournament...
I was rooting for Tal.
He fell behind by half a point...
Don’t laugh at your mother.
Those trips are suspicious
not only to me...
To who else?
Eat the onion soup—recipe
of the great writer Dumas père.
Lyuba finds these trips suspicious. She’s right.
She doesn’t want to marry a bungler.
- Did she tell you that?
No, not now. He’s only just arrived.
That evening Maxim Podberezovikov
was moving in an unknown direction.
From the other end of the city,
in an even more unknown direction,
Yury Detochkin was walking.
They were walking toward fate.
They were drawing closer.
Every investigator invariably has a hobby
to which he devotes the time
free from hunting criminals.
Sherlock Holmes, for example, played the violin;
Maxim Podberezovikov—
amateur theater.
...The development of people’s amateur art
is moving forward in leaps and bounds.
The spirit of the times has finally touched
even us, amateur collectives. We’ve begun
to be consolidated, creating
people’s theaters—one might say, club troupes
are being formed into all-star teams.
Today is a ceremonial day for us.
Today we are creating a new
people’s theater.
I hope it will be a strong organism...
close-knit.
Comrade Detochkin, stop fidgeting,
sit in your place.
Within the welcoming walls of our
House of Culture, all conditions are created
for people of different professions
to be introduced to Melpomene,
who, as is known, was the muse...
Our people’s theater, in particular,
is being created, so to speak, from two
friendly collectives. Uh... from
the police collective and, uh... drivers.
- I recognized you.
- That wasn’t me.
But you... you said: “And who are the judges?”
I never said anything like that about judges.
You did, you did...
Weren’t you the one who played Chatsky?
I... I completely forgot...
And now we’ll be acting together with you
in the same play.
- I’m very glad!
- Me too!
There is an opinion that people’s theaters
will soon... supplant...! At last...
professional theaters!
And that is correct!
An actor who doesn’t receive a salary
will perform with greater inspiration.
After all, besides,
an actor must work somewhere...
It’s wrong if he spends the whole day,
you see, loafing around the theater.
Why, how much better would Yermolova have played
in the evening if during the day she...
you see... worked...
at a grinding machine.
The title of “people’s theater”
places many obligations.
We’ve played all sorts of roles
in our troupes!
Isn’t it time, my friends, we took a swing at William — Shakespeare, that is.
Isn’t it time, my friends, we
And we will!
Transistor radio “Alpinist,” please.
Careful, if you please.
Excuse me, which of you is Dima?
I’m from Oleg Nikolayevich.
- Oleg Nikolayevich who?
- A friend of Leonid Osipovich.
I need a foreign tape recorder—
American or German.
Here’s a very good domestic one.
No, domestic won’t do.
- A foreign one must be “sourced.”
- I understand. How much?
- What’s the matter, citizen?
- Just looking.
What is this, a zoo or something?
Go watch the TV over there.
- Fifty.
- Fifty?
- Pull yourself together.
- Need to find one, bring it in. Italy?
We’ll have to hold off...
- ...leave your phone number...
- All right.
- “Belomor,” please.
- No “Belomor.”
Well... what do you have? Then give me
“Friend” cigarettes.
Taxi! Taxi! Taxi!
Please! I beg you!
I’m late. Is this your car?
- No.
- But are you the driver?
No, no.
- Then what are you doing here?
- I want to steal a car, and you’re in the way.
Then please steal it with me,
I’m late for my train.
Ah! Get in. But you are becoming an accomplice.
There! I warned you!
Get him! There he is! Caught him!
Get him, get the thief!
Get him! Don’t let him go!
What a thief!
I’m not a thief! I’m late for my train.
Please, here’s my ticket!
Came prepared! Look how prudent he is! Huh?
Finally! Hurry! They caught the crook!
He tried to steal my car!
- Who’s the owner?
- Me... I mean, we are.
I’m not a thief. I’m late for my train,
and he took my ticket.
- Your documents?
- Here. My ticket.
- And yours.
- What?
- We won’t sort this out here.
Who’s the witness? - Me! …What’s going on?
I’m not a thief. The thief got away.
Unfortunately I didn’t remember his face...
I’m late for my train!
Though I’m already too late.
- Is it yours?
- Why, no! Heaven forbid!
Yes, I’m a witness. A witness. Me.
I look better in profile...
So, I’ll start from the very beginning.
They didn’t bring me “Belomor” today.
Well... they didn’t, so they didn’t.
Could you make it shorter?
Young man... in your profession,
there’s no need to rush.
“Belomor” is a detail for the investigation!
And that very man,
the one who climbed into your car,
also first asked for “Belomor,”
and then bought “Friend” cigarettes,
30 kopeks a pack,
with a little dog on the label.
And then I thought:
“Why is he nervous? Why?”
Stop! Stop, stop! What do you keep thinking about?
Every player must know the part by heart
and you don’t need to run dumbly
around the stage.
You have to act with your head!
And don’t be rude, or I’ll send you off the field...
uh... off the rehearsal!
- I’m not being rude, I...
- B-r-e-a-k!
Yevgeny Alexandrovich, this line:
“Leave it, for God’s sake!”
Ah... leave it! Break!
- What am I, some kid to him or what?
- Don’t get upset! Come on...
- What are you smoking?
- “Friend” cigarettes.
Yes-yes... “Friend” cigarettes...
dog on the label... thirty kopeks...
Normally I smoke “Belomor,” but there wasn’t any.
There wasn’t any “Belomor,” exactly—
that’s why he bought “Friend” cigarettes.
- Who’s “he”?
- The criminal.
What criminal?
A modern one—I’d even say,
a new type of criminal.
What did crooks used to leave
at the crime scene? - What?
Caps, cigarette butts—and now...
Shakespeare!
Don’t be afraid—
there are no bloodstains here!
- So you’re an investigator?
- Yes. I handle car theft cases.
No fingerprints. The criminal works in gloves.
- But you’re not interested?
- No... very interested!
You see, there’s no library stamp, no...
I’m saying: no library stamp,
and no owner’s name.
You know how some people sign their books?
I do, but I don’t sign mine.
There’s a gang operating in the city.
Stealing private cars.
Over the year, four cars have been stolen
from one district.
Three!
There, you’ve heard too.
Yes, three.
They failed to steal the fourth.
But we’ll put an end to this soon.
- How?
- We detained one member of the gang.
A respectable man—an engineer.
Wife’s a doctor. Two kids.
- What does he look like?
- Sort of small.
- Roundish?
- Yes...
- And... and you arrested him?
- Why take such a harsh measure?
He was about to run off to a resort,
but I made him sign a travel restriction.
What if he’s not an accomplice? A respectable man—
and you deprived him of his vacation?
My instinct tells me he’s not guilty.
But the final clarification is a matter
of a few days.
I already know the ringleader’s
distinguishing features...
Tall... wears a raincoat,
a hat, carries a briefcase...
and the main feature—hunched...
And how are you going to catch the ringleader?
Comrades! Everyone for the second half, please!
We’d like a trap for large game.
- Hunting fox, or wolf?
- Bear. - He’s joking.
Tell me... how does it work?
You put the bait here.
- You have bait?
- I do, I do.
The predator smells the bait... sneaks up,
sneaks up... and the beast is caught!
- Lovely!
- Write it up!
- I think it’s all good.
- Lovely! Bring ice cream...
Sima! You’re not in the woods! Guys,
don’t split up! Stick together!
Semitsvetov! Dima!
- She’s blonde!
- Beige-ish!
Guys, when I’ve been drinking, I don’t get behind the wheel.
Take us for a ride, Dima! Take us for a ride,
Dima... Take us for a ride, Di-ma!
Quiet! Quiet! Quiet!
They’ve invented this little tube at the police—
you... phew!
You breathe into it and it immediately shows
whether a person drank or not.
And if you did—they take your license.
- I’m going anyway!
- Sima, this isn’t the beach!
- Why are you lying down? It’s polished!
- So what!
- Listen, I’m r-really smashed!
- Yeah!
I must place myself
in a horizontal position.
- Who is it?
- Lyuba, it’s me!
What is it?
What happened?
Lyuba, you see, they’ve set traps everywhere!
- My God!
I’m miserable, miserable—
I’m so unlucky!
The criminal attempted twice
on the same car.
Not a coincidence. I think he meant
to steal your car specifically.
Reasonable... I figured that out too.
But you shouldn’t set a trap for a living person.
You couldn’t protect us from the bandit,
so we had to take up self-defense.
Why did he latch on to your car in particular?
You don’t suspect anyone
among your acquaintances?
Our acquaintances are perfectly decent people.
Well, perhaps someone envies you?
Envies what? You’re asking strange questions.
Check the clinics—see whether anyone came in
with a characteristic leg injury.
Let’s set up surveillance
on your car!
No, thank you...
We’re putting up a garage tomorrow.
How can you not come? Look, the director will give you a penalty kick!
Ah, your leg hurts! Well then, lie down...
Of course, I’ll pass it on... get well!
- Who’s the one with the leg?
- The right person.
- All right then, call.
- When?
When your car gets stolen.
Dima, they’re taking away Toptunov’s dacha!
- Who’s taking it?
- Are you an idiot?
Daddy, they’re taking away Toptunov’s dacha.
And they’re right to take it—long overdue!
We must fight crooks, for instance.
Why is he a crook? The man knows how to live.
Tell me this: on what salary did the deputy director
of a knitwear factory
build himself a two-story mansion?
- That’s his business!
- No, it’s ours!
We will mercilessly fight those
living on unearned income!
- Hush, Daddy!
- Ah, scared, are you?
I’ll give you a knee, I swear,
and you’ll fly off my land!
Dad, I’m sick of your drill-sergeant humor!
What do you mean, “a knee”? Why?
Why are you getting uppity, son-in-law?
Who do you think you are?
This is my dacha!
Let everyone hear it—this is my dacha!
It’s registered in your name!
But it’s being built with my money.
Prove it!
Oh, stop it already!
You live in this world on a power of attorney!
The car’s in your wife’s name, the dacha’s in mine—
you own nothing. You’re a nobody!
Why! Why do I have to live like this?
Lord, why? Why?
I, a man with a university degree,
have to hide, adapt,
wiggle, maneuver! Why can’t I live
freely, openly?
Oh, when will it all end! Never!
What do you even mean by that?
Do you know what I can,
plain and simple,
do to you for this?
- I know... I know...
- He’s scared!
Have pity on him, Daddy!
This type must always remember
who I am! And he’s a common crook!
Still, I ought to give you a knee!
- Who is it?
- Lyuba, it’s me!
- What happened? Another trap?
- No, this time it all worked out.
You’re leaving? On a trip?
Now? At night?
It’s not my fault... I have to...
because, you see,
a “business trip” is quite
a complicated undertaking.
Lyuba! Why get
so upset.
I’ll be back in a few days.
I’ll write to you from there. Do you hear?
Lyuba! I’m very upset too.
See?
Hello. You know, our right turn signal sticks.
And when shifting gears,
there’s this sound...
We’ll listen.
And the day before yesterday the whole day
the car smelled of gasoline.
We’ll sniff.
Where’s the car?
- Comrade chief...
- Hello!
I see you’re driving alone. Help me,
please, start this heap of junk.
- Start a motorcycle?
- Yes. Can’t manage it alone.
No, it’s just the battery’s dead.
I’ve asked the bosses a thousand times
to move me to a new motorcycle.
Yeah... with an old battery
it’s no life.
- So? Three-four, ready?
- Let’s try.
Come on, get a running start!
A running start, a running start.
- All right... stop! I see you’re worn out.
- A bit.
- Now let me give you a ride.
- What’s the point?
Listen, pal. Let’s hook it to your Volga.
Do you have a tow rope?
Who knows what’s in there...
I don’t remember. I’ll look now.
Got a tow rope!
Great!
All right! Thanks, pal, you saved me.
- Man to man is a friend.
- Exactly.
Trouble happened to me—you helped me.
If it happens to you—I’ll help.
And together we do one common cause:
you in your way, and I in mine.
Tell me, pal, is there a telegraph around here?
Not far. Hop on, I’ll show you.
Please grant five days unpaid leave
due to the sudden grave
condition... grave condition...
of my beloved nephew.
All right, all right... I understand!
I’m writing... done.
- Taking a rest?
- Uh-huh...
- Something happen?
- No, nothing, nothing.
- Who’s the owner?
- Me.
Car documents.
Sorry.
A chase! What detective plot
can do without one?
One runs, the other gives chase—
such is the immutable law of the genre.
A detective without a chase is like
life without love.
Detochkin loved children. He couldn’t do otherwise.
Detochkin understood it was the end.
He wanted to close his eyes,
but he was afraid of running over a Young Pioneer.
But the inspector also loved children
and was no less noble than Detochkin.
- Got you, brother!
- Yeah, got me!
You won’t get away from the police... damn it!
Hold on a second!
- You... you wait, don’t drive off!
- What is it, brother?
What, what... well, again, you see,
the battery...
I warned you. With an old battery—it’s no life.
I always feared it. Important work comes up,
and it lets me down.
There! They didn’t move me
to a new motorcycle.
My sympathies.
- Bad luck for you.
- But good luck for you!
Between the two of us, someone had to get lucky.
So what do we do, brother?
And why were you running from me?
Habit. You chase, I run.
And I’ve got a habit too. You run,
I chase... you could’ve gotten out, helped.
We could’ve hooked it to your Volga,
like last time.
No way! I’ve already seen how you repay kindness.
Sorry!
Stop interfering!
Look, the police!
Lock the garage! Proceed!
Lift!
Lower!
I always said he was
a talented criminal.
Maybe even... more talented
than me.
Good grief, all the money is in one-ruble notes!
Don’t distract me, or I’ll have to start over.
Five thousand five hundred! That’s it!
Why is all your money in one-ruble notes?
That’s suspicious. Not good!
And what are you, a prosecutor?
I’m not asking where the car came from,
why there are no documents.
And I can be frank.
I stole this car.
I can be frank too. I’m a pastor.
These rubles are donations to him! Come on!
Just a little left!
And you believe in God?
Everyone believes—some believe
God exists, others believe He doesn’t.
Neither can be proven!
Going to recount?
I am!
There! As promised...
a Grundig tape recorder.
But is it new?
- Absolutely new. Personally checked it.
- Then write it up. I remember everything.
- Eighty!
- What? You said fifty!
- Personal circumstances have changed.
- You know, that’s plain robbery!
I’m not insisting. It’ll be gone in a second.
A classy item...
- ...four tracks... stereo.
- Write it up!
Citizen, it’s sold. Don’t touch it with your hands.
It’s sold.
Why did he still want to steal your car specifically?
- What’s wrong with you?
- They caught me...
I’m done for... an investigator came to see me.
You steal — you get locked up.
Semyon Vasilyevich, this is my house.
— Your house is jail.
Your house is jail.
Inka, Inka! What do we do? What do we do?
Inka, what do we do?
Pack a toothbrush.
Dima, don’t worry! You’ve got to grease
the investigator’s palm!
Are you out of your mind? Grease his palm!
You’re crazy!
- Give him a lot! Then he’ll take it!
- Silence! Attention!
I won’t allow it! Shame!
Dad, take your lectures back to your market stall.
I sell strawberries grown
with my own hands.
And for bribes, not only a son-in-law—
I’ll grind my own daughter into dust!
It’s fine! Prison will re-educate you.
In ten years you’ll come back
a different man!
Put the little bird down!
One should marry an orphan...
Don’t doubt it, I have that money—
here... a full briefcase.
Do you really want to transfer
- ...this amount to an orphanage?
- Yes.
Were you raised in that home?
Are these your personal savings?
Well, how to put it... generally...
I had a hand in it too.
Hello! I need Yury Ivanovich Detochkin.
- I’m Yura’s mother.
- Very nice to meet you.
I’m from the people’s theater.
I’m very glad Yura acts in the theater.
- I think he has ability.
- He has real talent.
- He missed rehearsal...
- Dearie, he’s on a business trip.
I hate his “business trips.”
He bolts in the middle of the night, disappears.
Lyuba’s right—something’s not right.
Lyuba is Yura’s fiancée.
He’s so... old-fashioned.
He’s been courting her for ages.
They met when he came
to insure her...
Tell me, what kind of business trips
can an insurance agent have?
- What’s your profession?
- Investigator.
Then you figure it out!
When I was young,
an investigator courted me.
But I married a Red Army soldier.
We sang: “Our locomotive races ahead,
the commune is our stop!”
- And when did he leave, and for how long?
- Three days ago, at night.
And the strangest thing: he came to say goodbye
to Lyuba in some Volga.
- Ah! He took a taxi!
- No, he was driving himself.
- Does Yury Ivanovich drive?
- Yura? He worked as a driver for 10 years.
Then he had an accident, got a concussion.
The doctors advised him not to drive for a while,
so he became an insurance agent.
What’s wrong?
To what city did you send
your employee Detochkin
on a business trip?
I didn’t send him anywhere.
Detochkin has a great many
chronically ill relatives
in different cities of the Soviet Union.
I recently received
a telegram... here it is. Here.
His next beloved nephew fell ill.
He took unpaid leave.
Maxim was beside himself. Memories
burned his heart.
How cleverly Detochkin hid his interest
in the hunt for the ringleader! Hypocrite!
How he stole a car
with the help of a crane!
A vile schemer, a thief!
He betrayed what was dearest—friendship!
And there is no mercy for such a man.
Mom? It’s me. I just arrived...
I’m fine... is everything calm at home?
Did anyone come by?
You’ve played yourself with that people’s theater.
An investigator stopped by to see you.
- Defend yourself, sir!
- At your service...
I have the honor to attack you...
- Where have you been?
- Damn it, I was on a business trip!
And how is the nephew?
- What nephew?
- The beloved one!
And the wolf trap? And the bad leg?
And “Friend” cigarettes?
Stop ad-libbing! In Shakespeare’s time
there were no “Friend” cigarettes!
And besides, why have you switched
to prose?
- Podberezovikov!
- Yes?
What do you keep thinking about?
Stop it! Stop waving your saber!
What a blow!
Easy!
- Where is he?
- He’s coming to!
- Alive!
- Break!
- How many cars did you sell?
- Four.
Let’s say four. A decent sum—
a whole fortune.
Where did you come from like this:
a mother so nice, singing about locomotives?
- Excuse me, are you crazy?
- No, I even have a certificate.
Some actor!
I always said: a real crook,
as a rule, is a good actor!
You stole only from those you considered crooks.
I figured it out right away!
Think the court will shave off a year or two?
Where do you hide your capital?
- Here.
- Aha! I see!
Hello! Why didn’t you tell me at once?
Please go with your friend
to a separate office.
Raya! Lyuda!
They’ll bring fresh beer in a moment—
just delivered—and serve dried roach...
- And the fish was just caught!
- Your friend’s a joker!
Tell me, is there any news
about the car?
There will be soon.
- Let’s go from here.
- Let’s stay a little longer, if we may.
I doubt they’ll feed me in prison
the way they do here.
- What’s that?
- A change of underwear, just in case.
- And this?
- Certificates, receipts, documents...
- What documents? Where’s the money?
- That is the money.
What? You transferred the money
to children’s homes?
Uh-huh.
- And how much did you keep for yourself?
- I kept nothing.
Only for travel and per diem.
Yes, dear viewer, Detochkin
didn’t take the money for himself.
He may be a thief, but he’s
a selfless, honest man.
They spread accounting documents on the table.
That’s an audit... bring them our “house beer.”
Right.
I didn’t sell the first car.
I left it with the police in Kursk.
I stuck a detailed explanation note
to the windshield
and went to the station and returned
to Moscow.
And... with the second car,
an injustice happened.
I drove it to the police too,
and left a note too,
that the owner was a crook!
But they returned it to the owner...
that’s when I decided to sell them!
I love you!
Here! The warrant for your arrest!
And now give it to me!
Take it!
- And now I’ll tear it up!
- Maxim! Maxim. Don’t you dare!
- Yura!
- Don’t you dare! You’ll get in trouble!
Maxim! Guys! We’re friends! Guys!
Dad! Everything’s fine! Dad!
Everything’s fine! Dad!
Then take it for yourself!
I’m giving it to you as a gift!
Come in! Goodbye!
Goodbye!
Friend! Friend!
If I fall ill, I won’t go
to the doctors.
I’ll turn to my friends—
don’t think I’m delirious...
Listen, friend! Don’t lock me up
before the premiere, I beg you!
I won’t lock you up at all.
Live free!
What a part! It happens once in a lifetime, you know?
Play the premiere and all
the performances after it.
- ...not the ones after.
- No, you must, you must!
- Oh, you dear!
- I’m going to Lyuba!
Don’t get run over!
Why did you do it? Who asked you?
Who made you?
Look at yourself.
You’re... an idiot.
You reason like
a three-year-old child.
Why are you sitting there? Stand up!
What am I to do? My God!
Did you think about me? No? No.
You always thought only of yourself.
They’ll lock you up, Yura.
- And rightly so.
- Not rightly so.
Button up. I’ll wait for you, Yura.
Five years, eight years, ten years.
Thank you... ten... ten, so then
I’ll be forty-six.
Yes, that’s, of course...
- My God!
- What have I gotten myself into!
- Into what, huh? Into what?
No, just look,
what you look like...
And what do I look like?
My God, you’ve ruined my whole life,
Yurochka!
Yura!
- Good morning! It’s me!
- Hi!
Have you heard that today
a car was stolen again?
And today, have you looked out the window?
Hello? Hello! Why are you silent?
You’re looking out the window, aren’t you?
So, how is it?
Why did you do it?
Since when have you started stealing
cars from honest people?
Where are your principles?
Oh no! That’s Stelkin’s car—
and he’s a bribe-taker.
What Stelkin? It belongs to a famous scientist!
A Doctor of Sciences!
One moment, I’ll check the card index.
His card index! His card index!
Wretched bureaucrat!
It’s Stelkin’s car—
and he’s a bribe-taker.
It can’t be... did I really make a mistake!
You will drive the Volga back
to its owner immediately. And to you I advise...
Come to me, as they say,
with your things!
And the performance?
There will be no performance!
Come in!
Here is the report on the work done.
The warrant... for my arrest.
Good evening!
- Congratulations on the premiere!
- Same to you.
They brought me such a funny wig!
Why do you need a wig?
Your whole life has been spent in makeup.
And why are you talking about my life
as if it’s already in the past?
Because tomorrow is the trial.
You’re facing five years.
I have mitigating circumstances.
I’m an honest man.
What kind? That you stole cars
from one crook and sold them to another?
Well, my work had some shortcomings.
And who doesn’t?
You, for example, couldn’t catch me
for a very long time.
It’s hard to catch a man
who leads a double life!
I-it always weighed on me terribly,
tormented me.
Uh... tie my bow.
No good deed can be accompanied
by lies and deception.
Imagine that! You took it upon yourself
to pass judgment, to mete out punishment.
To be honest, it’s all foolishness
and a crime.
Defendant, where are you going?
So you also believe
- ...that I’m guilty?
- Yes!
Comrades, the house is full.
Everyone to the stage, please.
Yes, don’t forget to say: “To be or not to be?”
And you’re not ready again?
Here, Hamlet, my handkerchief! Wipe your brow!
The Queen drinks to your success, Hamlet.
But the third time, Laertes, no joking.
Fight with full strength.
- Do you think me a weakling?
- You imagine it? Begin!
Let us forgive each other, noble Hamlet.
Be pure before heaven! I follow you!
Horatio!
- I am dying... mother... farewell!
- Yura, I’m here!
All rise! Court is in session!
We continue the hearing.
Detochkin broke the law, and the law,
as is known, doesn’t like jokes.
In all the judge’s practice,
there has never been such a strange, paradoxical case.
By law, Detochkin faced
imprisonment for up to five years.
Detochkin is not simply a thief. He’s worse!
He’s a bandit!
He must be tried for
armed banditry with breaking and entering!
This type took a swing at what is most sacred to us!
At the Constitution!
It states: “Every person has the right to personal property.
It is protected by law.” Every person has the right to have a car,
a dacha, books... money! Comrades,
money has not yet been abolished.
From each according to ability, to each
according to his labor—in hard cash.
Criminal proceedings have been initiated
against witness Semitsvetov.
Dad! - It’s fine, it’s fine, you’ll find yourself another one—an honest one!
If the future of Dima Semitsvetov
now looked fairly clear,
the fate of Yury Ivanovich Detochkin
still remained uncertain.
At last the court called
the most important witness, Maxim Podberezovikov.
Esteemed comrades judges.
At first I led this case
as an investigator.
But when it turned out that
the defendant is my friend,
I withdrew from the case
and now speak
only as a witness.
I understand, comrades judges, you face
a difficult task:
Detochkin violated the law, but he did so
with noble intentions.
He sold cars, but
gave the money to children.
He is, of course, guilty,
but he... is not guilty.
Have pity on him, comrades judges:
he is a good man.
And an excellent worker!
If you don’t know, then be silent.
Free Yuri Detochkin! Yura!
Quiet! I demand silence, or I will immediately
order the hall cleared!
Defendant, you are given
your final word.
Citizens judges, perhaps I
acted wrongly,
but from a pure heart.
I... couldn’t stand it.
They steal, they steal a lot... I wanted
to help you, citizens judges.
Please let me go!
I won’t do it again...
I swear I won’t!
As is already known, the audience loves detective films.
It’s nice to watch a film,
already knowing how it ends.
This unbelievable story,
which no one knows where took place,
or whether it took place at all,
is coming to an end.
Hello, Lyuba. I’m back.
Russian subtitles at
http://subtitles.ee
29.09.2003
.