But the need to fill the void left
in its place remains. And while another
character from Dostoevsky's "Demons" says,
"If there is no God, then what kind of captain
am I after that?" Kirillov declares,
"If there is no God, then I can take his
place."
Remember, Grebenshchikov sang: "Do you feel
the draft from that empty space?"
Kirillov feels that very draft, and
he formulates a terrifying, insane idea
that he himself later falls in love with:
if a person, he says, dares to declare his
will and simply, not out of anger,
fear, or malice, but just because he
has the right, decides to leave this life,
then, Kirillov argues, with this step
he will transform all of humanity and
himself become a human God.
At a step, all of humanity, and he himself
will become a god to people.
But there have already been millions of suicides,
they tell him, yet all not for this,
all with fear and not with this purpose, Kirillov replies.
And this insane approach of his remarkably
recalls an episode from Don Quixote.
Remember when the audacious and
far-reaching Sancho Panza says that he plans
to imitate the noble knights of yore and
go mad.
The pragmatic Sancho then asks: "But
do you have a reason to go mad, señor?
What reason?"
"That's precisely the point," answers Don Quixote.
"The peculiarity of my venture is
that
if a knight-errant goes mad
for any reason,
don't ask for reward or gratitude."
Did the knight go mad for some reason?
Don't ask for any reward or gratitude.
The whole trick is to go crazy
without any reason at all.