[Music
At night, somewhere around one o'clock, in a small
provincial town without a specific
name, a young man about 27 years old
enters a solitary wooden outhouse in the yard
to visit a construction engineer, who is
sitting on a couch with a latticed back and
firm leather
cushions. Almost immediately, he notices that on
the window, there is a plate with an untouched boiled
chicken.
My name is Armen Zakharian, this is
the literary channel "Armen and Fedor,"
and today we are launching a new segment
called "Episode." In this segment, we
will closely examine a single
fragment from the pages of world literature and
explore why this episode is special
and how what we call art works within it.
.
chose one of the most eerie yet intriguing
scenes from Fyodor Dostoevsky's novel "Demons."
This is an episode from almost the very
end of the book, from its
concluding part. There, a certain
Verkhovensky comes at night to the house of
a certain Kirillov and sees a chicken
cooked with rice on the window.
And although there is a loaded gun right
next to the chicken, it is not the gun, but the
chicken that fulfills the role
of Chekhov's gun in this scene, which is about to
go off. However, to understand what
this shot is and at whom it is directed, one must
first understand who these two are and how
they ended up together in one room at night
in the wing.
It's interesting how right at the beginning of the book
while just introducing us to
the characters, Dostoevsky already
lays the groundwork for their
eerie nocturnal encounter. Kirillov is
depicted as a young man, about 27 years old;
Verkhovensky is almost a mirror image:
a young man, about 27 years old.
This deliberate similarity, of course, only
emphasizes how deep the differences between
them are. Kirillov is a vivid representative
of Dostoevsky's famous series of fanatic
heroes, characters who become overly
passionate about an idea, begin to serve that
idea, and live for its sake.
Only Kirillov has a different plan—he intends to die for the idea.
He is obsessed with the notion of a human-god.
He arrives at this through a problem that
literature in the second half of the 19th century
often attempted to solve: how should a person
live after renouncing God?
Suppose God no longer exists. Suppose we
no longer believe in Him, we have, as
Verkhovensky would put it, deconstructed Him.
But the need to fill the void left in His place
remains.
And while another character in Dostoevsky's
"Demons" says, "If there is no God, then what kind
of captain am I after that?", Kirilov says
"If there is no God, then I can take His
place."
Remember, Grebenshchikov sang: "Do you feel
the draft from the fact that this place is vacant?".
Kirillov feels that very draft, and
he formulates a terrifying, insane thought,
which he later falls in love with himself. If
a person, he says, decides to assert their
will and, just like that—not out of anger,
fear, or rage, but solely because
they have the right and are justified—leaves this life,
then, Kirillov reasons, this step will transform
all of humanity, and they themselves will become
a human-God.
"But there have already been millions of suicides,"
he's told, "but not for that reason, all
with fear and not for that purpose," Kirillov replies.
And this crazy approach of his strangely
resembles an episode from Don
Quixote. Remember when daring and far away,
says Sancho Panza, he plans
to emulate the glorious knights of the past
and go mad.
"But do you have a reason to go mad,
señor? What reason?"
"That's the whole point," Don Quixote replies.
"The peculiarity of my undertaking
lies precisely in that. If a knight-errant
goes mad for some reason,
don't expect any reward or gratitude.
The trick is to go insane without any motive."
.
And as we will soon see,
these echoes in the words of Kirillov
and Quixote are far from accidental.
.