But the need to fill the void in its place, that remains.
And while another character in Dostoevsky's "Demons" says,
"If there is no God, then what kind of captain am I?"
Kirillov says, "If there is no God, then I can take His place."
Remember, Grebenshikov sang:
"Do you feel the draft because this place is vacant?"
Kirillov feels that very draft, and
formulates a terrifying, insane thought
that he later falls in love with.
"If a person," he says,
"decides to express their will,
not out of anger, fear, or malice,
but simply because they have the right,
and leaves life, then,"
Kirillov argues, "this step will transform
all humanity and he himself
will become a man-god."
Step by step, all of humanity
and even God Himself will become human.
"But there have already been millions of suicides,"
they tell him, "all in vain, all with fear and not for that purpose,"
Kirillov replies.
And his insane approach remarkably resembles
an episode from "Don Quixote."
Remember when Sancho Panza says daringly
and far ahead that he plans to emulate
the glorious knights of the past and go mad.
The pragmatic Sancho then asks,
"But do you have a reason to go mad, sir?
What could the reason be?"
— "That's the whole point,"
Don Quixote answers.
"That's the peculiarity of my planned undertaking.
If a knight-errant goes mad
for some reason, don't expect any reward or gratitude."
.
If a knight has gone mad for any reason,
don’t ask for rewards or
gratitude. The whole point is
to go mad without any reason.
And, as we’ll soon see, these echoes
in the words of Kirillov and Quixote are
far from coincidental.