But the need to fill the void in its place remains.
And while another of Dostoevsky's characters in the same "Demons" says,
"If there is no God, then what kind of captain am I after that?",
Kirillov says, "If there is no God, then I can take his place."
Remember, Grebenshchikov sang: "Do you feel the draft
because that place is free?"
Kirillov feels that very draft, and he formulates a terrifying, insane idea,
which he then falls in love with: if a person, he says,
dares to assert his will and leaves life
not out of anger, not out of fear, not out of malice,
but solely because he has the right,
then, Kirillov reasons,
this step will transform all of humanity and
he himself will become a God-like figure for mankind.
and he himself will become
a God-like figure for mankind.
By step all humanity and himself will become
a God of man.
But there have already been millions of suicides,
they tell him.
"But that's not the point,
all with fear and not for that," Kirillov objects.
And his insane approach
in an amazing way resembles one episode from "Don
Quixote." Remember when the adventurous and
far-reaching, says Sancho Panza,
plan to emulate the glorious knights of the past
and go mad.
The pragmatic Sancho then asks:
"But do you have a reason to go mad, sir? What reason?!"
"That's the whole point," replies Don Quixote.
"That's the uniqueness of my endeavor.
Those wandering knights
who went mad for any reason,
don't ask for reward or gratitude."
.
The knights went mad for some reason.
He asked for neither rewards nor thanks.
The whole point is to
lose one's mind without any cause.