But the need to fill
the void in its place, that still remains. And
while another Dostoevsky character in the same
"Demons" says: "if there is no God, then what
kind of captain am I"; Kirillov says
if there is no God, then I can take his
place.
Remember, Grebenshchikov sang: "do you feel
the draft from the fact that this place is vacant?"
Kirillov feels that same draft, and
he formulates a terrifying, insane idea, in
which he then falls in love himself: "if a
person," he says, "dares to declare
declare his will and simply, not from anger
fear, nor from rage, but precisely only
only because he has the right, leaves this life,
then, argues Kirillov, he will transform
all of humanity with his step and himself become
.
Marching all of humanity and oneself will become
God to man.
But there have already been millions of suicides,
they tell him. - But never...
Then everything with fear. - And not for that reason,
Kirillov retorts.
And this mad approach of his surprisingly
resembles an episode from "Don
Quixote." Remember when the daring hidalgo
tells Sancho Panza that he plans to
emulate the glorious knights of the past and
go mad.
The pragmatic Sancho then asks: "But do you
have a reason to go mad, señor? What
is the reason?"
"That's the whole point," Don Quixote replies. "That's
the peculiarity of the enterprise
I have devised. Whoever among the wandering
knights went mad for some reason,
do not ask for reward or gratitude."
Knights for some reason went mad,
neither asking for rewards
nor gratitude. The whole
point is to go insane without
any reason.