Yet the need to fill the void still remains.
While another character in Dostoevsky's "Demons" questions,
"If there is no God, what kind of captain am I after that?",
Kirillov asserts, "If there is no God,
then I can take his place."
Remember how Grebenshchikov sang,
"Do you feel the draft because this place is vacant?"
Kirillov feels that exact draft and
formulates a terrifying, mad thought
that captivates him.
If a person, he says,
dares to assert their own will—
not out of anger, fear, or malice,
but simply because they have the right—
and departs from life,
then, argues Kirillov, this act will
regenerate humanity
and transform them into
a human-God.
Step by step, all of humanity
and he himself will become God as man.
But there have already been millions of suicides,
people tell him, yet still not all.
Kirillov objects, saying that their actions
are driven by fear, not for that purpose.
His seemingly irrational approach
astonishingly resembles an episode from
'Don Quixote.' Remember the moment when the
daring hidalgo himself, Don Quixote,
aspires to emulate the noble knights of yore
and descend into madness?
The pragmatic Sancho Panza then questions,
'But do you have a reason to go mad, señor?
What is the reason?'
'That's the whole point,' Don Quixote replies.
'That’s the uniqueness of the quest I've devised.
Any knight-errant who has gone mad
for a particular reason
neither seeks reward nor gratitude.'
The knight-errants went mad for some reason.
He neither sought rewards nor thanks:
the trick was to
lose one's wits without any cause.
And as we will soon see,
these echoes in
the words of Kirillov and Quixote are far from