[Music]
At night, around one o'clock, in a small
provincial town without a specific
name, a young man of about 27 or so
enters
a solitary wooden wing in the yard to visit
a civil engineer sitting on a sofa with
a latticed back and hard leather
cushions. Almost immediately, he notices that
on the window there is a plate with an
untouched boiled
chicken.
My name is Armen Zakharian, this is
the literary channel "Armen and Fedor", and
today we are launching a new segment —
"Episode". In it, we will
closely examine a single
fragment from the pages of world literature and
explore why this episode is special
and how what we call art
works within it. And for the first
such experience, we
and how what we call art works in it.
For our first such experience we
chose one of the creepiest yet most
interesting scenes from Fyodor
Dostoevsky's novel "Demons". This is an episode
from nearly the very end of the book,
from its final part. In it, a certain
Verkhovensky comes at night to the house of
a certain Kirillov and sees a chicken
cooked with rice on the window.
And although there is a loaded gun right next
to the chicken, it is not the gun but
the chicken itself that serves as the
Chekhov's gun in this scene, poised to
"fire" at any moment. However, to understand
what this shot is and whom it is aimed at,
one must first figure out who these two are
and how they ended up together in a room
at night in the wing.