[Music
At around one o'clock at night, in a small
provincial town with no specific
name, a young man of about 27 or so
enters a solitary wooden annex in the yard
to visit a civil engineer
sitting on a sofa with a latticed back and
firm leather cushions. He almost
immediately notices that on the
window there's a plate with an untouched boiled
chicken
My name is Armen Zakharyan, this is the
literature channel "Armen and Fyodor,"
and today we are launching a new segment
called "Episode." In it, we will
each time closely examine a single
passage from the pages of world literature and
explore why this episode is special
and how what we call art operates within it
for this first experience.
chose one of the creepiest, yet most
interesting scenes from Fyodor Dostoevsky's
novel "Demons." This episode almost
occurs near the very end of the book, in its
concluding part: a certain
Verkhovensky comes at night to the house of
a certain Kirillov and sees
a chicken boiled with rice on the window.
And although there is a loaded gun
lying right next to the chicken, it is
not the gun, but the chicken that plays the role
of Chekhov's gun, which is
about to go off. However to understand what
this shot is about and who it is aimed at,
one first needs to understand who these two are and how
they ended up
in a room together at night in the annex.