[Music]
At night, around one o'clock, in a small provincial town
without a specific name
a young man around 27 years old
enters a solitary wooden
annex in the yard
visiting a civil engineer sitting on a couch with a
with a lattice back and firm leather cushions
Almost immediately, he notices that there is a plate
with an untouched boiled chicken on the window
My name is Armen Zakharayan. This is
the literary channel "Armen and Fyodor"
and today we are launching a new section
In each episode,
we will carefully examine just one fragment
from the pages of world literature
and understand why it is special
and how what we call art works in it.
For our first such experience, we have
chosen one of the most sinister, yet
intriguing scenes from the novel 'The Demons' by Fyodor Dostoevsky
It is an episode, almost at the very
end of the book, from its final part
There, a certain Verkhovensky comes at
night to the house of
a certain Kirillov and sees
a boiled chicken with rice on the window.
although right next to the chicken lies a loaded pistol,
it is not the pistol,
but the chicken that plays the role of Chekhov's gun,
which is about to fire
However, to understand what this shot is
about and at whom it is aimed,
we first need to figure out, who these two are and how
they ended up here,
in one room at night in the annex