The audience loves detective films.
It’s nice to watch a film
already knowing how it ends.
And in general, it’s flattering
to feel smarter than the authors.
Residents of the capital claim
this incredible story
happened in Moscow.
People from Odessa insist
it happened in their city.
Leningrad and Rostov-on-Don
disagree.
Seven cities dispute it
in exactly the same way
as seven cities call themselves
Homer’s birthplace.
It must be said that it’s unknown
where this story took place,
or whether it took place
at all.
So, as you’ve noticed,
it was a dark night.
The unknown man tried very hard
to remain unnoticed,
and he succeeded.
It was so dark, quiet,
and deserted here
that one almost couldn’t help
wanting to commit a crime.
- Call Post No. 2-06V...
- Yes, sir!
- Block all the highways!
Get me the photos urgently—
- ...of the tire tread prints!
- Yes, sir!
Tanya! And you—find out about the fingerprints.
So, the third car has been stolen
from the same district.
It’s the same hand at work—
experienced and skillful!
That hand works in cotton gloves
from Factory No. 8.
Then it’s not Fedka “Gold Tooth.”
And what did the oil analysis show—
the oil the criminal so loves
to pour over garage hinges?
The oil turned out to be refined.
And did you notice that in the courtyard
where the theft occurred,
and on the street nearby,
a lot of cars without garages spend the night?
Yes.
And stealing a car from the street
is easier than from a garage, right?
That’s a very accurate observation.
If we apply Stanislavsky’s doctrine
of the “super-objective,”
an interesting thought arises:
the criminal is taking the path
of greatest resistance. Why?
Once we uncover his super-objective,
we’ll catch him.
That’s brilliant!
Comrade investigator, I forgot
to report one detail—
- ...maybe it will help.
- I’m listening, comrade victim.
On my rear fender, someone scratched
an obscene word with a nail...
Wait... so... which one?
Hello, Lyuba. I’m back.
Comrades! Fill the vehicle faster.
Don’t bunch up at the back.
Yuri Ivanovich, the trolleybus entrance
is on the other side.
Coming.
- Hello, Yakov Mikhailovich!
- Hello, Detochkin!
- So, how is your uncle from Dushanbe?
- Uncle? Bad.
Last time it was an aunt from Moldavia...
A cousin!
- No, but you said...
- She passed away.
Yeah... we’re all mortal, Detochkin...
we’re all mortal.
And if people didn’t die,
we wouldn’t be able to insure them
against death.
You won’t deny, Detochkin,
that I show you consideration.
Every time your relatives fall ill or die,
I grant you
unpaid leave.
You’re an exceptionally considerate boss.
That’s right, Detochkin, but
you have a great many relatives...
and I have very few staff positions.
You see, your departures
throw off our plan.
I’ll make it up!
Understand, I can’t put
family interests
above public ones.
- I... I’ll make it up!
- Then go and make it up.
A policeman stopped me yesterday.
The power of attorney is invalid.
You need to stop by and have it notarized
at the notary office.
- Sign here, please.
- Dima, sign it!
To be honest, I don’t even know myself
why I insure my property.
What about fires?
It would be a shame if such property
burned down for nothing.
Maybe we should insure
our car?
Have you bought a car?
Car insurance is provided
in case of total loss
or an accident due to collisions
or natural disasters.
- And in case of theft?
- In case of theft—no.
I’m not rich enough
to pay for natural disasters
as well.
- And where do you keep it?
- Come here!
Beige... not a flashy color...
and you don’t have a garage?
Not yet.
I’m working on it, but it’s
a difficult matter.
They promise to allocate a spot... so
no garage yet.
But I’ve already gotten a lock—Japanese,
no key can be picked for it.
Yes, hard to pick... even a lock pick
won’t do it.
You’d need an acetylene torch, and cutting
with a torch... that’s such a hassle...
My clever one.
- Need a lift?
- We’re not going the same way.
Suit yourself!
Everyone who doesn’t have a car
dreams of buying one.
And everyone who has a car
dreams of selling it,
and doesn’t do it only because
after selling it, you’re left without a car.
Man, more than any other living creature,
loves creating
additional difficulties for himself.
That is exactly what explains the desire
to have one’s own car.
The thought that five and a half thousand
have simply been thrown into the gutter
can poison any happy life.
- Mom!
- You’re here!
I can’t understand what kind of business trips
an insurance agent could have.
Why are you standing there? Lunch is ready,
go wash your hands.
What heavy things are you carrying
in your briefcase?
Necessary things for work.
It’s scary to look at you—
you’ve gotten so thin and drawn...
Korchnoi won the chess tournament...
I was rooting for Tal.
He fell behind by half a point...
Don’t laugh at your mother.
These business trips seem suspicious
not only to me...
To whom else?
You’re eating onion soup by the recipe
of the great writer Dumas père.
Lyuba finds these trips suspicious. She’s right.
She doesn’t want to marry
a bungler.
- Did she tell you that?
No, not now. He’s only just arrived.
That evening, Maxim Podberezovikov
was moving in an unknown direction.
From the other end of the city, in an even more
unknown direction,
Yuri Detochkin was walking.
They were heading toward their fate.
They were drawing closer.
Every investigator inevitably has a hobby
to which he devotes time
free from tracking criminals.
Sherlock Holmes, for example, played the violin,
Maxim Podberezovikov—
amateur theatre.
...The development of folk amateur art is moving
forward by leaps and bounds.
The spirit of the times has finally touched
us as well—our amateur groups.
They’ve begun consolidating us, creating
people’s theatres—one might say,
forming “all-star teams” from club troupes.
Today is a festive day for us.
Today we are creating a new people’s theatre.
I hope it will be a strong organism...
united.
Comrade Detochkin, don’t fuss—sit down.
Within the hospitable walls of our House of Culture
all conditions have been created
so that people of different professions
may be initiated into Melpomene—
who was, as we know, a muse...
Our people’s theatre in particular
is being created, so to speak, from two
friendly collectives. Uh... from
the police collective and, uh... drivers.
- I recognized you.
- That’s not me.
But... you said: “And who are the judges?”
I didn’t say anything like that about judges.
You did, you did...
Weren’t you the one who played Chatsky?
I... I completely forgot...
And now we’ll be acting with you
in the same production.
- I’m very glad!
- So am I!
There is an opinion that people’s theatres
will soon... displace...! At last...
professional theatres!
And that’s right!
An actor who doesn’t get a salary
will act with greater inspiration.
Besides,
an actor must work somewhere...
It’s wrong if he spends the whole day,
you understand, hanging around the theatre.
Just imagine how much better Yermolova
would have acted in the evening if during the day she...
you understand... worked...
at a grinding machine.
The title of “people’s theatre”
carries many obligations.
Whom haven’t we played
in our groups!
Isn’t it time, my friends, for us
to take a swing at William, you know—
our Shakespeare?
And we will!
A transistor radio “Alpinist,” please.
Careful, I beg you.
Excuse me, which of you is Dima?
I’m from Oleg Nikolayevich.
- Which Oleg Nikolayevich?
- A friend of Leonid Osipovich.
I need a foreign tape recorder—
American or German.
Here’s a very good domestic one.
No, a domestic one won’t do.
- A foreign one has to be “sourced.”
- I understand. How much?
- What’s going on, citizen?
- Just looking.
What is this, the zoo?
Go watch the TV over there.
- Fifty.
- Fifty?
- Pull yourself together.
- Need to find one, bring it. Italy?
Need to hold off a bit...
- ...leave your phone number...
- All right.
- A pack of “Belomor,” please.
- No “Belomor.”
Well... what do you have? Then give me
“Drug” cigarettes.
Taxi! Taxi! Taxi!
Would you be so kind! I beg you!
I’m late. Is this your car?
- No.
- But you’re the driver?
No, no.
- Then what are you doing here?
- I want to steal a car, and you’re in the way.
Then please steal it with me—
I’m late for my train.
Ah! Get in. Only then
you become an accomplice.
There! I warned you!
Stop him! There he is! Got him!
Catch him, catch the thief!
Catch him! Don’t let him go!
What a thief!
I’m not a thief! I’m late for my train.
Please—here’s my ticket!
Prepared himself! Look how prudent!
Huh?
Finally! Quick! We caught the crook.
He tried to steal my car!
- Who’s the owner?
- I am... I mean, we are.
I’m not a thief. I was late for the train,
and he took my ticket from me.
- Your documents?
- Here you go. Here’s the ticket.
- And yours.
- What?
- We won’t sort this out here.
Who’s a witness?
- I am. What happened?
I’m not a thief. The thief ran away.
Unfortunately, I didn’t remember his face...
I’m late for my train!
Though I’m already late.
- Is it yours?
- What are you saying! God forbid!
Yes, I’m a witness. I’m a witness. I am.
I look better in profile...
So, I’ll start from the very beginning.
They didn’t deliver “Belomor” to me today.
Well... they didn’t, so they didn’t.
Can you make it shorter?
Young man... in your profession,
there’s no need to hurry.
“Belomor” is a detail for the investigation!
And that very man
who climbed into your car,
also asked for “Belomor” first,
and then bought “Drug” cigarettes—
30 kopecks a pack,
with a little dog on the label.
And then I thought:
“Why is he nervous? Why?”
Stop! Stop, stop! What are you thinking about all the time?
Every actor must know the role by heart,
and there’s no need to run senselessly around the stage.
You have to act with your head!
And don’t be rude, or I’ll send you off the field...
uh... off the rehearsal!
- I’m not being rude, I...
- Brea-a-ak!
Yevgeny Alexandrovich, this part:
“Leave me alone, for God’s sake!”
Ah... leave me alone! Break!
- What am I, a little boy to him or what?
- Don’t be upset! Come on...
- What are you smoking?
- “Drug” cigarettes.
Yes, yes... “Drug” cigarettes...
a dog on the label... thirty kopecks...
Usually I smoke “Belomor,” but there wasn’t any.
There wasn’t any “Belomor”—that’s right,
so that’s why he bought “Drug” cigarettes.
- Who is “he”?
- The criminal.
What criminal?
A modern one—I’d even say,
a criminal of a new type.
What did crooks used to leave at the scene?
- What?
Caps, cigarette butts—and now...
Shakespeare!
Don’t be scared—
there are no bloodstains here!
- So you’re an investigator?
- Yes, I handle car theft cases.
No fingerprints. The criminal
works in gloves.
- But you’re not interested?
- No... very interested!
You see, there’s no library stamp, no...
I’m saying: there’s no library stamp,
no owner’s name.
You know how some people
inscribe their books?
I know, but I don’t.
There’s a gang operating in the city.
Stealing private cars.
In a year, four cars were stolen from one district.
Three!
Well, there—you’ve heard too. Yes, three.
They failed to steal a fourth.
But soon it will be over.
- How?
- We detained one member of the gang.
A decent man—an engineer.
Wife’s a doctor. Two kids.
- What does he look like?
- Small.
- Round?
- Yes...
- And... you arrested him?
- Why such a harsh measure?
He was going to run off to a resort, but I made him sign
a pledge not to leave town.
What if he’s not an accomplice? A respectable man,
and you deprived him of his vacation?
My instincts tell me he’s not guilty.
But the final clarification is a matter of a few days.
I already know the ringleader’s distinguishing features...
Tall... wears a raincoat,
a hat, carries a briefcase...
and the main feature—stooped...
And how are you going to catch the ringleader?
Comrades! Everyone to the second half!
We’d like a trap
for a large beast.
- Going after a fox? A wolf?
- A bear.
- He’s joking.
Tell me... how does it work?
You put the bait here.
- Do you have bait?
- Yes, yes.
The predator smells the bait... creeps up...
creeps up... and the beast is caught!
- Wonderful!
- Write it up!
- I think everything’s good.
- Splendid! Bring ice cream...
Simочка! You’re not in the woods! Guys,
don’t split up! Stay with the group!
Semitsvetov! Dima!
- She’s blonde!
- Beige-ish!
Guys, when I’ve been drinking, I don’t get behind the wheel.
Take us for a ride, Dima! Take us for a ride, Dima...
Take us for a ride, Di-ma!
Quiet! Quiet! Quiet!
These days the police have invented a test tube—like...
ugh!
You breathe into it, and it shows at once
whether you’ve been drinking or not.
And if you have—they take your license.
- And I’ll drive anyway!
- Simochka, this isn’t a beach!
- Why are you lying down? That’s the polish!
- Please do!
- Listen, I’m r-really plastered!
- Yeah!
I must put myself
in a horizontal position.
- Who is it?
- Lyuba, it’s me!
What is it?
What happened?
Lyuba, you see, they’ve put traps everywhere!
- Oh my God!
I’m miserable, miserable—
such bad luck!
The criminal tried twice
to steal the same car.
Not a coincidence. I think
he wanted to steal your car specifically.
Reasonable... I figured that out too.
But you shouldn’t have set a trap for a living person.
You failed to protect us from the bandit,
so we had to take up self-defense.
Why is he fixated on your car in particular?
Do you suspect anyone among your acquaintances?
Our acquaintances are quite decent people.
Well, maybe someone
envies you?
Envies what? You ask strange questions.
Query the clinics—
whether anyone came in
with a characteristic leg injury.
Let’s set up surveillance
on your car!
No, thank you...
We’re putting in a garage tomorrow.
You’re not coming? Look, the director will award you a penalty kick!
Ah, your leg hurts! Then lie down...
of course, I’ll pass it on... get well!
- Whose leg?
- The leg! The right person’s leg!
- Well then, call.
- When?
When your car gets stolen.
Dima, they’re taking away Toptunov’s dacha!
- Who’s taking it?
- Are you stupid?
Daddy, they’re taking away Toptunov’s dacha.
And rightly so—high time!
We must fight crooks, for sure.
Why is he a crook? The man knows how to live.
Tell me—on what salary did a deputy director
of a knitwear factory
build himself
a two-story mansion?
- That’s his business!
- No, it’s ours!
We will mercilessly fight those
living on unearned income!
- Be quiet, Daddy!
- Ah, scared!
I’ll knee you, I swear,
and you’ll fly off my property!
Dad, I’m sick of your barracks humor!
What do you mean, “knee”? Why?
Why are you getting uppity, son-in-law?
Who do you think you are?
This is my dacha!
Let everyone hear it—this is my dacha!
It’s registered in your name!
But it’s being built with my money.
Then prove it!
Oh, stop it already, will you?
You live your whole life
by proxy!
The car’s in your wife’s name, the dacha’s in mine—
you own nothing. You’re a nobody!
Why! Why do I have to live like this?
Lord, why? Why?
I, a man with a higher education,
have to hide, adapt,
wriggle out of things! Why can’t I
live freely, openly?
Oh, when will it all end! Never!
And what do you even mean?
Do you know what I can—
quite simply—
do to you for this?
- I know... I know...
- He’s scared!
Have pity on him, Daddy!
That type must always remember who I am!
And he’s a common crook!
Still, I ought to knee you!
- Who is it?
- Lyuba, it’s me!
- What happened? Another trap?
- No, this time it all worked out.
You’re leaving? On a business trip?
Now? At night?
It’s not my fault... I have to...
because, you see,
a business trip is a rather
complicated undertaking.
Lyuba! Why get
so upset.
I’ll be back in a few days.
I’ll write to you from there. Hear me?
Lyuba! I’m very upset too.
See?
Hello. You know, our right turn signal sticks.
And when shifting gears,
there’s this sound...
Let’s listen.
Yes, and the day before yesterday the car smelled of gasoline all day.
Let’s smell.
Where’s the car?
- Comrade chief...
- Hello!
I see you’re driving alone. Help me, please,
start this jalopy.
- Start the motorcycle?
- Yes. Can’t manage alone.
No. The battery’s run down.
I asked the bosses a thousand times
to transfer me to a new motorcycle.
Yeah... with an old battery,
this isn’t living.
- Well? Three, four—go?
- Let’s try.
Come on, give it a running start!
A running start, a running start.
- Well... stop! I see you’re worn out?
- A little.
- Now let me give you a ride.
- What’s the point?
Listen, friend. Let’s hitch it to your Volga.
Do you have a tow rope?
Who knows what’s in there...
I don’t remember. I’ll check now.
There’s a towline!
Great!
All set! Thanks, friend, you saved me.
- Man is a friend to man.
- Exactly.
Misfortune happened to me—you helped.
If it happens to you—I’ll help.
And together we’re doing a common cause:
you in your way, and I in mine.
Tell me, friend, is there a telegraph office around here?
Not far—get in, I’ll show you.
Please grant five days unpaid leave
due to the sudden severe
condition... severe condition...
of my beloved nephew.
All right, all right... I understand! Writing it down...
that’s it!
- Taking a rest?
- Uh-huh...
- Did something happen?
- No, nothing, nothing.
- Who’s the owner?
- Me.
The car documents.
Sorry.
A chase! What detective plot can do without one?
One runs, the other gives chase—
that’s the immutable law of the genre.
A detective story without a chase is like
life without love.
Detochkin loved children.
He couldn’t do otherwise.
Detochkin understood it was the end.
He wanted to close his eyes,
but he was afraid of running over a Young Pioneer.
But the inspector also loved children,
and was no less noble than Detochkin.
- Got you, brother!
- Yeah, you got me!
You can’t get away from the police—what the devil!
Hold on a second!
- You... you wait, don’t drive off!
- What is it, brother?
What, what... well, again, you see,
the battery...
I warned you. With an old battery—this isn’t living.
I always feared this. There’ll be important work,
and it’ll fail.
There! They didn’t transfer me
to a new motorcycle.
My sympathies.
- Bad luck for you.
- But good luck for you!
Of the two of us, someone had to be lucky.
So what do we do, brother?
Why were you running from me?
Habit. You chase, I run.
And I’ve got a habit too. You run,
I chase... you could’ve gotten out and helped.
We could’ve hitched it to your Volga,
like last time.
No way! I’ve already seen how you repay kindness. Sorry!
Don’t interfere!
Look—the police!
Lock the garage! Proceed!
Lift it!
Lower it!
I always said he was
a talented criminal.
Maybe even... more talented than me.
For crying out loud, all the money is in one-ruble bills!
Don’t distract me, or I’ll have
to start over.
Five thousand five hundred! That’s it!
Why are your bills all one-ruble notes?
That’s suspicious. Not good!
And you are what—some prosecutor?
I’m not asking where this car came from,
why there are no documents.
And I can tell you frankly:
I stole this car.
I can tell you frankly too:
I’m a pastor.
These rubles are donations to him! Come on!
Just a little left!
And you believe in God?
Everyone believes—some believe
that God exists, others believe He doesn’t.
Neither can be proven!
Will you recount it?
I will!
Here! As promised—
a Grundig tape recorder.
But is it new?
- Absolutely new. I checked it personally.
- Then write it up. I remember everything.
- Eighty!
- What? You said fifty!
- Personal circumstances have changed.
- You know, that’s just robbery!
I’m not insisting. It’ll be gone in a second.
An elegant item...
- ...four tracks... stereo.
- Write it up!
Citizen, it’s sold. Don’t touch it with your hands.
It’s sold.
Why did he want to steal your car specifically?
- What’s wrong with you?
- I got caught...
I’m finished... an investigator
came to see me.
You’ll get locked up—so don’t steal!
Semyon Vasilyevich!
You’re in my house!
Your home is prison!
Inka, Inka! What do we do? What do we do?
Inka, what do we do?
Start drying crackers!
Dima, don’t worry! You have to slip
the investigator some cash!
Are you out of your mind? Slip him cash!
You’re crazy!
- Give a lot! Then he’ll take it!
- Silence! Attention!
I won’t allow it! Shame!
Dad, with your lectures you should perform at your market.
I sell strawberries grown
with my own hands.
And for bribes, I’d grind not just my son-in-law—
my own daughter into dust!
No matter. Prison will re-educate you.
In ten years you’ll come back
a different person!
Put the bird down!
You should marry an orphan!
Don’t doubt it—I have the money,
here... a full briefcase.
Do you really want to transfer
- ...this sum to an orphanage?
- Yes.
Were you brought up in that home?
Are these your personal savings?
Well, how to put it... in general...
I had a hand in it too.
Hello! I need Yuri
Ivanovich Detochkin.
- I’m Yuri’s mother.
- Very nice to meet you.
I’m from the people’s theatre.
I’m very glad that Yura
is acting in the theatre.
- I think he has ability.
- He’s simply talented.
- He didn’t come to rehearsal...
- Dear, he’s on a business trip.
I hate these business trips.
He tears off in the middle of the night, disappears.
Lyuba is right—something’s not right.
Lyuba is Yura’s fiancée.
He’s kind of old-fashioned.
He’s been courting her for a very long time.
They met when he came
to insure her...
Tell me, what kind of business trips
can an insurance agent have?
- What’s your profession?
- Investigator.
Then you figure it out!
When I was young,
an investigator courted me.
But I married a Red Army soldier.
We used to sing: “Our locomotive rushes ahead,
the next stop is the commune!”
- When did he leave, and for how long?
- Three days ago, at night.
And the strangest thing—he came to say goodbye to Lyuba
in some Volga.
- Ah! He took a taxi!
- No, he himself was behind the wheel.
- Does Yuri Ivanovich drive?
- Yura? He worked as a driver for 10 years.
Then he got into an accident—he had a concussion.
The doctors advised Yura not to drive for the time being,
so he became an insurance agent.
What’s wrong?
To which city did you send
your employee Detochkin
on a business trip?
I didn’t send him anywhere.
Detochkin has a great many
sickly relatives
in different cities of the Soviet Union.
I recently received a telegram...
here it is. Here.
Another of his nephews fell ill—his beloved one.
He took unpaid leave.
Maxim was beside himself.
Memories burned his heart.
How cleverly Detochkin hid his interest
in tracking down the ringleader! Hypocrite!
How he stole a car
with the help of a crane!
A vile schemer—a thief!
He betrayed the most precious thing—friendship!
And such a man deserves no mercy.
Mom? It’s me. I just arrived...
I’m fine... is everything calm at home?
No one came by?
You’ve played around in your people’s theatre enough.
An investigator came to see you.
- Defend yourself, sir!
- At your service...
I have the honor to attack you...
- Where have you been?
- Damn it, I was on a business trip!
And how is the nephew’s health?
- What nephew?
- Your beloved one!
And the wolf trap? And the sore leg?
And the “Drug” cigarettes?
Stop ad-libbing! In Shakespeare’s time there were no “Drug” cigarettes!
And besides, why did you switch to prose?
- Podberezovikov!
- Yes?
What are you thinking about all the time?
Stop it! Stop waving your sword!
What a blow!
Easy!
- Where is he?
- He’s coming to!
- Alive!
- Break!
- How many cars did you sell?
- Four.
Let’s say four. A decent sum—an entire fortune.
Where did you come from like this—
your mother’s so good, sings about the locomotive.
- Excuse me, are you crazy?
- No, I even have a certificate.
Some actor!
I always said: a real crook
is usually a good actor!
You only stole from those you considered crooks.
I guessed it right away!
Do you think they’ll cut a year or two off at trial?
Where do you hide your capital?
- Here.
- Aha! Right!
Hello! Why didn’t you tell me right away?
Please, you and your friend
come to a separate office.
Raya! Lyuda!
They’ll bring fresh beer now,
just delivered, and they’ll serve dried fish...
- And the fish was just caught!
- Your friend’s a joker!
Tell me, any news
about the car?
Soon.
- Let’s go.
- Let’s stay a little longer, if I may.
I doubt they’ll feed me in prison
like they do here.
- What’s that?
- A change of clothes, just in case.
- And this?
- Certificates, receipts, documents...
- What documents? Where’s the money?
- That is the money.
What? You transferred
the money to orphanages?
Uh-huh.
- And how much did you keep for yourself?
- I kept nothing.
Only for travel and per diem.
Yes, dear viewer, Detochkin
didn’t take the money for himself.
He may be a thief, but he’s a selfless,
honest man.
They spread accounting documents out on the table.
This is an audit... give them our
“house beer.”
Okay.
I didn’t sell the first car.
I left it in Kursk with the police.
I stuck a detailed explanatory note to the windshield,
then went to the station and returned
to Moscow.
And... with the second car there was an injustice.
I drove it to the police too,
and left a note too,
that the owner was a crook!
But they returned it to the owner...
that’s when I decided to sell them!
I love you!
Here! The warrant for your arrest!
Now give it back to me!
Take it!
- And now I’ll tear it up!
- Maxim! Maxim, don’t you dare!
- Yura!
- Don’t you dare! You’ll get in trouble!
Maxim! Guys! We’re friends! Guys!
Dad! Everything’s fine! Dad!
Everything’s fine! Dad!
Then take it for yourself!
I’m giving it to you!
Come in! Goodbye!
Goodbye!
Friend! Friend!
If I fall ill, I won’t go to doctors.
I’ll turn to my friends—
don’t think I’m delirious...
Listen, friend! Don’t lock me up before the premiere, I beg you!
I won’t lock you up at all.
Live free!
Such a role! It happens once in a lifetime, you know?
Play the premiere and all the shows after.
- ...No need for the later ones.
- No, you do, you do!
- Oh, you little rascal!
- I’m going to Lyuba!
Don’t get hit by a car!
Why did you do it? Who asked you?
Who forced you?
Look at yourself.
You’re... an idiot.
You reason like
a three-year-old child.
Why are you sitting there? Get up!
What am I supposed to do? Oh my God!
Did you think about me? No? No.
You always only thought about yourself.
They’ll lock you up, Yura.
- And they’ll be right.
- They’ll be wrong.
Button up. I’ll wait for you, Yura.
Five years, eight years, ten years.
Thank you... ten... ten, so
then I’ll be forty-six.
Yes, that’s of course...
- Oh my God!
- Who did I get mixed up with!
- Who did you get mixed up with, huh?
No, just look,
what you look like...
So what do I look like?
Oh God, you ruined my whole life,
Yurochka!
Yura!
- Good morning! It’s me!
- Hi!
Have you heard that today
a car was stolen again?
And today, you haven’t looked out the window?
Hello? Hello! Why are you silent?
Are you looking out the window, yes?
Well, how is it?
Why did you do this?
Since when did you start stealing
cars from honest people?
What about your principles?
No, no! That’s Stelkin’s car,
and he’s a bribe-taker.
What Stelkin? It’s the car
of a famous scientist! A Doctor of Sciences!
One moment, I’ll check
the card index.
He’s got a card index! A card index!
Wretched bureaucrat!
It’s Stelkin’s car,
and he’s a bribe-taker.
It can’t be... could I really be mistaken!
You will immediately return the Volga
to its owner. And you, I advise...
Come to me, as they say,
with your belongings!
And the play?
There will be no play!
Come in!
Here is the report on the work done.
The warrant... for my arrest.
Good evening!
- Congratulations on the premiere!
- Same to you.
They brought me such a funny wig!
And why do you need a wig?
Your whole life has been spent in makeup as it is.
And why are you speaking of my life
as if it’s already in the past?
Because tomorrow is the trial.
You’re facing five years.
I have mitigating circumstances.
I’m an honest man.
What are they? That you stole cars
from one crook and sold them to another?
Well, there were some shortcomings in my work.
Who doesn’t have them?
You, for example, couldn’t catch me
for a long time.
It’s hard to catch a man
who lives a double life!
I-it always weighed on me terribly and tormented me.
Uh... tie my bow.
No good deed can be accompanied
by lies and deceit.
Well, I’ll be... He took it upon himself to pass judgment,
to mete out punishment.
To be honest, it’s all stupidity
and a crime.
Defendant, where are you going?
So you also think
- ...that I’m guilty?
- Yes!
Comrades, the audience is a full stadium.
Everyone to the stage.
Yes, don’t forget to say: “To be or not to be?”
And you’re not ready again?
Here, Hamlet, my handkerchief! Wipe your brow!
The Queen drinks to your success, Hamlet.
But the third time, Laertes, you’re not joking.
Fight with full strength.
- Do you think I’m a weakling?
- Do you? Begin!
Let us forgive each other, noble Hamlet.
Be pure before Heaven! I follow you!
Horatio!
- I am dying... Mother... farewell!
- Yura, I’m here!
All rise! Court is in session!
We continue the hearing.
Detochkin broke the law, and the law,
as is known, does not like jokes.
In all the judge’s practice there has never been
such a strange, paradoxical case.
By law, Detochkin faced
imprisonment for up to five years.
Detochkin is not just a thief. He’s worse!
He’s a bandit!
He must be tried
for banditry with breaking and entering!
This type has encroached upon the most sacred thing we have!
Upon the Constitution!
It states: “Every person
has the right to personal property.
It is protected by law.” Every person has the right to have a car,
a dacha, books... money! Comrades,
money has not yet been abolished.
From each according to his abilities, to each according to his work—
in cash.
A criminal case has been opened
against witness Semitsvetov.
Dad!
- It’s all right, all right—you’ll find yourself another one, an honest one!
If Dima Semitsvetov’s future
was now fairly clear,
then Yuri Ivanovich Detochkin’s fate
was still uncertain.
Finally the court called the most important witness—
Maxim Podberezovikov.
Esteemed comrades judges.
At first I handled this case
as the investigator.
But when it became clear that
the defendant was my friend,
I withdrew from the case
and now speak
only as a witness.
I understand, comrades judges, you face
a difficult task:
Detochkin broke the law, but he did so
out of noble intentions.
He sold cars, but
gave the money to children.
He is, of course, guilty,
but he... is not guilty.
Have mercy on him, comrades judges:
he is a good man.
And an excellent worker!
If you don’t know, then keep quiet.
Freedom for Yuri Detochkin! Yura!
Quiet! I demand silence, or I will immediately ask that the hall be cleared!
Defendant, you are granted
your last word.
Citizens judges, perhaps I acted
incorrectly,
but from the bottom of my heart.
I... couldn’t stand it.
They steal, they steal a lot... I wanted
to help you, citizens judges.
Please let me go!
I won’t do it anymore...
I give you my word, I won’t!
As is already known, the audience loves detective films.
It’s nice to watch a film
already knowing how it ends.
This incredible story,
which no one knows where took place,
or whether it took place at all,
is coming to an end.
Hello, Lyuba. I’m back.
Russian subtitles at
http://subtitles.ee
29.09.2003
.
No