The audience loves detective
movies.
It's pleasant to watch a film
when you already know how it ends.
And in general, it's flattering
to feel smarter than the authors.
Residents of the capital claim that
this incredible story
happened in Moscow.
Odessites insist it took place
in their city.
Leningrad and Rostov-on-Don
disagree.
Seven cities dispute it
in just the same way
as seven cities claim to be
Homer's birthplace.
It should be said that it's unknown
where this story took place,
or whether it took place
at all.
So, as you may have noticed,
it was a dark night.
The unknown man tried very hard
to remain unnoticed,
and he succeeded.
It was so dark, quiet,
and deserted here
that you almost felt like
committing a crime.
- Call Post No. 2-06V...
- Yes, sir!
- Block all highways!
Get me the photos urgently—
—of the tire tread prints!
- Yes, sir!
Tanya! You find out about the
fingerprints.
So, from one district,
the third car has been stolen.
It's the same hand at work—
experienced and skillful!
A hand wearing cotton gloves
from Factory No. 8.
Then it's not Fedka "Gold Tooth."
And what did the oil analysis show,
the oil the criminal so likes
to pour on garage hinges?
The oil turned out to be refined.
And did you notice that in the yard
where the theft took place,
and nearby on the street,
lots of cars without garages
spend the night?
And stealing a car from the street
is easier than from a garage, right?
That's a very accurate observation.
If we apply Stanislavsky's doctrine
of the super-objective,
an interesting thought arises:
the criminal is taking the path of
greatest resistance. Why?
By uncovering his super-objective,
we'll catch the criminal.
That's brilliant!
Comrade investigator, I forgot
to mention one detail—
—maybe it will help.
- I'm listening, comrade victim.
On my rear fender, an obscene word
was scratched with a nail...
Wait... so... what word?
Hello, Lyuba. I'm back.
Comrades! Get inside faster.
Don't bunch up at the back.
Yury Ivanovich, the trolleybus entrance
is on the other side.
I'm coming.
- Hello, Yakov Mikhailovich!
- Hello, Detochkin!
- So, how is your uncle from Dushanbe?
- My uncle? Bad.
Last time it was an aunt from Moldavia...
A cousin!
- No, you said...
- She passed away.
Yes... we're all mortal, Detochkin...
we're all mortal.
And if people didn't die,
we wouldn't be able to insure
against death.
You won't deny, Detochkin,
that I'm being considerate toward you.
Every time your relatives fall ill
or die,
I grant you
unpaid leave.
You're an exceptionally considerate boss.
That's right, Detochkin, but
you have an awful lot of relatives...
And I have very few staff positions.
You see, your trips
disrupt our plan.
I'll make it up!
Understand, I can't place
family interests
above public ones.
- I... I'll make it up!
- Well, go on and make it up.
Yesterday a policeman stopped me.
The power of attorney is invalid.
You need to stop by and have it certified
at the notary office.
- Please sign here.
- Dima, sign it!
To be honest, I myself don't even know
why I insure my property.
Fires!
It'd be a shame if such property
burned down for nothing.
Maybe we should insure
our car?
Have you bought a car?
Car insurance is provided
in case of total loss
or accidents due to collisions
or natural disasters.
- What about theft?
- Theft—no.
I'm not rich enough
to pay for natural disasters
as well.
- Where do you keep it?
- Come here!
Beige... not flashy...
And you don't have a garage?
Not yet.
I'm trying, but it's
a difficult business.
They promise to allocate a spot...
so no garage yet.
But I've already gotten a lock—Japanese,
you can't pick a key for it.
Yes, hard to pick... and you can't
open it with a picklock either.
You'd need an acetylene torch, and
cutting with a torch... what a hassle...
My clever one.
- Need a ride?
- We're not going the same way.
As you like!
Everyone who doesn't have a car
dreams of buying one.
And everyone who has a car
dreams of selling it,
and doesn't do it only because
after selling it, you'd have no car.
Man, more than any other living creature,
loves creating
additional difficulties for himself.
That's exactly what explains
the desire to have your own car.
The thought that five and a half thousand
have simply been thrown onto the pavement
can poison any happy life.
- Mom!
- You're here!
I can't understand what business trips
an insurance agent could possibly have.
Why are you standing there? Lunch is ready.
Go wash your hands.
What heavy things are you carrying
in your briefcase?
Things I need for work.
It's painful to look at you—
you're so thin and worn...
Korchnoi won the chess tournament...
I was rooting for Tal.
He fell behind by half a point...
Don't laugh at your mother.
Those trips seem suspicious
not only to me...
To whom else?
You're eating onion soup made from
the recipe of the great writer Dumas père.
Those trips seem suspicious to Lyuba.
She's right.
She doesn't want to marry
a bungler.
- Did she tell you that?
No, not now. He just arrived.
That evening Maksim Podberezovikov
was moving in an unknown direction.
From the other end of the city, in an
even more unknown direction,
Yury Detochkin was walking.
They were heading toward their fate.
They were drawing closer.
Every investigator inevitably has a hobby
to which he devotes the time
free from hunting criminals.
Sherlock Holmes, for example,
played the violin;
Maksim Podberezovikov—
amateur theatre.
...The development of folk amateur art is
moving ahead in giant strides.
The spirit of the times has finally
touched us as well, amateur troupes.
They're expanding us now, creating
people's theatres—one might say
they're forming teams from club groups.
Today is a ceremonial day for us.
Today we are creating a new
people's theatre.
I hope it will be a strong organism...
united.
Comrade Detochkin, don't fuss,
sit down.
Within the welcoming walls of our
House of Culture, all conditions have been created
for people of different professions
to join Melpomene,
who, as is known, was the muse...
Our people's theatre, in particular,
is being formed, so to speak, from two
friendly groups—uh... the police troupe and,
uh... the drivers.
- I recognized you.
- That's not me.
But... you said: "And who are the judges?"
I didn't say anything like that
about judges.
You did, you did...
Weren't you the one who played Chatsky?
I... I completely forgot...
And now we'll be acting together
in the same play.
- I'm very glad!
- Me too!
There is an opinion that people's theatres
will soon... replace...! Finally...
professional theatres!
And that's correct!
An actor who doesn't receive a salary
will act with greater inspiration.
Because, besides,
an actor must work somewhere...
It's wrong if he spends the whole day,
you see, hanging around the theatre.
Just imagine how much better Yermolova
would have acted in the evening if during the day she...
you see... worked...
at a grinding machine.
The title of people's theatre
is a great responsibility.
Whom haven't we played
in our troupes!
Isn't it time, my friends, for us
to take a swing at William, you know,
our Shakespeare?
And we will!
A transistor radio "Alpinist," please.
Careful, I beg you.
Excuse me, which of you is Dima?
I'm from Oleg Nikolaevich.
- Which Oleg Nikolaevich?
- A friend of Leonid Osipovich.
I need a foreign tape recorder,
American or German.
We have a very good domestic one.
No, a domestic one won't do.
- You'll have to look for a foreign one.
- I understand. How much?
- What's the matter, citizen?
- Looking.
What is this, a zoo?
Go watch the TV over there.
- Fifty.
- Fifty?
- Pull yourself together.
- Need to find out, bring it in. Italy?
Need to hold off...
- ...leave your phone number...
- All right.
- "Belomor," please.
- No "Belomor."
Well... what do you have?
Then give me "Drug" cigarettes.
Taxi! Taxi! Taxi!
Please! I beg you!
I'm late. Is this your car?
- No.
- But you're the driver?
No, no.
- Then what are you doing here?
- I want to steal the car, and you're in the way.
Well then, please steal it with me—
I'm late for my train.
Ah! Get in. Only you'll become an accomplice.
There! I warned you!
Get him! There he is! Caught him!
Get him—hold the thief!
Hold him! Don't let go!
What a crook!
I'm not a thief! I'm late for my train!
Please, here's my ticket!
Prepared! Look how prudent he is! Huh?
Finally! Hurry! We've caught the swindler.
He tried to steal my car!
- Who's the owner?
- I am... I mean, we are.
I'm not a thief. I'm late for the train,
and he took my ticket from me.
- Your papers?
- Here. The ticket.
- And yours.
- What?
- We'll sort it out somewhere else.
Who's the witness? - Me. What's happened?
I'm not a thief. The thief got away.
Unfortunately, I didn't remember his face...
I'm late for the train!
Though I've already missed it.
- Yours?
- Why, no! God forbid!
Yes, I'm a witness. A witness. Me.
I look better in profile...
So, I'll start from the very beginning.
They didn't deliver "Belomor" to me today.
Well... they didn't, so they didn't.
Could you make it shorter?
Young man... in your profession,
one mustn't rush.
"Belomor" is a detail for the investigation!
And that very man
who got into your car also asked for "Belomor" first,
and then bought "Drug" cigarettes—
30 kopecks a pack,
with a little dog on the label.
And then I thought:
"Why is he nervous? Why?"
Stop! Stop, stop!
What are you thinking about all the time?
Every actor must know his part by heart,
and there's no need to run stupidly across the stage.
You have to act with your head!
And don't be rude, or I'll throw you off the field—
uh... off the rehearsal!
- I'm not being rude, I...
- Break!
Yevgeny Alexandrovich, this part—
"Leave me alone, for God's sake!"
Ah... leave me alone! Break!
- What am I, a little boy to him or what?
- Don't be upset! Come on...
- What are you smoking?
- "Drug" cigarettes.
Yes-yes... "Drug" cigarettes... a dog on the label...
thirty kopecks...
Actually I smoke "Belomor," but there was no "Belomor."
There was no "Belomor"—exactly,
that's why he bought "Drug" cigarettes.
- Who did?
- The criminal.
What criminal?
A modern one—I'd even say,
a new type of criminal.
What did crooks used to leave at the crime scene?
- What?
Caps, cigarette butts—now...
Shakespeare!
Don't be afraid—
there are no bloodstains!
- So you're an investigator?
- Yes. I handle car theft cases.
No fingerprints. The criminal works in gloves.
- But you're not interested?
- No... I'm very interested!
You see, there's neither a library stamp, nor...
I'm saying: there's neither a library stamp,
nor the owner's name.
You know some people write their names in books?
I know, but I don't.
There's a gang operating in the city—
stealing private cars.
In one district, four cars have been stolen in a year.
Three!
There you go—you've already heard it.
Yes, three.
They failed to steal the fourth.
But soon that'll be the end of it.
- How?
- We've detained one member of the gang.
A respectable man—an engineer.
Wife's a doctor. Two children.
- What does he look like?
- Sort of short.
- Roundish?
- Yes...
- And... and you arrested him?
- Why such a harsh measure?
He was going to run off to a resort,
but I took a written pledge from him not to leave town.
What if he's not an accomplice?
A respectable man—and you took away his vacation?
My instinct tells me he's not guilty.
But the final determination is a matter
of a few days.
I already know the identifying marks
of the gang leader...
Tall... wears a raincoat,
a hat, carries a briefcase...
and the main feature—he's hunched...
How are you going to catch the leader?
Comrades! Everyone to the second half!
We'd like a trap
for large game.
- Going after a fox? A wolf?
- A bear.
- He's joking.
Tell me... how does it work?
You put bait here.
- Do you have bait?
- Yes, yes.
The predator scents the bait... creeps up...
creeps up... and the beast is caught!
- Wonderful!
- Write it up!
- I think everything's fine.
- Wonderful! Bring ice cream...
Sima! You're not in the woods! Guys,
don't split up! Stay with the group!
Semitsvetov! Dima!
- She's a blonde!
- Beige-ish!
Guys, when I've been drinking,
I don't drive.
Give us a ride, Dima! Give us a ride, Dima...
Give us a ride, Di-ma!
Quiet! Quiet! Quiet!
The police have invented this test tube now,
where if you... ugh...
you blow into it, it shows immediately
whether a person drank or not.
And if you drank—they take away your license.
- I'm going anyway!
- Sima, this isn't the beach!
- Why are you lying down? It's polished!
- And so what!
Listen, I got r-really plastered!
Need to put myself
in a horizontal position.
- Who's there?
- Lyuba, it's me!
What's wrong?
What happened?
Lyuba, you see, they've set traps everywhere!
- My God!
I'm miserable, miserable,
I'm so unlucky!
The criminal tried twice
to steal the same car.
Not a random coincidence. I think
he wanted to steal your car specifically.
Reasonable... I figured that out too.
But you shouldn't have set a trap
for a living person.
You failed to protect us from the bandit,
so we had to take up self-defense.
Why did he latch onto your car in particular?
Do you suspect anyone
among your acquaintances?
All our acquaintances are perfectly decent people.
Well, maybe someone
envies you?
Envies what? You're asking strange questions.
Check the clinics—whether anyone has come in
with a characteristic leg injury.
Let's set up surveillance
on your car!
No, thank you...
Tomorrow we're putting up a garage.
What do you mean you won't come? Look,
the director will give you a penalty kick!
Ah, your leg hurts? Then lie down...
Sure, I'll pass it on... get well!
- Whose leg?
- It's "the leg"—the right leg, of the right person!
- All right, call.
- When?
When your car gets stolen.
Dima, they're taking Toptunov's dacha away!
- Who's taking it?
- Are you an idiot?
Daddy, they're taking Toptunov's dacha away.
And rightly so—it's about time!
You have to fight crooks.
Why is he a crook? The man knows how to live.
Tell me, on what salary did the deputy director
of a knitwear factory build himself
a two-story mansion?
- That's his business!
- No, ours!
We will fight mercilessly against those
living on unearned income!
- Be quiet, Daddy!
- Ah, scared?
I'll boot you in the knee, and you'll fly off my property!
Dad, I'm sick of your drill-sergeant humor!
What do you mean "in the knee"? Why?
And why are you acting high and mighty, son-in-law?
Who are you anyway?
This is my dacha!
Let everyone hear it—this is my dacha!
It's registered in your name!
But it's being built with my money.
Prove it!
Oh, stop it, will you?
You live in this world
on a power of attorney!
The car's in your wife's name, the dacha in mine—
you have nothing. You're a nobody!
Why? Why do I have to live like this?
Lord, why? Why?
I, a man with higher education,
have to hide, adapt,
wriggle out of things! Why can't I live
freely, openly?
Oh, when will this end! Never!
And what do you even mean?
Do you know what I could,
quite simply,
do to you for that?
- I know... I know...
- He's afraid!
Have pity on him, Daddy!
That guy must always remember who I am!
And he's a common crook!
I really should boot you in the knee!
- Who's there?
- Lyuba, it's me!
- What happened? Another trap?
- No, this time it worked out.
You're leaving? On a business trip?
Now? At night?
It's not my fault... I have to...
because, you see,
a business trip is a rather
complicated undertaking.
Lyuba! There's no need
to get so upset.
I'll be back in a few days.
I'll write to you from there, you hear?
Lyuba! I'm very upset too.
See?
Hello. You know, our right turn signal
keeps sticking.
And when shifting gears
there's this sound...
Let's listen.
And the day before yesterday
the car smelled of gasoline all day.
Let's smell.
Where's the car?
- Comrade chief...
- Hello!
I see you're driving alone. Please help me
start this old wreck.
- Start your motorcycle?
- Yes. Can't manage alone.
No, it's just the battery's run down.
I've asked the bosses a thousand times
to move me to a new motorcycle.
Yeah... with an old battery,
it's no life.
- Well? On three—four, go?
- Let's try.
Come on, let's pick up speed!
Pick up speed, pick up speed.
- Well... stop! I see you're worn out.
- A bit.
- Now let me give you a ride.
- What's the point?
Listen, friend. Let's hitch it to your Volga.
Do you have a tow rope?
Who knows what I've got in there...
I don't remember. I'll check.
I've got a tow line!
Great!
All right! Thanks, friend, you saved me.
- Man to man is a friend.
- Exactly.
Trouble happened to me—you helped.
If it happens to you—I'll help.
Together we do a common cause:
you in your way, and I in mine.
Tell me, friend, is there a telegraph office
somewhere around here?
Not far. Hop in, I'll show you.
Please grant me five days' unpaid leave
due to the sudden serious
condition... serious condition...
of my beloved nephew.
All right, all right... I understand!
Writing it down... that's it!
- Resting?
- Uh-huh...
- Something happen?
- No, nothing, nothing.
- Who's the owner?
- Me.
Car documents.
Sorry.
A chase! What detective plot can do without one?
One runs, the other catches up—
such is the immutable law of the genre.
A detective story without a chase is like
life without love.
Detochkin loved children.
He couldn't act otherwise.
Detochkin realized it was the end.
He wanted to close his eyes,
but he was afraid of running over the Pioneer.
But the inspector also loved children,
and in nobility was no less than Detochkin.
- Caught you, brother!
- Yeah, got caught!
Can't get awa... what the devil!
Hey, wait!
- You... you wait, don't drive off!
- What's up, brother?
Well, you see, again it's the battery...
And I warned you: with an old battery—it's no life.
I always feared it. There'll be important work,
and it will let me down.
There! They didn't move me
to a new motorcycle.
My sympathies.
- You're unlucky.
- But you're lucky!
Of the two of us,
someone had to be lucky.
So what do we do, brother?
Why were you running from me?
Habit. You chase, I run.
And I have a habit. You run,
I chase... you should've gotten out and helped.
We could have hitched it to your Volga,
like last time.
No way! I've already seen
how you repay kindness. Sorry!
Don't get in the way!
Look, the police!
Lock the garage! Begin!
Lift!
Lower!
I always said he was
a talented criminal.
Maybe even... more talented
than me.
For heaven's sake, it's all in one-ruble notes!
Don't distract me, or I'll have
to start over.
Five thousand five hundred! That's it!
Why are your bills all one-ruble notes?
That's suspicious. Not good!
And you are... a prosecutor?
I don't ask where the car is from,
why there are no papers.
And I can tell you frankly:
I stole this car.
And I can tell you frankly too:
I'm a pastor.
These rubles are donations to him! Come on!
Just a little left!
And you believe in God?
All people believe: some believe
God exists, others believe He doesn't.
Neither can be proven!
Will you recount them?
I will!
Here! As promised—
a Grundig tape recorder.
But is it new?
- Absolutely new. I checked it myself.
- Then write it up. I remember everything.
- Eighty!
- What? You said fifty!
- Personal circumstances have changed.
- You know, that's daylight robbery!
I'm not insisting. It'll be gone in a second.
An elegant thing...
- ...four tracks... stereo.
- Write it up!
Citizen, the item is sold—don't touch it with your hands.
It's sold.
So why did he want to steal your car specifically?
- What's wrong with you?
- I got caught...
I'm finished... an investigator came to see me.
You'll go to jail—so don't steal!
Semyon Vasilievich!
You're in my house!
Your home is prison!
Inka, Inka! What do I do? What do I do?
Inka, what do I do?
Dry crackers!
Dima, don't worry! You have to grease
the investigator's palm!
Are you out of your mind? Grease his palm!
You lunatic!
- Give him a lot—then he'll take it!
- Silence! Attention!
I won't allow it! Shame!
Dad, with your lectures you should speak
at your market stall.
I sell strawberries grown
with my own two hands.
And for bribes—not just my son-in-law,
I'd grind my own daughter into dust!
Never mind! Prison will re-educate you.
In ten years you'll come back
a different man!
Put the bird down!
You should marry an orphan!
Don't doubt it, I have the money—
here, a whole briefcase.
Do you really want to transfer
- ...this sum to an orphanage?
- Yes.
Were you raised in that home?
Are these your personal savings?
Well, how can I put it... generally...
I had a hand in it too.
Hello! I'd like to see Yury
Ivanovich Detochkin.
- I'm Yura's mother.
- Very nice to meet you.
I'm from the people's theatre.
I'm very glad Yura
acts in the theatre.
- I think he has ability.
- He has real talent.
- He didn't come to rehearsal...
- Dear boy, he's on a business trip.
I hate his business trips.
He bolts in the middle of the night, disappears.
Lyuba is right—something's not right.
Lyuba is Yura's fiancée.
He's somehow old-fashioned.
He's been courting her for so long.
They met when he came
to insure her...
Tell me, what business trips
could an insurance agent have?
- What's your profession?
- Investigator.
Then you figure it out!
When I was young,
an investigator courted me.
But I married a Red Army soldier.
We sang: "Our locomotive speeds ahead,
the commune is our stop!"
- And when did he leave, and for how long?
- Three days ago, at night.
And the strangest thing is, he came
to say goodbye to Lyuba in some Volga.
- Ah! He took a taxi.
- No, he himself was driving.
- Does Yury Ivanovich drive?
- Yura? He worked as a driver for 10 years.
Then he had an accident, got a concussion.
The doctors advised Yura not to drive for now,
so he got a job as an insurance agent.
What's wrong with you?
To what city did you send
your employee Detochkin
on a business trip?
I didn't send him anywhere.
Detochkin has a great many sickly relatives
in different cities of the Soviet Union.
I recently received a telegram...
Here it is. Here.
His next beloved nephew fell ill.
He took unpaid leave.
Maksim was beside himself. Memories
burned his heart.
How cleverly Detochkin hid his interest
in the hunt for the gang leader! Hypocrite!
How he stole the car
with the help of a truck crane!
A vile schemer—a thief!
He betrayed what was dearest—friendship!
And such a man deserves no mercy.
Mom? It's me. I just arrived...
I'm fine... is everything calm at home?
Nobody came by?
You've played too far in your people's theatre.
An investigator came to see you.
- Defend yourself, sir!
- At your service...
I have the honor to attack you...
- Where have you been?
- What the devil, I was on a business trip!
And how's your nephew?
- What nephew?
- Your beloved one!
And the wolf trap? And the sore leg?
And the "Drug" cigarettes?
Stop improvising! In Shakespeare's day
there were no "Drug" cigarettes!
And why did you switch to prose?
- Podberezovikov!
- Yes?
What are you thinking about all the time?
Stop it! Stop waving your sabre!
What a blow!
Easy!
- Where is he?
- He's come to!
- Alive!
- Break!
- How many cars did you sell?
- Four.
Let's say four. A decent sum—
a whole fortune.
Where did you come from like this?
Your mother is such a good woman, sings about locomotives.
- Excuse me, are you crazy?
- No. I even have a certificate.
What an actor!
I always said: a real crook is,
as a rule, a good actor!
You stole only from those you considered crooks.
I guessed it right away!
Think they'll cut a year or two off at trial?
Where do you hide your capital?
- Here.
- Aha! Well!
Hello! Why didn't you tell me right away?
Please come with your friend
to a separate office.
Raya! Lyuda!
They'll bring fresh beer,
just delivered, and serve dried fish...
- And the fish was just caught!
- Your friend is a joker!
Tell me, any news
about the car?
Soon.
- Let's go.
- Let's stay a little longer, if we may.
They probably won't feed me in prison
like they do here.
- What's this?
- A change of underwear—just in case.
- And this?
- Certificates, receipts, documents...
- What documents? Where's the money?
- This is the money.
What? You were transferring
money to orphanages?
Uh-huh.
- So how much did you keep for yourself?
- I kept nothing.
Just for travel and per diem.
Yes, dear viewer, Detochkin
didn't take any money for himself.
He may be a thief, but a selfless,
honest man.
They spread accounting documents out on the table.
It's an audit... bring them our "signature beer."
Sure.
I didn't sell the first car.
I left it with the police in Kursk.
I taped a detailed explanatory note
to the windshield
and went to the station and returned
to Moscow.
And... with the second car there was an injustice.
I drove it to the police too
and left a note too,
that its owner was a crook!
But they returned it to the owner...
that's when I decided to sell them!
I love you!
Here! The warrant for your arrest!
Now give it to me!
Take it!
- Now I'm going to tear it up!
- Maksim! Maksim, don't you dare!
- Yura!
- Don't you dare! You'll get in trouble!
Maksim! Guys! We're friends! Guys!
Dad! Everything's fine! Dad!
Everything's fine! Dad!
Then take it for yourself!
I'm giving it to you as a gift!
Come in! Goodbye!
Goodbye!
Friend! Friend!
If I fall ill, I won't go to doctors.
I'll turn to my friends—
don't think it's delirium...
Listen, friend! Don't send me away before the premiere,
I beg you!
I'm not going to send you away at all.
Live free!
Such a role! It happens once in a lifetime, you know?
Play the premiere—and all
the following performances.
- ...no need for the following.
- No, you must, you must!
- Oh, you rascal!
- I'm going to Lyuba!
Don't get run over!
Why did you do it? Who asked you?
Who forced you?
Look at yourself.
You're... an idiot.
You reason like
a three-year-old child.
Why are you sitting? Stand up!
What am I supposed to do? My God!
Did you think about me? No? No.
You always thought only about yourself.
They'll imprison you, Yura.
- And it'll be right.
- It'll be wrong.
Button up. I'll wait for you, Yura.
Five years, eight years, ten years.
Thank you... ten... ten, so,
then I'll be forty-six.
Yes, that, of course...
- My God!
- What kind of man did I get involved with!
- What kind? Tell me!
No, just look at you—
what do you look like...
What do I look like?
My God, you ruined my whole life,
Yurochka!
Yura!
- Good morning! It's me!
- Hi!
Have you heard that today a car
was stolen again?
And you haven't looked out the window today?
Hello? Hello! Why are you silent?
You're looking out the window, right?
So, what is it?
Why did you do it?
Since when have you started stealing
cars from honest people?
Where are your principles?
Oh no! That's Stelkin's car,
and he's a bribe-taker.
What Stelkin? It's the car
of a famous scientist! A Doctor of Sciences!
Just a moment, I'll check
my card index.
He's got a card index! A card index!
Wretched bureaucrat!
It's Stelkin's car,
and he's a bribe-taker.
It can't be... could I really be mistaken!
You will immediately return the Volga
to its owner. And as for you, I advise...
Come to me, as they say,
with your things!
And the play?
There will be no play!
Come in!
Here's my report on the work done.
The warrant...
for my arrest.
Good evening!
- Congratulations on the premiere!
- Same to you.
They brought me such a funny wig!
And why do you need a wig?
Your whole life has been spent in makeup anyway.
And why are you talking about my life
as if it's already in the past?
Because tomorrow is the trial.
You're facing five years.
I have mitigating circumstances.
I'm an honest man.
What are they? That you stole cars from
one crook and sold them to another?
Well, there were certain shortcomings
in my work. And who doesn't have them?
You, for example, couldn't catch me
for a long time.
It's hard to catch a person
who leads a double life!
I-it always weighed on me terribly
and tormented me.
Uh... tie my bow.
No good deed can be accompanied
by lies and deception.
Imagine that! He took the law into his own hands,
carried out reprisals.
To be honest, all this is foolishness
and a crime.
Defendant under investigation, where are you going?
So you also think
- ...I'm guilty?
- Yes!
Comrades, the house is full.
Everyone to the stage.
Yes, don't forget to say: "To be or not to be?"
And you're not ready again?
Here, Hamlet, my handkerchief! Wipe your brow!
The Queen drinks to your success, Hamlet.
But the third time, Laertes, don't jest.
Fight with full force.
- Do you take me for a weakling?
- Do you think so? Begin!
Let us forgive each other, noble Hamlet.
Be pure before heaven! I follow you!
Horatio!
- I'm dying... mother... farewell!
- Yura, I'm here!
All rise! Court is in session!
We continue the hearing.
Detochkin broke the law, and the law,
as you know, doesn't like jokes.
In all the judge's practice, there has never been
such a strange, paradoxical case.
By law, Detochkin faced
up to five years' imprisonment.
Detochkin is not just a thief. He's worse!
He's a bandit!
He must be tried for banditry with breaking and entering!
This type has encroached on the most sacred thing we have!
The Constitution!
It says: "Every person
has the right to personal property.
It is protected by law." Every person has the right
to have a car,
a dacha, books... money! Comrades,
no one has abolished money yet.
From each according to his ability,
to each according to his work—in cash.
Criminal proceedings have been opened
against witness Semitsvetov.
Dad! - It's all right, all right,
you'll find yourself another one—an honest one!
If Dima Semitsvetov's future
was now fairly clear,
Yury Ivanovich Detochkin's fate
still remained uncertain.
At last the court called its most important witness:
Maksim Podberezovikov.
Esteemed comrades judges.
At first I handled this case
as an investigator.
But when it became clear that
the defendant is my friend,
I withdrew from the case
and now appear
only as a witness.
I understand, comrades judges, you face
a difficult task:
Detochkin broke the law, but he did so
from noble motives.
He sold cars,
but he gave the money to children.
He is, of course, guilty,
but he is... not guilty.
Have pity on him, comrades judges:
he is a good man.
And an excellent worker!
If you don't know—then be silent.
Freedom for Yury Detochkin! Yura!
Quiet! I demand silence, or I'll
order the courtroom cleared immediately!
Defendant, you are granted
the last word.
Citizens judges, perhaps
I acted incorrectly,
but from a pure heart.
I... couldn't stand it.
They steal—steal a lot... I wanted
to help you, citizens judges.
Please, let me go!
I won't do it anymore...
I swear I won't!
As is already known, the audience loves
detective movies.
It's pleasant to watch a film,
when you already know how it ends.
This incredible story,
which no one knows where took place,
or whether it took place at all,
is coming to an end.
Hello, Lyuba. I'm back.
Russian subtitles at
http://subtitles.ee
29.09.2003