[music]
at night, somewhere in the first hour in a small
provincial town without a specific
name, a young man of about 27 years old or so
walks into
a wooden outbuilding standing alone in the yard to visit
a civil engineer sitting on a sofa with
a slatted back and hard leather
pillows almost immediately notices that on
the window there is a plate with an unfinished boiled
chicken
My name is Armen Zakharyan this is
the literary channel of Armen Fedor and
today we are opening new section
episode in it Each time we will
carefully look at just one
fragment from the pages of world literature and
figure out why this episode is special
and how what we call
art works in it and for the first such experience we
chose one of the most terrible But at the same time
interesting scenes from the novel Demons
by Fyodor Dostoevsky this is an episode almost
at the very end of the book from its
final part there a certain
Verkhovensky comes at night to the house of
a certain Kirillov and sees
a chicken boiled with rice on the window
and Although there is a loaded pistol right next to the chicken
, it is not he, but
the chicken that plays the role of Chekhov’s gun in this scene,
which is about
to fire. However, in order to understand what kind
of shot this is and who it is aimed at, you must
first figure out who these two are and how
they ended up here in the same room at night in
the outbuilding. It’s