[music]
at night, somewhere in the first hour in a small
provincial town without a specific
name, a young man of about 27 years old or so
walks into
a wooden outbuilding standing alone in the yard to visit
a civil engineer sitting on a sofa with
a slatted back and hard leather
pillows almost immediately notices that on
the window there is a plate with an unfinished boiled
chicken
My name is Armen Zakharyan this is
the literary channel of Armen Fedor and
today we are opening new section
episode in it Each time we will
carefully look at just one
fragment from the pages of world literature and
figure out why this episode is special
and how what we call
art works in it and for the first such experience we
chose one of the most terrible But at the same time
interesting scenes from the novel Demons
by Fyodor Dostoevsky this is an episode almost
at the very end of the book from its
final part there a certain
Verkhovensky comes at night to the house of
a certain Kirillov and sees
a chicken boiled with rice on the window
and Although there is a loaded pistol right next to the chicken
, it is not he, but
the chicken that plays the role of Chekhov’s gun in this scene,
which is about
to fire. However, in order to understand what kind
of shot this is and who it is aimed at, you must
first figure out who these two are and how
they ended up here in the same room at night in
the outbuilding. It’s
curious how even at the very beginning of the book,
only by introducing us to the characters, Dostoevsky
is already preparing the ground for their
terrible night meeting, Kirillov, he has
a young man of about 27 years old,
almost Verkhovensky a mirror-image young
man of about 27 years old or so,
this deliberate resemblance, of course, only
emphasizes how deep
the differences are between them. Kirillov is a bright representative of
the famous series of heroes, fanatics
of Dostoevsky, heroes who are too
much carried away by some idea,
begin to serve this idea, live in the name of
this idea, only Kirillov has a different plan,
he is going to die in the name of the idea,
Kirillov is obsessed with the thought of man God,
he comes to it through a problem that
the literature of this period of the second half of
the 19th century often tried to solve how
a person can live. After abandoning God,
let’s say there is no God anymore Suppose we
no longer believe in him, we have, as
Verkhovenski put it, deformed
him , but the need to fill
the void with something in his place remains, and
while another hero of Dostoevsky in the same
demons says if there is no God, then what kind of captain
am I after that, Captain Kirillov says
if there is no God, then I can take his
place
, remember Grebenshchikov sang, you feel
a draft from the fact that this place is free
Kirillov feels that same draft and
he formulates a terrible crazy thought in
which Then he himself falls in love, if
a person says he decides to declare his
will and just like that, not out of anger or
fear or malice, but only
because he is right, he will die, then
he argues that Kirillov will regenerate
all of humanity with this step and he himself will become
a human God.
So after all, there have been millions of suicides already,
they tell him, but still nothing. Then
Kirillov objects with fear and for the wrong reasons,
and this Insane approach of his surprisingly
resembles one episode from Don
Quixote, remember when the daring and
far away Sancho says to Pansi that he plans
to imitate the glorious knights of the past and
to go crazy,
the pragmatic Sancho then asks but And
the reason you have to go crazy is
senor reason, what is the whole
point in this, Don Quixote answers, that
is the unusualness
of the enterprise I have conceived. Who are
the knights errant for any reason who went crazy,
it is not the reward of ingratitude, do not
ask the whole trick is to
go crazy for no reason
And how do we we will soon see these echoes in
the words of Kirillov and Quixote, not
by chance.
So, in order to carry out his crazy
Kirillov's idea is that
there is a loaded revolver on the window next to the chicken, you can
ask, but what is he waiting for then? Why
won't he carry out his intention since he
doesn't need a reason for this? This is
where his nightly visitor comes into play.
Revolutionary and nihilist Peter
Stepanovich Verkhovensky is a
completely different character, an amazing hero, funny
and scary at the same time, comic and
parody, terribly talkative and
theatrical, but at the same time creepy
because he is ready for any evil.
Verkhovensky Yes, to a certain extent,
he resembles Mephistopheles, only
Mephistopheles had a better sense of humor And
due to his life experience and age, he
was more modest, but the main thing is that they
still share Verkhovensky
is an extremely practical person. He believes
that the end justifies any means and
the meeting of the darling with this project of his
ideological suicide, Verkhovensky immediately
comes up with how it can be used
for good, No, not for the degeneration
of humanity, he doesn’t believe in a penny
, but for his demonic business, He decides
to commit a political murder and since
Kirillov absolutely doesn’t care how and
when to die, then ask him before
his death to write a Confession of this
murder, that is, to use
Kirillov’s death as an Alibi in his crime.
So this is the disposition at
the time of their night meeting, a conflict of
the spiritual. Even if the sick but spiritual
Don Quixote was also mad, and
a material conflict of the sublime and
the mundane, tragic and
pragmatic, but how to show all this
through one single image
and with the help of a chicken
episode, as is often the case with
Dostoevsky unfolds
rapidly Verkhovensky Just
came in just clarified that
our intention is strong I hope we don’t give up on suicide,
we’ll sign the paper and almost without
a pause immediately ba Yes, I notice something there
on the window on a plate He approaches the window
Wow, chicken boiled with rice but why is it
still unfinished, so we
are in such a mood of the Spirit that
even I ate the chicken,
Kirillov interrupts him and it’s none of your business keep quiet about
of course And besides, it’s all the same, but for me
it’s not the same now imagine I
almost didn’t have lunch at all and therefore if now this
chicken, as I think, is no longer needed
and Pay attention to how
Kirillov formulates his answer Eat if you can
Verkhovensky can do as well as he can for himself
because of that guy, maybe I thank him,
he says and then tea and then
something even more creepy follows the bone
on the cake of this scene Verkhovensky instantly
settled down at the table at the other end
of the sofa from he pounced on the food with extreme greed,
but at the same time,
every moment he watched his victim, Kirillov
looked at him motionlessly with evil disgust,
as if unable to tear himself away.
Verkhovensky here is a triumph of the flesh,
he eats greedily with an appetite with excitement, because
the man sitting a meter away from him is about
to shoot himself, but the chicken also began to be
vacant,
notice in this one paragraph,
Verkhovensky takes away from Kirillov
absolutely all his freedom, his last
will his last meal and in the end
his life
the chicken is, of course, only a metaphor
because in its essence Verkhovensky Cannibal
people are consumable for him,
feeding his pathetic ambitions and terrible
plans Is happiness worth humanity’s
tears of a child asks Ivan
Karamazov And a baby with a side dish or so
without anything,
Peter and Kirillov clarify
this strange Kirillov Yes, with
his crazy idea, but still not with an evil
heart, he cannot tear himself away, he
watches with horror after Verkhovensky eats
chicken because not only does
he eat chicken, but he will also
eat his Kirillov
, Verkhovensky Barabek ate 40 people and
the cow and the Bull and the Crooked Butcher and the cart
and the arc and the broom and the poker ate the chicken with
a side dish and ended with this world
and this whole tangle of contradictions of fears
and destinies Dostoevsky shows through
one scene of a meal through one plate of
cold chicken with rice
the eloquent horror of this gastronomic
scene was very accurately captured in the legendary
production of demons of the St. Petersburg Maly
Drama Theater in a six-hour
performance Lvadodin, who was on
stage for almost 30 years, those who
were lucky enough to attend this performance
probably remember the scene with
Verkhovensky’s chicken, having seen it once
in real life, it’s already hard to forget. Look at
a fragment of how this scene was played,
this is an illustration; in fact, we could
finish talking about today’s
fragment if not for one detail. The fact is
that this opposition of
refusal to eat, gluttony as a metaphor for
a value conflict was encountered in
one book that Dostoevsky really
loved, books that influenced to all his
main texts, the book about which he
said that in the whole world there is no deeper and
stronger than this work, finally, the book
that we mentioned today, of course, in
Don Quixote by Cervantes, remember how
the relationship between Don Quixote and Sancho
panse is built in the first Volume We talked about this
in one of the early issues of Armen and
Fedor dedicated to this novel Sancho
is fixated on food, he always reminds
Quixote about food, he
strives to eat at every opportunity, regardless
of what he is experiencing at
that time moment his master is preaching whether
he is fasting or suffering and the Great
American director Orson Welles in
his Don Quixote who, by
an amazing coincidence, will come out almost
simultaneously with Dodin’s performance
to depict a scene more reminiscent of
this episode from the demons there, Sancho Panza in front of
the fasting eyes of Quixote will
greedily eat
What do you think, that
of course it is the chicken
[music]
I want this, that Marina will go,
all that remains is to make a reservation that they want
the spirit of Don Cervantes's Quixote this episode
corresponds completely but not
completely to the letter in the text of the novel
there was no such scene with the chicken. However, this is,
in the end, easily explainable. Cervantes
did not read Dostoevsky, unlike
Orson Wells,
this is the literary channel of Armen Fedor and
the episode section. I hope that our
experiment with this new laconic
format was a success and If so,
write to us in the comments What other
episodes would you like to see in this
section in the future
, but for now that’s all My name is Armen zakharyan
see you next time
[music]