Okay, I know how to handle your type!
Well, old faithful,
that's your shooting for the day.
If we haven't rung up
at least two rabbits,
we deserve to go home empty-handed.
Yeah. Still, blessed are they
who expect nothing
for they shall not be disappointed.
Hmm.
Fewer things in life give
a man more pleasure than hunting.
It satisfies his primitive nature.
Striding through the woods,
picking up his kill.
Well, come on, old faithful.
There's plump rabbits
waiting for the frying pan.
If this can had four legs and a tail,
we'd be eating it tonight.
Clean through the heart.
For rice cake, I've done him in.
A harmless potshot at a rabbit
and I'm a murderer, a killer.
Mother always said
I'd come to a bad end.
What in Hades were
you doing here anyway?
I can't say that I've
seen you around here before.
If you're going to get yourself shot,
do it where you're known.
"Mr. Harry Worp, 87 Maple Avenue,
Boston, Massachusetts."
Well, Worp, you're
a long way from home.
By the looks of it, you won't
get back for Christmas.
We're going to have
a cold, hard winter.
You might keep here a long time,
an awful long time.
Too long for me, Harry.
Yes.
Captain Wiles.
Yes, ma'am?
What seems to be the trouble, Captain?
Well, it's what you might call
an unavoidable accident.
He's dead.
Yes.
I would say that he was. Of course,
that's an unprofessional opinion.
- Do you know him, Miss Gravely?
- No.
- Doesn't live around here.
- Well, he died around here.
That's what counts now.
Embarrassing. What do you plan
to do with him, Captain?
Miss Gravely,
without cutting the hem
off truth's garment,
I'm going to hide him.
Cover him up. Forget him.
Are you never going to
inform the police, Captain?
No. Forget you saw me, Miss Gravely.
Chase it out of your mind,
for heaven's sake. It was an accident.
He was poking around the clearing
and I thought he was a rabbit or something.
It was a human error.
Please, don't.
Don't say anything
to anybody, Miss Gravely.
Do as you think best, Captain.
I'm sure you must have met
many similar situations
in your travels in foreign lands.
Yeah, I've seen much worse things.
- I certainly won't say anything.
- Much worse things.
I remember when I was on the Orinoco.
We had a Turk, a great big Turk
there running amok with a machete.
Captain, if I were going to hide
an accident, I shouldn't delay.
You're right as rain, Miss Gravely.
Yes, you know something?
I'm glad I met you today.
I feel better for telling somebody as warm,
tender, understanding as yourself.
On the contrary, Captain, it...
I'm certainly glad
if I helped you, Captain.
Perhaps you would care to come over
for some blueberry muffins
and coffee later on.
High-bush blueberries.
This is certainly something
of an interesting surprise.
And perhaps a touch of elderberry wine.
After all, we've been neighbors
for nearly three years now
and we've never exchanged social calls.
You're right.
It's high time I paid a call.
What time?
Oh, say, early this afternoon?
I'll be there with a clean shirt
and a hungry face.
Do that.
You'd better be going along now.
You don't want to be
an accessory after the fact.
You are a considerate man,
Captain Wiles.
- Goodbye.
We're almost there, Mommy.
Here he is, Mommy, here he is.
- What did I tell you, Mommy?
- Don't touch it, Arnie.
There he is.
No, it can't be. Harry.
Harry. Thank Providence,
the last of Harry.
Who's Providence, Mommy?
- A very good friend.
- Don't you know who it is?
You said, "Harry."
Can't you remember, Arnie?
Why don't he get up and do something?
He's asleep.
He's in a deep sleep.
A deep, wonderful sleep.
How'd he hurt his head?
Putting it where it wasn't
wanted would be my guess.
Will it get better?
Not if we're lucky.
Let's run home and I'll make you
some lemonade.
Will lemonade put me in a wonderful,
deep, deep sleep, Mommy?
No, Arnie, but it's
better than no lemonade.
- I don't understand that.
- Never mind.
Now you just forget
you ever saw this man.
Is there a special way to forget?
Just think of something else.
I think I'll try not
to see him tomorrow, Mommy.
That's a good boy, Arnie. Now let's run
home and get that lemonade.
She won't care what I do with him.
Couldn't have had more people here
if I'd sold tickets.
What's the big attraction, I wonder.
This could turn out to be
the luckiest day of my life.
Might as well sit here till
the rest of the world comes by
to pay their last respects.
Sooner or later one of them has
to turn out to be the deputy sheriff.
Flaggin' the train that's goin' home
Flaggin' the train to Tuscaloosa
Never no more, no more to roam
Gotta get back to Tuscaloosa
Got a sweet gal who's on my mind
Back to the gal I left behind
Got no baggage
Just got my fare
But all I need, yes, indeed
Is waitin' for me there
Flaggin' the train to Tuscaloosa
Oh, how I love that choo-choo sound
Flaggin' the train
that's homeward bound
Gotta get back to Tuscaloosa
Got a sweet gal who's on my mind
Back to the gal I left behind
Got no baggage
Just got my fare
But all I need, yes, indeed
Is waitin' for me there
Hello, Mr. Marlow.
Wiggy, you haven't sold a painting.
All my pictures in the same place.
So few cars. They don't seem to...
- Guess the cider takes their attention.
- Cider?
Cider, indeed. Throw it away! Drink it!
No, I hate cider.
Not a picture sold.
I'm sorry, Mr. Marlow. Let's get a look
at your new one. Hold it up.
What good would it do to show it to you?
You don't deserve to see it.
How am I going to eat?
Mr. Wiggs always used to thump
his stomach when he got mad.
He busted something inside once.
You think we'd do any
better on Fifth Avenue?
If there's more people there.
Oh, lots of people. Hundreds and thousands
and billions of people.
Well, might be better then.
But what sort of people, Wiggy?
What breed?
I'll tell you. They're little people.
Little people with hats on.
How are your cigarettes?
I'll buy the other half tomorrow.
What does your son do with those
old cars he always works on?
He sells them. Mechanical antiques.
Doesn't make much,
but he needs the money.
Doesn't he get paid
for being deputy sheriff?
Piecework. Gets paid
by the arrest, I think.
Oh. Mr. Marlow, it's wonderful.
I've been in a tortured mood lately.
What is it?
Good old Wiggy, my sternest critic.
I don't understand your work.
I think it's beautiful.
So does Mrs. Rogers.
Oh! You talk about me?
She's the pretty woman
with the little boy, isn't she?
Mmm-hmm.
I only brought up your name once
when we were talking about strange people.
Huh?
That is, strangers.
People she hadn't met yet.
And what does the pretty little thing
say about me?
Nothin'.
I think we better discuss business.
Now, my shopping list.
I'll go in and start puttin' it up.
Say, Wiggy, how do
you spell Tuscaloosa?
Sam?
Hi, Calvin.
- You hear any shootin' a while back?
- Nope.
Well, I did, and there shouldn't be
any shootin' around here.
- Why?
- It's posted land, that's why.
- Why's that?
- 'Cause I posted it.
What do you got against people doing
a little shooting now and then?
Let off a little steam.
Bullets and guns are dangerous.
They kill things.
No one around here could hit
a freight car with a cannon.
I guess you're right, Sam.
All the same the law's the law.
And I got a good mind to scout around,
find out who's doin' the shootin'
and level a little fine.
And pick up a little piecework?
If I can do anything to make it
any harder for you, let me know.
How do you want your bacon, Mr. Marlow?
- What were you saying?
- I asked how you want your bacon.
Sliced.
Where's Calvin?
Off somewheres unimportant.
What a wonderful day.
So was yesterday, but you didn't
say anything to me about it.
What you want Calvin for?
These marvelous pictures.
Someone told me they were yours.
Why don't you sell them,
make a lot of money?
Never thought of that.
Guess I'll just have to think about it.
And that song.
You sing it so beautifully.
You wrote it yourself, of course.
- What do you want to borrow?
- Oh, dear.
I just think people need encouragement
sometimes, don't you, Mr. Marlow?
- How do you know my name?
- Well, it's on the pictures, isn't it?
Not supposed to be readable.
You can tell it's not supposed to be.
They're very professional.
Don't you think, Mrs. Wiggs?
Well, Miss Gravely,
all I know is nobody buys them.
Thank you for your encouragement,
Miss Gravely.
I wonder how you know my name.
- Easy. Wiggy just said it.
- Wiggy.
What a perfectly
ridiculous little nickname.
Do you mind if I call
you "Wiggy," Mrs. Wiggs?
Not if you pay all your bills on time.
All right, Mr. Marlow.
Bacon, beans, cabbage, sugar, salt,
tea, oleo margarine. $1.95.
Don't forget half
a package of cigarettes.
- Oh, yes. Ten cents. $2.05.
- That much?
Don't seem to be able to find...
I know, Mr. Marlow. As soon
as we sell some of your paintings.
Just a minute, Mr. Marlow.
Let me make my position clear.
What do you think?
I think it'll hold coffee.
Would you try it, Mr. Marlow?
Put your finger through
the handle, please.
How about the size?
What about the handle?
Hmm?
I mean, does it fit?
Is it the right finger size?
It's my finger size.
I'll take it.
Fifteen cents.
- And the saucer?
- Ten.
That seems a fair price.
What's the finger size
got to do with it?
Um... I wanted to be certain
it would fit a man.
- A certain size man.
- A man?
A certain somebody is coming over
to my cottage this afternoon.
Not really?
For coffee and blueberry muffins.
Why, you old social butterfly, you.
Old?
That was figuratively
speaking, Miss Gravely.
Think we've got
a nearsighted cider customer.
How old do you think I am, young man?
Mmm...
Fifty. How old do you think you are?
Forty-two.
I can show you my birth certificate.
I'm afraid you're gonna
have to show more
than your birth certificate
to convince a man of that.
What do you mean?
I mean you have to show your character.
The inner self. The hidden qualities.
The true Miss Gravely,
sensitive, young in feeling,
timeless with love and understanding.
I can do it.
At least I think I can do it.
Do what?
Well, I think I'll just go out
and see what that gentleman wants.
At a time like this?
Where are your scissors?
- Outside.
- We're going to cut her hair.
- Hair?
- Cut it short.
Bring it up to date.
Make a nice romantic styling.
Take ten years off
your birth certificate.
How are you fixed for ribbon?
Should be some around somewhere.
- Powder, rouge, lipstick?
- I think so.
Nothing cheap, shoddy or obvious.
Just youth, gentility, character.
I'll go out and get the scissors.
You find the other things.
- Ah! Here they are.
- Excuse me, young man, I...
Oh, well.
All right, Ernest, let's go.
Well, always grow back, I guess.
- There's Calvin.
- Is he alone?
Yep. Guess he didn't sell his car.
Hey. Would you mind
getting out of my picture?
Next thing you know,
they'll be televising the whole thing.
Uh...
- This your body, little man?
- Oh, don't turn me in.
It was an accident, an accident,
pure and simple.
I thought he was a rabbit
or a pheasant or something.
It could have happened to you.
Suppose we straighten
this whole thing out?
Well, I guess that's the only way out.
First thing I seen
when I rolled out this morning
was a double-breasted robin,
drunk as a hoot owl
from eating fermented chokecherries.
Right away I knew
somebody was in trouble.
What I didn't know was that it was me.
Well, the larder was empty,
and I got to thinking
about a toothful of fried rabbit...
Stands to reason they
can't touch you for it.
Nothing these days stands to reason.
It was accidental,
an act of God, perhaps.
In a way you should be grateful
that you were able to do your share
in accomplishing
the destiny of a fellow being.
Suppose, for instance,
it was written in the Book of Heaven
that this man was to die
at this particular time
at this particular place.
And suppose for a moment the actual
accomplishing of his departure
had been bungled.
Something gone wrong. Uh...
Perhaps it was meant
to be a thunderbolt
and there was no thunder
available, say.
Then you come along, and you shoot him
and heaven's will is done
and destiny fulfilled.
Your conscience is quite clear.
You got nothing to worry about.
Sammy, I haven't got a conscience
and it's not heaven that's worrying me
'cause I don't expect
I'll ever have to face it.
And it's none of those noble things
you were talking about, no.
Nothing like that.
Then what is it?
It's me. It's me that's worrying me.
Me and my future life.
I know the police
and their suspicious ways.
You're guilty until
you're proved innocent.
I want nothing more to do with them.
Bury him, I say,
and have done with him.
He's no good to anyone now.
Lay him to rest.
Put him under the sod. Forget him.
I never did it, and you never saw him.
Yes, what about all those
other people who saw him?
How about the woman and the little boy?
Miss Gravely and the tramp
and the man who was reading
the book, Dr. Greenbow.
How about all of them?
Nobody was interested, I tell you.
Nobody ever cared until you came along.
Ah. That's what you think.
Suppose someone starts to care
after you've buried him.
I can't wait for people to start
caring whenever they feel like it.
I don't want a little accident
to turn into a career.
Suppose that woman
who called him Harry.
Suppose she decides
she loves him after all.
She was downright
hysterical with delight.
What was she like?
Pretty as a rainbow.
Wish I was two years younger.
- And with a little boy?
- About four or five years of age.
It's got to be Mrs. Rogers and her son.
Sammy,
what do you say we slip him underground now
that you've finished drawing him? Eh?
We could discuss
the smaller details later.
I don't like it.
The authorities like
to know when people die.
All right, Sammy. Forget it.
You cut off home.
I killed him, and I'll
look after his remains.
What will you do, drag him around
the countryside the rest of the day?
I'll do my best.
That's all a man can do.
If you're not careful, you will get
a murder charge lined up.
Matter of fact, I'm beginning
to suspect something myself.
There you are then. See?
If you, an artist, suspect the worst,
what are they, the police,
going to think?
What about that envelope
with his name and address on it?
By rights you should
mail him back home.
Sammy, have you forgotten
who carries the mail
down to the station every night?
Calvin Wiggs, deputy sheriff.
Yes, you're right.
Tell you what we'll do.
Tell you what.
We'll find out how well
Mrs. Rogers knows this man
and whether she intends to notify
the police of his death.
What good will that do?
A lot of good.
If she's just a distant friend of his
who doesn't intend
to notify the authorities,
then I personally
will help you bury Harry.
Oh, Sammy, you've signed on
for the cruise.
What time is it?
- About noon.
- Good heavens!
I've got to go home and spruce up.
I've got a date with Miss Gravely.
Not you?
You're not the one.
Oh, Sam, she could do
a lot worse, you know.
Couldn't do any better.
Just think, you'll be
establishing a precedent.
I'm not establishing nothing.
I'm going over for some
blueberry muffins and coffee
by her own invitation.
And, possibly, some elderberry wine.
Do you realize that
you'll be the first man to
cross her threshold?
Hmm.
It's not too late, you know.
She's a well-preserved woman.
- I envy you.
- Yes. Very well-preserved.
And preserves have
to be opened someday.
Yes. You just trot down
and see what Mrs. Rogers has to say.
- How about hiding Harry first.
- Holy smoke!
Forgetting a little detail
like that could hang a man.
Oh, I beg your pardon.
I hope I never have to be
operated on by Dr. Greenbow.
- Come on. Let's get going.
- Yeah.
Good afternoon.
You're beautiful, wonderful.
You're the most wonderful,
beautiful thing I've ever seen.
I'd like to paint you.
Is there something else you wanted,
Mr. Marlow, isn't it?
You certainly are a lovely woman.
I'd like to paint you nude.
Some other time, Mr. Marlow.
I was about to make Arnie some lemonade.
Oh, yes, yes, of course.
Perhaps I've come at an awkward moment.
If you want to undress me, you have.
It wasn't exactly that. I came here
to talk to you about something
but after I saw you,
it slipped my mind.
- Couldn't have been very important, then.
- Yes, you're right.
Why don't you sit down on the porch?
I'll get you a lemonade,
and maybe you'll think of it.
You're not only beautiful,
you're considerate, too.
- Arnie!
- Hello, Mr. Marlow.
Hi. What have you got? A rabbit?
Dead. What have you got?
Oh!
I got me a little frog.
There he is.
It's hungry. It needs a mother.
- I'll trade ya.
- Your mother for mine?
- The rabbit for the frog.
- It's yours, Arnie.
I think you got the best deal.
Dead rabbits don't eat.
I'll just take it in the kitchen
and give him some lemonade.
Four rabbits' feet, and he got killed.
He should have carried
a four-leaf clover, too.
And a horseshoe.
Say, how do rabbits get to be born?
- Same way elephants do.
- Oh, sure.
How come you never came over
to visit me before?
Didn't know you had
such a pretty mother, Arnie.
If you think she's pretty,
you should see my slingshot.
- Hmm. Perhaps I'll come back tomorrow.
- When's that?
Day after today.
That's yesterday. Today's tomorrow.
It was?
When was tomorrow yesterday,
Mr. Marlow?
- Today.
- Oh, sure. Yesterday.
You'll never make sense out of Arnie.
He's got his own timing.
- Lemonade, Arnie?
- I already swiped two glasses.
- I would have given you two glasses.
- It's more fun swiped.
- Can I borrow your rabbit, Mr. Marlow?
- Sure, Arnie.
What are you gonna do with it?
You never know when
a dead rabbit might come in handy.
It already got me one frog.
Arnie, where you going now?
To make some more trades.
- Arnie, come home in time for supper.
- I'll try.
What's your given name? If you don't want
to tell me, just make one up.
Jennifer. Jennifer Rogers.
Nice.
Um...
Who's the man up on the path?
- What man?
- You know, Harry, the dead man.
Oh, him. That's my husband.
Your husband's dead, then?
Is your lemonade sweet enough?
- Seems to be.
- I like it tart.
Harry is Arnie's father then?
- No, Arnie's father's dead.
- So is Harry.
Thank goodness.
He was too good to live.
From his looks, he didn't appear
to be the kind that was "too good."
Well, he was. Horribly good.
I like your mouth, too.
Especially when you say "good."
- Will you have some more lemonade?
- Maybe later. Thanks.
Where'd Arnie get the rabbit?
He found it. I think
Captain Wiles shot it.
I'd like to hear more of your life story,
if you don't mind.
You see, we don't know
quite what to do with Harry.
Thought you might
have some suggestions.
You can stuff him, for all I care.
Stuff him and put him in a glass case.
Only I'd suggest frosted glass.
What did he do to you,
besides marry you?
Look. I've wanted to explain
about Harry a lot of times.
Nobody would understand,
least of all Harry.
But you, you've got an artistic mind.
You can see the finer things.
When I'm lucky. Go on.
Tell me everything.
Let it all out.
It was a long time ago,
and I was in love.
- I was too much in love.
- What was his name?
Robert.
We'd agreed to overlook each other's families
and everything and get married.
Did you?
Oh, yes.
And then Robert got killed.
Oh?
I was heartbroken
for six weeks, and then I discovered
little Arnie was on the way.
- Must have been a shock.
- That's where Harry came in.
Harry the handsome hero.
Harry the saint. Harry the good.
- I didn't catch his last name.
- Harry Worp.
Robert's brother. His older brother.
And he fell in love with you?
If he'd fallen in love with me,
I wouldn't have minded.
He wanted to marry me because
he was Robert's brother and felt noble.
But you thought he was
in love with you.
And I decided to let him
love me because of Arnie.
It was on my second wedding night
that I learned the truth.
You didn't learn on your first?
This was a terrible truth.
The truth about Harry.
Just what happened?
How old are you, Mr. Marlow?
About thirty.
This is what happened.
I was in the hotel room alone.
I put on my best nightie.
You understand?
Perfectly.
Although I had
no true feeling for Harry,
I had worked myself
into a certain enthusiasm
because I thought he loved me.
Must have been hard work.
There was a full moon,
and I sat by the window
because I thought it would show off
my new nightie to advantage.
Naturally.
I don't know why
I'm telling you all this.
You, a perfect stranger, too.
I'm not boring you, am I?
No, no, not at all.
- How about some more lemonade?
- Soon.
Where was I?
You were sitting by the window
because it was a full moon
and you'd worked yourself up
to a certain enthusiasm?
I said all that?
When does Harry come in?
He doesn't. He never came in.
He called the following morning.
The following morning?
In the hotel lobby the night before,
he had bought a magazine.
- His horoscope was in it.
- Bad?
It said... He was a Taurus.
It said, "Don't start
any new project that day.
"It could never be finished."
And what did you do?
I left him on the spot
and went home to Mother's.
The end.
What a poignant story.
I knew you'd understand.
Nobody else does.
Not even Mother?
Well, she thought I should live
with him, but I wouldn't.
He pestered me to go back,
but I always refused.
Suppose some night
I wanted him to do something.
Like the dishes, for example.
His horoscope just wouldn't let him.
You're absolutely right.
There are some things I just
don't like to do by myself.
And no one with any true understanding
would blame you for it.
Soon as Arnie was born
I moved away to where I thought
Harry could never find me.
I changed my name and...
But he was persistent?
This morning there was a knock
on the door.
Before I opened it, I knew
he was standing on the other side.
- What did he want?
- Me.
He wanted me because I was his wife.
He wanted me because,
as he put it, he suddenly felt
some basic urge. Loneliness.
What did you feel?
I felt sick.
Did you see his mustache
and his wavy hair?
When I saw him, he was dead.
He looked the same when he was alive,
except he was vertical.
So he entered. What did you say?
Nothing. I hit him over the head
with a milk bottle and knocked him silly.
Silly?
Bats. Tappy.
He went staggering up towards the woods
saying he was gonna find his wife
and drag her home if it killed him.
Apparently it did.
Have some more lemonade.
Why, Captain Wiles, what a surprise.
But you invited me, Miss Gravely.
At least, that's how I remember it.
Of course I did, Captain,
but somehow it's still a surprise.
Yeah.
You certainly know
how to make a man feel wanted.
Won't you come in, Captain?
Thank you. I've looked forward to it.
Takes a real cook to make
a good blueberry muffin
to keep the blueberries
from sitting on the bottom.
High-bush blueberries.
That's the secret.
I picked them up near where you shot
that unfortunate man.
A real, handsome, man's cup.
It's been in the family for years.
My father always used it,
up until he died.
I trust he died peacefully,
slipped away in the night?
He was caught in a threshing machine.
I hope I haven't
distressed you, Captain.
Not at all, Miss Gravely. Not at all.
I'm used to looking
on the rough side of things.
I'm a man who's faced death many times.
Rather recently, too.
Yes.
Arnie, what are you carrying there?
A rabbit.
A rabbit?
- What do you call it?
- Dead.
- It ain't mine.
- Whose is it?
Yours. You shot it with your gun.
You must have killed it today.
It should make a nice stew for you.
A rabbit! I finally killed a rabbit!
- Where did you find it?
- In the blueberry muffins.
- What?
- Out in the woods.
Here you are. One muffin for one rabbit.
Fair enough?
That was a two-muffin rabbit.
- I gotta go now.
- Oh.
Mmm...
It's certainly a nice
afternoon, Miss Gravely.
Isn't it.
Yes, and you're a nice woman.
And I think you're awfully nice,
Captain Wiles.
Um... Let's get back
to our little problem. Harry.
What's going to become of him?
Oh, now, now,
don't you worry about Harry.
He'll be comfortably
underground before nightfall.
All that digging and work.
Couldn't you just let him slide
off the end of your boat pier
into the pond?
And have him pop up like a cork?
No, sir. Nobody ever popped up
from under four feet of ground.
No. Besides, they'll be cutting ice
there this winter.
Now, wouldn't it be a nice thing
if they were cutting
blocks of ice and...
Never mind, Captain. You're right.
Yes, underground
is the best place for Harry.
He seems comfortable, Sam.
Very comfortable and snug.
We'd better find a place and
get it dug, and the sooner the better.
If what you're telling me about Mrs. Rogers
and her husband is right,
I agree with you, Sammy.
Let's find a place.
No use making hard work out of it.
We need a place where
the earth is soft.
Yeah, and a place where the whole town
won't stumble over us as we work.
A place with a certain character
and attractiveness.
Facing west, so that Harry
can watch the setting sun.
- Where it'll be cozy in winter.
- And cool in the summer.
You know, I'm half envying Harry.
Wouldn't take much longer
to dig it twice as wide.
Thanks for your kindness,
but some other time.
- This looks like a good place.
- Ah!
You're a lucky fellow, Harry Worp.
- Come on, Captain, off with your coat.
- Who, me?
Certainly you.
It's your body, isn't it?
I'm not much of a hand
at grave-digging.
You should have thought of that
before you went hunting this morning.
Calvin Wiggs. What do we do now?
Think up the best story
he's ever heard.
Lay down your shovel, Sam.
What's the trouble?
I'm dead beat.
Good. I was dead beat ten minutes ago.
I wanted to keep digging
until you gave up.
Gives me the creeps.
What? Come on.
Let's get Harry and pop him in.
With hasty reverence.
Would you like to say
a few words, Captain?
That I would. Harry Worp, don't ever
show your face around here again.
Let's finish this job
and get out of here.