[music]
before we begin, it seems right to me
to make some digression ,
today’s conversation was born out of
a failed dispute with many
Russian philologists, translators
and literary critics
who are accustomed to putting Don Quixote and
Odysseus on the same level, talking about them separated by
commas kk2
cunning wanderers, it seems to me
that such a comparison is not only
superficial, but it also refers to
comparisons of the kind that can
offend and outrage both
participants at once
, like how can I even be compared with
this? as if Brodsky is compared to
Yevtushenko
or Nabokov with Dostoevsky, of course
Odysseus and Quixote are doomed
to be side by side because they
personify the two main wanderings
of European literature;
however, in their case, behind the only form,
the opposite of content is hidden;
Don Quixote is not only not
the heir
or reincarnation of Odysseus; a subtle move
in almost everything anti-odyssey,
this is exactly what we will talk about today; my
name is Armen Zakharyan and this is literature-
centric channel Armena Fedor here
for our narrow circle to calm down and become and
the odyssey of stalemates today we will encounter
real magic
we will try to be transported to the
only place where they could
meet and imagine what this meeting
could be like
earlier I have already spoken separately about each of
them on the channel there is an episode about what it
means to be
an Odysseus and what it means to be Don Quixote
so if you want to get
the maximum and aesthetic pleasure
from our conversation today
, then I recommend listening to them first and
so Don Quixote and odyssey
it would be wrong to deny that there are a number of
obvious signs that
unite them they are both warriors Odysseus the king and
the leader of the army under Troy
Don Quixote the knight both constantly
find themselves in difficult situations and are looking for
a way out of them both heroes are acting
they are not satisfied with the status quo they actively
influence the world around them finally both
were nicknamed cunning but this
coincidence is observed only in their
Russian incarnations in the native language
of Cervantes Don Quixote is always inha news y is
cunning while odyssey,
even in the text itself, Quixote is prudent and
sane in a word, all these coincidences are
nothing more than the similarity of costume, the main thing
that unites Odyssey and Don Quixote is that they
wander, they are in constant
motion
, but it is from this similarity that
the essential differences begin. Do you know why
the famous hobbit Bilbo Baggins from
Tolkien’s fairy tale cannot be put on a
par with Odysseus
and Quixote because his story is about
back and forth
Don Quixote is only there Odysseus is always
back the whole meaning of Odysseus's journey
returning home
is what the Greeks called the word but stos
is the essence of Quixote's movement is exactly
the opposite, he strives to escape from
home to go out into the world to go as far as possible
in this sense Don Quixote chooses what
the same Greeks called koleos words and
contrasted the nose with tus to return,
that is, Odysseus and Quixote both move but
in opposite directions directions, so
from the very beginning they turn out
to face each other with
the same force of movement but with different
vectors and its applications they come closer,
however, if Don Quixote prances from point a
to point b,
Odysseus at the same time sails from
point b to point and what will happen
is true, sooner or later they will meet and
we even know where, but it will be later, but
for now at the very start, at the maximum
distance from each other, Quixote and Odysseus
most of all look like they are both sitting
in captivity one on the island of the calypso nymphs,
the other in his house, endlessly
reading chivalric novels, however, even
the mouth of their imprisonment is already different, Odysseus
languishes with his body, Don Quixote, with his mind, and so
how opposites attract, he
begins to push them towards each other and
the more they get closer, the less
they have in common Don Quixote is extremely serious
in everything he does and therefore
he is endlessly funny two long there and
everyone makes fun of him
one of the heroes will say the benefits of Don
Quixote his sanity cannot be
compared with the pleasures
that his extravagance gives
Odysseus often makes fun of
those around him,
but don’t let Zeus, someone jokes about
him Don Quixote beats him all the time
, throws stones at him, puts him in a cage and
repeatedly beats him, scratching
his face
, and in one of the episodes he is practically
crucified on a cross.
Odysseus is invulnerable, he ends up in the cave
of the Cyclops, passes between Scylla and
Charybdis, is shipwrecked, loses
companion after satellite, but emerges from
the waters raised by Poseidon relatively
dry. at the decisive moment, no one
manages to not only beat him
, but at least to hit him, Don Quixote
is gullible, he is always deceived,
he is constantly lied to, he is endlessly
manipulated for the amusement of the public,
Odysseus is careful and prudent, he does not
trust anyone, moreover, he deceives
everyone
, he lies, he pretends to get out and
mimics
the naive Don Quixote will one day say that it is impossible
and should not be called deception for what
has a good goal for Odysseus, the goal
always justifies the means, the move
is self-confident and arrogant, up to a certain
point,
doubts are completely alien to him, Odysseus
is arrogant, but in general he
assesses himself and his strength much more soberly,
he tends to doubt
from this sobriety of Odysseus and the arrogance
of Quixote, another difference arises from
Odysseus’s extremely down-to-earth move
, extremely exalted, he is still a knight, he
talks about the honor of valor and courage,
of course his courage is most often
ridiculous, but he truly enters
a cage with lions Odysseus
speaks much more often about Homer's stomach throughout the entire
Iliad; all the heroes together mention
the power of the stomach over a person less often than
Odysseus alone does in
his personal and mass.
Each time the tirade of the stomach begins with
the fact that suffering is, of course, terrible and
ends with the fact that
but there is nothing more vile than our terrible
stomach and it would be nice to have a snack.
The main irony of this comparison, of course,
is that Odysseus here is not just an anti-
Quixote who fasts and eats wild
acorns odyssey here flights Sancho
Panza
don Quixote is a very bad strategist as
a boss he is a real disaster under
his leadership Sancho
who dreamed of becoming a governor become
a complete laughing stock Odysseus
a born military commanders
are charismatic and calculating and cruel under
such leadership and death is red
with Odysseus's leg smart Don Quixote madman
Odysseus king Don Quixote holy fool Odysseus
the Old Testament god the punisher Don Quixote
of the New Testament Christs
[music]
being complete opposites
they come to the same point We were not
warned about this in school textbooks
, but the route from a to b and back
goes through hell and Odysseus and Don Quixote
descend into the afterlife and this is of course
the only possible one. meetings on their
route
for Odysseus is a descent into the kingdom
of the dead before Don Quixote, a descent into the
Montesinos cave, but even in this the heroes remain
themselves, Odysseus sets off involuntarily
because he is not offered any other
means to achieve the desired goal
when he learns about the need
to go to the underworld, his
reaction is described by Homer, how long
he rolled in bed and cried, and
the first question after the sobs was: who
is Don Quixote taking me there?
descends into the Montesinos cave
voluntarily without accompaniment and
preconditions because those
move considers himself a hero and the hero faces
a test
just before the descent, he notices that
they forgot to take the bell
with which they could have signaled upward
and this is an excellent reason to postpone
the adventure
but the knights do not retreat the meeting must
happen and Quixote descends into the cave
and then the most terrible thing happens
Odysseus they come according to all the calculations according to
the logic of events in the inheritance of
heroic experience he should have been
there but Odysseus a practical man he
goes to the kingdom of the dead for
divination by them the elders Theresa the madman
Quixote is not interested in him
at the bottom of a damp cave in the impenetrable darkness
the knight is left alone it is then that
for the first time he encounters his own
disbelief his own madness standing in
the pitch darkness food repair sine Quixote
will think
if there is no Odysseus here then maybe
everything else castles and giants
princesses and islands were not in
the afterlife point either crossing their routes,
Odysseus boldly turns his ship
to meet new challenges, leaving the
worst behind,
nothing has changed for him, because Hades
is material to Odysseus
and the most rational thing now is to just
continue to stick to his plan
so that he doesn’t have to go through anything good
for the second time,
but what’s good for Odysseus is death for Quixote, and
after passing this point of not meeting,
he begins to doubt and
spots of common sense appear in the picture of his fantasy
, destructive for a madman,
Quixote now begins to mark time
with increasing peering into himself with fear
, his journey becomes a wandering
through those nooks and crannies of consciousness
where he shouldn’t look at all
now their paths will never
cross again, each leaves his
afterlife kingdom renewed and goes on
his way, the odyssey awaits new
trials ahead
, but after the triumphant return of a faithful
wife,
a loving son and reprisal against his enemies, but
Don Quixote will end his journey as a knight
who called himself reckless and
daring, who spoke about himself.
stood up for the humiliated and straightened out
the wrongs, coral, audacity, convinced giants
and trampled on monsters, and there is no feat that
exceeds human capabilities
that I would not accomplish,
this daring madman will end
his journey with perhaps the saddest assessment
that he could come,
I don’t know for sure if I’m good, one thing I can
say is that I
was not bad with you Armen Zakharyan
until next time
[music]