Yura is canceled Hello everyone My name is
Armen Zakharyan you are on the literary channel
Armen and Fedor and we have a certain
situation in an interview with Yuri Dudy I
offered my list of ten texts
that I would recommend
aliens to read if they visited us
with their attention Dante ST Chekhov James
Joyce several times I later
regretted it many people noticed that
all this classic
ten Cervantes and so on consisted
exclusively of men so say no
more, let’s balance this
out for the aliens, only this
time these are exclusively books written
by women. Of course, we will begin to introduce
aliens to the beautiful Japanese
novel monogatari, a story created by
Murasaki Shibu at the end of the beginning of the century.
The history of the ganzi is not just a love
search and the machinations of no. This is a complex
Labyrinth of self-knowledge and an irresistible
desire for beauty through this book,
aliens will be able to learn this
human quality as the desire for
external and internal harmony is just as
desirable. How difficult it is to achieve from
harmony and order we move from harmony and order to their complete
opposite to passions and chaos with
them dear aliens Let them
introduce the novel Wuthering Heights by Emily
Brontë this is a book about the Storm that rises
in the human soul and spills out
outward a book about the inexorable force of passion
this is a novel that first of all will scare
the aliens with these wild heathcliff
branching linto us and a lot of media with Kat
us and Katie whoever read it will not forget And whoever
hasn’t read it, correct this omission and
secondly, explain to them that a person can
sometimes be flooded with emotions and that
you can be at enmity not only with others but
also with yourself, then we
will go with the aliens to my beloved
15th century, I couldn’t really
miss it so that they read the collection
of short stories Heptameron by Margarita Vars
Margarita of Navarre the king's sister
Francis Pe is one of the most prominent
representatives of the ideas of humanism in
France, an outstanding woman who
patronized writers and poets and
wrote herself an e-meron consisting of knives
for aliens on how to reconcile
the man of the Universe Murasaki Kibu
striving for order and the man
of the Universe Emily Brontë striving for
chaos because the short stories of Margarita
Novars explore the boundaries of human
morality truth and deception righteousness and
Temptation Our next stop is after
4 Centuries and thousands of kilometers in New
Zealand where We will introduce aliens to
Rin and E’s stories of
a garden party and many others through
its heroes and plots. It would seem so
everyday and simple, we will show
aliens how even the most fleeting
experiences can reveal the complex
inner world of a person, we will show how
the most fragile and simple moments
turn out to be infinitely valuable, we will show
that a person is not only scope and
daring, but also cooling down on table,
a cup of tea in the house of a lonely elderly
woman
, then we
were taken aback by a leap to the other
extreme and from the subtle mental states
of Field's heroes, let's turn to the thundering
questions that
Mary Shelley poses to her readers, I insist that
her Frankenstein is one of
the main books in the history of literature because
never before her the question of
the responsibility of the creator for the happiness
of his creation was raised so
acutely this book will help us tell
aliens about the moral choice in
the face of progress will help warn what
if they suddenly decide to deal with us
, they should weigh this decision up to
seven times, because even creating
a person from dust and ashes is easier than making
a person
happy and again a jump in time and
we find ourselves in a century where we meet with
a completely unique work
of world literature, one of the first, if
not the first, psychological Novel in
prose stories, of course, about the Princess
of Cool Marie Madeleine de Lafette This is not
just a whole world of spiritual doubts and
experiences in which honor and duty
come between love and personal happiness
, but also an opportunity to show
aliens how sometimes behind the brilliance
of external virtue hides a complex and
suffering
soul, well, we are talking about duty, then it’s time
to introduce our dear aliens to
Jane Austen and let the amazing and
harmonious world of her Novels open to them
through the gates of the field park, firstly, then they
will be able to know the boundaries of external and
internal freedom and how a person
probes them in the struggle for the right to
his own happiness, and secondly, they
will see that a person is sometimes capable
of overcoming any obstacles
with his moral fortitude,
since if there is
an unshakable moral imperative in world
literature , it is the imperative of the name of Jane
Austen. With this, we are almost saying goodbye to
the previous centuries, for the last three
books will take us back to the century I would
advise dear ones for aliens
to read the poetry of the glory of Szymborski
ste observes itself as its
complex nature is reflected in the simplicity
of life, the poetry of ShIM Borska would show
aliens that very often
a person’s understanding of the world is nothing more than a set
of questions To which there cannot be and
never will be
an answer, and another poetess on this list,
however, she asked to call herself a poet
Cozy
le 37 I will choose the sun, not poetry, but I will do it
for someone may have a non-obvious choice in
favor of the Tale of Sonechka I really
want to introduce aliens to what
love is pure crazy
fascinating flowing musical
laughing crying parting
short-term eternal Impossible and without
which
it is impossible internet sweat and
they will feel they can preserve our species because with all
our shortcomings we are sometimes capable
of such a high, aching feeling and among
us, when would you know from what Sora
Tsvetaeva is born
finally Let this the top ten
is crowned by my favorite writer, one of
the pearls of English modernism,
the brilliant Virginia, here it
is extremely difficult for me to make a choice and
I would like to give the aliens a complete
collection of her works, including the incredibly
touching Diaries, but for the sake of
the purity of the experiment, let’s stop at
one novel and Let it be a lighthouse,
this is the deepest study of the nature of
time of our earthly time, the
very one with which the aliens will have
to deal here. The case is a spontaneous, torn,
fragmentary story that carries away you
through the years and memories to distant
familiar shores where you, nevertheless,
have never been,
this book will help aliens understand
how human experience can be
multidimensional, how it can be composed of
a mosaic of feelings and thoughts where the movements
of the soul exist simultaneously in
time and in
eternity, on this philosophical note,
finally loading the aliens again
with an overly complex list of literature, and
this was precisely the main complaint
of the broad masses to
our previous alien experience, we would have to
say goodbye But here we are the time is coming
Postscript of the bonus book and for
this purpose I have prepared
a surprise for the aliens, an essay
from 1405, think about it, this is the very beginning of the 15th
century, an essay by Franco by the Italian
writer Christina of Pisa, this is
a book about the city of women, a literary and
philosophical text in which Christina
of Pisa responded to the rude and
unfair accusations
of male writers of her and previous eras
and created an alternative world, a world where
women are guaranteed dignity and
respect where they have the inalienable
right to one’s own voice in a book about
the city of women Christina Pizanskaya raised
the question of the contribution of women to culture and
social order more than 600 years
ago, she created this text with the goal of
inspiring and supporting the women
of her
time. I think that aliens will be able
to find in her book many questions that
remain relevant to this day
. Well,
this is
the list I came up with. I understand that many may be
disappointed, they say, why
did
n’t you answer
anything, Armen
? on the contrary, you want to defend
your top ten and speculate about why
your choice was impeccable and so
on and so forth Lord, this is
an endless word bni on which
our century stands, but even though I am simple-minded
that Sancho the writer would rather go to
heaven than Sancho the commentator So, with
your permission, not to make excuses,
I won’t defend myself and I won’t even attack,
but I will only be glad that this
discussion allowed us
to meet again and talk about important things about
literature So, dear ones aliens
It would be better if you hurry up because we
are waiting for you, we now have a list of
music tracks from the beautiful Anya
Vilna and two whole lists of literature
, and Armen and Fyodor are not the time to relax,
because there are a total of 22 books
that you have to work on carefully,
you
have it, and with you, dear friends, Armen
Zakharyan and the literary channel Armen and
Fyodor, see you next
[music]
meeting N