But the need to fill the void
in its place—it lingers. And
while another of Dostoevsky's protagonists in the same
"The Demons" declares, "If there is no God, then what
kind of captain am I?", Kirillov counters with
"If there is no God, then I can assume his
place."
Remember, Grebenshchikov sang: "Do you feel
the draft because that place is vacant?"
Kirillov feels precisely that draft, and
he formulates a terrifying, insane thought, one
that he subsequently falls in love with: if
a person, he says, dares to assert their
will—not out of anger, fear,
or spite, but simply
because they have the right to—and departs from life,
then, Kirillov contends, this act
will transform all of humanity, and he himself will become
the God of humanity.
Step by step, all of humanity and each individual will become
God.
"But there have already been millions of suicides,"
they tell him. "Not for that reason,
with fear and not for this purpose,"
Kirillov retorts. His insane approach
remarkably resembles an episode from "
Don Quixote." Remember when Sancho Panza
boldly remarks from a distance that he
plans to emulate the illustrious knights
of the past by going mad.
The pragmatic Sancho then asks: "But
do you have a reason to go mad,
Señor? What's the reason?"
"That's the whole point," Don Quixote replies,
"the peculiarity of my enterprise lies in that.
If a knight-errant went mad for
some reason, don't ask for any reward or gratitude;
the trick is to go insane
for no reason at all!"
Did the knight errant go mad for some reason?
He never sought reward or gratitude.
The essence lies in
going insane without any cause.
And as we will soon see,
these resonances in the
words of Kirillov and Quixote are anything but coincidental.