But the need to fill the void
in its place remains. And while
another of Dostoevsky's characters
in "Demons" says, "If there is no God,
then what kind of captain am I after that?"
Kirillov says, "If there is no God,
then I can take His place."
Remember, Grebenshchikov sang: "You feel
the draft because that place is vacant."
Kirillov senses that very draft, and
he formulates a terrifying, mad idea,
which he then falls in love with: "If a person,"
he says, "decides to assert his will
and simply ends his life, not out of anger,
fear, or malice, but precisely because
he has the right, then," Kirillov argues,
"with this step, he will regenerate
all of humanity and himself become
man's God."
As all humanity steps forward — one itself will become
God to man
But they tell him, there have already been millions of suicides
yet still no
fear, and not for that reason, Kirillov objects
and his mad approach surprisingly
resembles an episode from 'Don Quixote'.
Remember, when daring and far, says Sancho Panza,
who plans to emulate the glorious knights
of the past and go mad.
The pragmatic Sancho then asks:
'And do you have a reason to go mad,
señor?'. What's the reason?
That’s the crux of it, replies Don Quixote.
That’s the very peculiarity
of my intended enterprise.
Whoever among the knight-errants
went mad for some reason
should ask neither for a
reward nor gratitude.
The knight, for some reason, went mad.
He does not seek rewards or gratitude:
the whole point is to
go mad without any reason.
And, as we will soon see,
these echoes in the words of Kirillov
and Quixote are far from accidental.