[Music] Before we begin, it seems appropriate to make a diversion.
Today's discussion stemmed from an unmaterialized debate with many Russian philologists, translators, and literary critics, who are accustomed to placing Don Quixote and Odysseus on the same level, talking about them
in the same breath, as cunning wanderers. It seems to me,
that such a comparison is not only superficial, but it is also of the sort that can insult and outrage both participants, as if to say, how can I even be compared to that? It’s like comparing Brodsky with
Yevtushenko or Nabokov with Dostoevsky. Of course,
Odysseus and Quixote are destined to be seen together because they embody two major journeys of European literature.
However, in their case, beneath the unity of form lies a contentual opposition.
Don Quixote is not just not a successor or reincarnation of Odysseus; Don Quixote, in almost all respects, is the anti-Odysseus. This is precisely what we shall discuss today.
My name is Armen Zakharian, and you're watching the literature-centric channel "Armen and Fyodor". Here
in our close circle, we set Don Quixote and Odysseus against each other. Today we will encounter real magic.
We will attempt to transfer ourselves to the only place they could meet and imagine what that meeting might have been like.
Previously, I have talked about each of them separately: there are episodes on the channel about what it means to be an Odysseus and what it means to be a Don Quixote. So if you want to get
the maximal aesthetic pleasure from our conversation today, I recommend listening to those first.
So, Don Quixote and Odysseus. It would be wrong to deny that there are a number of obvious features that unite them. They are both warriors: Odysseus — a king,
leader of the army at Troy, Don Quixote — a knight. Both constantly find themselves in difficult situations and seek a way out. Both are heroes acting,
they refuse to accept the status quo, they affect the world around them. Finally, both
have been dubbed ingenious, but this coincidence is observed only in their Russian incarnations. In their original tongues
Don Quixote is "ingenioso", ingenious, whereas Odysseus — even in the text of Quixote itself — is "prudente", sensible. In a word, all these coincidences
are no more than similarities of costume. The main thing that unites Odysseus and Don Quixote is the wandering, the constant movement.
But it is from this similarity that significant differences arise. Do you know why
famous hobbit Bilbo Baggins from Tolkien's tale cannot be placed in the same category with Odysseus and Quixote? Because his story is there and back again.
Don Quixote is only there, Odysseus — back. The whole meaning of Odysseus's journey is the return home, which is what the Greeks called "nostos". The essence
of Quixote's movement is quite the opposite — he seeks to break free from his home, to get out into the world, to go as far as possible. In this sense, Don Quixote chooses what
the same Greeks called "kóleos" and opposed to "nostos", the return. So Odysseus and Quixote both are in motion,
but in opposite directions. Thus,
from the very beginning they find themselves facing each other with the same strength of movement but different application vectors. They converge, yet
if Don Quixote is galloping from point A to point B,
Odysseus at this time is sailing from point B to point A. What will happen? Something is certain — sooner
or later they will meet, and we even know where. But this will be later,
while at the very start, at the maximum distance from each other, Quixote and Odysseus are most alike. They both sit
in captivity: one on the island of the nymph Calypso, the other in his home behind the endless reading of knightly novels. However, even
the nature of their captivity is already different: Odysseus is tormented physically, Don Quixote mentally. Thus,
as opposites attract, they are propelled towards one another.
The closer they come, the less they have in common. Don Quixote is extremely serious
in everything he does and therefore infinitely comical. In the end, where everyone
makes fun of him, one of the characters will say: the benefit of Quixote and his reason cannot compare to the pleasure his folly brings.
Odysseus often jokes at others' expense, but heaven forbid anyone else jokes about him. Don Quixote is constantly beaten,
pelted with stones, caged, repeatedly thrashed, his face scratched, and in one episode, he is almost crucified.
Odysseus, however, is invulnerable — he enters the Cyclops' cave, sails between Scylla and Charybdis, survives a shipwreck, losing companion after companion, but emerges from Poseidon's stirred waters relatively untouched. At decisive moments, no one can
even touch him, let alone beat him. Don
Quixote is gullible, perpetually deceived, lied to, and endlessly manipulated for public amusement. Odysseus is cautious and calculating; he
trusts no one; moreover, he deceives everyone, lies, feigns, twists the truth, and blends in.
Naive Don Quixote once said: one cannot and should not call deception that which has a noble goal. For Odysseus, the end always justifies the means. Quixote
is self-assured and arrogant to a certain point,
completely free of doubt. Odysseus might be arrogant, but generally, he evaluates himself and his capabilities more soberly, and has the tendency to doubt.
From this sobriety of Odysseus and the arrogance of Quixote comes another difference.
Odysseus is extremely grounded, Quixote extremely lofty. He is, after all, a knight,
speaks of honor, valor, and bravery. Of course, his courage is more often
laughable, but he really does step into the cage with lions. Odysseus, however,
talks far more often about the stomach: throughout all of the Iliad, all the heroes combined mention the stomach's power over man less frequently than Odysseus does in
his personal epic.
Each tirade about the stomach begins with "that suffering is of course terrible," and ends with "there is nothing baser than our awful stomach" and "it would be nice to have a bite to eat."
The main irony of this comparison, of course, is that Odysseus here is not just the anti-Quixote, who fasts and feeds on wild acorns. Odysseus here is the spitting image of Sancho
Panza. Don Quixote is a very poor strategist. As
a leader, he is a real catastrophe — under his command, Sancho, who dreamed of becoming a governor, becomes a laughingstock. Odysseus
is a leader: charismatic, calculating, and ruthless. Under such command, even death is glorious. Odysseus is wise, Don Quixote is mad.
Odyssey is a king, Don Quixote is a holy fool. Odysseus is an Old Testament God-punisher, Don Quixote is a New Testament Christ.
[Music] And so, being complete opposites, they come to a single point. We were not
warned about this in school textbooks, but the route from A to B and back passes through hell. Both Odysseus and Don Quixote
descend into the underworld, and this, of course, is the only possible meeting point on their journey.
For Odysseus, it's a descent into the realm of the dead, for Don Quixote it's a descent into the Cave of Montesinos. Yet, even in this, the heroes remain
themselves. Odysseus goes there unwillingly because he is presented with no other means to reach his desired goal.
When he learns of the need to visit the underworld, Homer describes his reaction as "rolling in bed and weeping," and his first question after his tears was: "And who will guide me there?" Don Quixote, however,
descends into the Cave of Montesinos voluntarily, without escort or preliminaries, because Quixote considers himself a hero, and a hero must face trials.
Just before the descent, he notices that he and Sancho forgot to bring a bell to signal above, an excellent reason to postpone the adventure.
But knights do not retreat — the meeting must occur, and Quixote descends into the cave. And then the most frightening thing happens:
Odysseus does not arrive. According to all calculations, by the logic of events, by the inheritance of heroic experience, he was supposed to be there. But Odysseus is practical, he
goes to the realm of the dead for a prophecy from the old man Tiresias. The mad Quixote does not interest him.
At the bottom of the damp cave, in the pitch darkness, the knight remains alone. It is then that he
first encounters his own disbelief, his own madness. Standing in
total darkness, Quixote wonders: if Odysseus isn’t here, then perhaps none of the rest — the castles and giants, princesses and islands — existed either? In
the afterlife checkpoint of their routes, Odysseus boldly turns his ship towards new trials, having left the worst behind.
For him, nothing has changed — for Hades is tangible to Odysseus, and the most rational thing now is to simply keep following the plan, to avoid unpleasantly having to enter it again.
But what is good for Odysseus spells death for Quixote. And
after passing this point of non-meeting, he begins to doubt, and spots of common sense appear in the tapestry of his imagination, fatal for a madman.
Quixote now begins to tread nervously in place, gazing inward with growing fear.
His journey turns into a wandering of those corners of consciousness he should rather not explore at all.
Now their paths will never cross again: each exits his underworld renewed and proceeds on his own way. Odysseus has new challenges ahead,
but then — a triumphant return, a faithful wife, a loving son, and a reckoning with enemies. But as for
Don Quixote, he will end his path as a knight, calling himself reckless and daring, having said of himself: "I stood up for the humiliated and rectified wrongs, punished insolence, convinced giants, and trod on monsters, and there’s no deed beyond human capabilities that I haven’t accomplished."
This daring madman will end his path with perhaps the saddest assessment he could reach: "I don't know if I'm exactly good,
but I can say I'm not bad." This is Armen Zakharian.
Until next time. [Music].