[music]
at night, somewhere around one o'clock, in a small
provincial town of no particular
named young man of about 27 years old
enter a wooden outbuilding standing alone in the
in the guests to
a civil engineer sitting on a sofa with
a lattice back and hard leather
pillows almost immediately notices that on
the window there is a plate of untouched boiled
chicken
My name is Armen Zakharyan, this is
Armen's literary channel Fedor and
today we are opening a new section
episode in it We will each time
look closely at just one
fragment from the pages of world literature and
to understand Why this episode is special
and how what we call
art works in it and for the first such experience we
chose one of the most creepy But together with
interesting scenes from the novel Demons
Fyodor Dostoevsky this episode is almost
the very end of the book from its
final part there is a certain
Verkhovensky comes at night to the
of a certain Kirillov and sees on the window
boiled with rice chicken
and Although right next to the chicken lies
a loaded pistol, but not it, namely
the chicken plays the role of
Chekhov's gun, which is about to
fire However, to understand what it is
for shot And who is it aimed at?
First, figure out who these two are and how
They were here in the same room at night in
The outbuilding ended up
It's curious how, at the very beginning of the book
Only introducing us to the characters Dostoevsky
Already prepares the ground for this
terrible night meeting Kirillov at his
young man about 27
Verkhovensky almost mirror-young
man about 27 or so
this is a deliberate resemblance Of course only
emphasizes how deep the differences are between them
Kirillov is a bright representative
of the famous series of fanatic heroes
Dostoevsky's heroes who are too
strongly carried away by some idea
begin to serve this idea to live in name
this idea only Kirillov has a different plan
he is going to die in the name of the idea
Kirillov is obsessed with the idea of ​​man God
he comes to it through a problem that
literature of this period of the second half
XIX century often tried to decide how
a person should live after rejecting God
let's say there is no God anymore Let's say we
we no longer believe in him, we
I would say Verkhovensky has been slanted
But the need to be filled with something
emptiness in its place it remained and
while another hero of Dostoevsky in the same
demons says if there is no God then what
after that captain Kirillov says
if there is no God then I can take his
place
remember Grebenshchikov sang you feel
a draft from the fact that this place is free
Kirillov feels that very draft and
he formulates a terrible crazy thought in
which he himself then falls in love with if
the man says he will decide to declare his
will and just like that not from anger or
fear or anger but namely only
because he is right he will leave this life then
he reasons Kirillov will regenerate this
step all of humanity and he himself will become
man God
But there have already been millions of suicides
they tell him but all do not Then all with
fear and not for that Kirillov objects
and this his Crazy approach amazing
reminds one episode from Don
Remember Quixote when the daring and
far away Sancho tells Pansy that he plans
to imitate the glorious knights of the past and
Go crazy
pragmatic Sancho then asks but A
then you have a reason to go crazy
senor the reason is what is all this
the salt is Don Quixote answers in that
and the unusualness of the conceived
my enterprise Who is wandering
knights for some reason went off
mind that not rewards ingratitude not
ask the whole trick is to
go crazy for no reason
And as we will soon see these roll calls in
in the words of Kirillov and Quixote far from
accidentally
So in order to carry out his crazy
idea, Kirillov has a loaded revolver on the window next to the chicken
you can
ask but What is he waiting for then Why
will not carry out his intention since he
precisely because he does not need a reason for this
here his night comes into play
Visitor revolutionary and nihilist Peter
Stepanovich Verkhovensky is a character
completely different amazing hero funny
and scary at the same time comic and
parody terribly talkative and
theatrical But at the same time creepy
because ready for any evil
verkhovensky Yes famous degrees
resembles Mephistopheles only in
Mephistopheles had a better sense of humor And
due to life experience and age, he
was more modest, however, the main thing They
still share Verkhovensky
an extremely practical person He believes
that the end justifies any means and
meeting a sweetheart with his project
ideological suicide Verkhovensky immediately
thinks up how this can be used with
use for the cause No, not for rebirth
of humanity he doesn't believe in it at all
and for his demonic cause he decides
to commit a political murder and once
Kirillov doesn't care at all, just like
when to die then ask him before
to write a confession to this
murder, that is, to use death
Kirillova as an Alibi in her crime
So this is the disposition at
the moment of their night meeting conflict
spiritual Let the sick but spiritual
Don Quixote was also mad and
material conflict of the sublime and
down-to-earth tragic and
pragmatic but how to show in all this
through one single image
and with the help of a chicken
episode as it often happens with
Dostoevsky unfolds
rapidly Verkhovensky Just now
came in just clarified the intention
the stage is almost 30 years old those who
were lucky enough to see this performance
surely remember the scene with
verkhovensky's chicken seeing this Once
it's hard to forget live Look here
fragment how this scene was played
these are illustrations actually it would be possible
to finish the conversation about today's
fragment if not for one detail The point is
that this opposition
refusal to eat gluttony as a metaphor
value conflict met in
one book that Dostoevsky very
loved books that influenced all his
the main texts of the book about which he
said that in the whole world there is no deeper and
stronger than this essay finally books
which we mentioned today of course in
Don Quixote by Cervantes remember how
the relationship between Don Quixote and Sancho is built
panse in the first volume We talked about this
in one of the early issues of Armen and
Fedora dedicated to this novel Sancho
fixated on food he constantly reminds
Quixote about food he at every convenient
case seeks to eat his fill regardless
depending on what he experiences in
this moment his master preaches li
is he fasting or suffering and the Great
American director Orson Welles in
his Don Quixote which by
an amazing coincidence will be released almost
simultaneously with Dodin's play
depict a scene more reminiscent of
this episode from the demons there Sancho Panza on
the eyes of the fasting Quixote will
devour with greed
What do you think
of course it is the chicken
[music]
I want this, that Marina will go
it remains only to stipulate that they want
this episode corresponds to the spirit of Don Quixote Cervantes
corresponds completely to the letter not
in the text of the novel exactly
there was no such scene with the chicken However, this
in the end it is easily explained Cervantes
did not read Dostoevsky, unlike
Orson Welles
this is Armen Fedor's literary channel and
heading episode I hope that our
experiment with this new laconic
format was a success and If so then
write to us in the comments What other
episodes would you like to see in this
heading in the future
but for now this is all My name is Armen Zakharyan
until next time
[music]
our strength I hope from suicide not
we will retreat, we will sign the paper and almost without
pause immediately ba Yes, I notice something there
on the window on a plate He comes to the window
Wow, boiled chicken with rice, but why same
still untouched therefore we
are in such a mood of the Spirit that
even the chicken I ate interrupts him
Kirillov and it is none of your business keep quiet about
of course And besides all the same but for me
then it is not equal now, imagine at all
I hardly had lunch and therefore if now it
I suppose chicken is no longer needed
and Pay attention to how he formulates his
answer Kirillov Eat if you can
Verkhovensky can and can for yourself
because of that guy maybe I thank you
he says and then tea and so on
something even more terrible follows bone
on the cake of this scene Verkhovensky instantly
settled down at the table at the other end
sofa with extreme greed
pounced on the food but at the same time
every moment Kirillov watched his victim
looked at him with malicious disgust
motionless as if unable to tear himself away
Verkhovensky here this is the triumph of the flesh
he eats greedily with appetite and passion because
the man sitting a meter away from him now
will shoot himself but the chicken began to be
vacant
notice in this one paragraph
Verkhovensky takes away from Kirillov
absolutely all his freedom his last
will his last meal and at the end
ends his life
chicken is of course only a metaphor
because in essence verkhovensky
Cannibal people are expendable for him
feeding his pathetic ambitions and terrible
plans Is happiness worth humanity
tears of a child Ivan asks
Karamazov And the child with a side dish or like that
without anything
Pyotr clarifies
and Kirillov, this strange Kirillov, Yes, with
his crazy idea, but still not evil
his heart can't tear itself away, he is horrified
watches Verkhovensky eats
chicken because not only chicken
he eats but also his Kirillov now
will eat
Verkhovensky Barabek ate 40 people and
cow and Bull and Crooked Butcher and cart
and the arc and the broom and the poker ate the chicken with
side dish and finished with this world
and this whole tangle of contradictions of fears
and Dostoevsky shows the fates through
one scene of a meal through one plate
cold chicken with rice
the eloquent horror of this gastronomic
scene was very accurately captured in the legendary
production of the Demons of the Petersburg Small
drama theater in a six-hour
performance by Lvadodin, which was on
the stage is almost 30 years old those who
were lucky enough to see this performance
surely remember the scene with
verkhovensky's chicken seeing this Once
it's hard to forget live Look here
fragment how this scene was played
these are illustrations actually it would be possible
to finish the conversation about today's
fragment if not for one detail The point is
that this opposition
refusal to eat gluttony as a metaphor
value conflict met in
one book that Dostoevsky very
loved books that influenced all his
the main texts of the book about which he
said that in the whole world there is no deeper and
stronger than this essay finally books
which we mentioned today of course in
Don Quixote by Cervantes remember how
the relationship between Don Quixote and Sancho is built
panse in the first volume We talked about this
in one of the early issues of Armen and
Fedora dedicated to this novel Sancho
fixated on food he constantly reminds
Quixote about food he at every convenient
case seeks to eat his fill regardless
depending on what he experiences in
this moment his master preaches li
is he fasting or suffering and the Great
American director Orson Welles in
his Don Quixote which by
an amazing coincidence will be released almost
simultaneously with Dodin's play
depict a scene more reminiscent of
this episode from the demons there Sancho Panza on
the eyes of the fasting Quixote will
devour with greed
What do you think
of course it is the chicken
[music]
I want this, that Marina will go
it remains only to stipulate that they want
this episode corresponds to the spirit of Don Quixote Cervantes
corresponds completely to the letter not
in the text of the novel exactly
there was no such scene with the chicken However, this
in the end it is easily explained Cervantes
did not read Dostoevsky, unlike
Orson Welles
this is Armen Fedor's literary channel and
heading episode I hope that our
experiment with this new laconic
format was a success and If so then
write to us in the comments What other
episodes would you like to see in this
heading in the future
but for now this is all My name is Armen Zakharyan
until next time
[music]